<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno quarto et quinto, Philippi &amp; Mariæ. Actes made at a Parliament begon and holden at Westminster, the .xx daye of January, in the fourth and fift yeare of the reigne of oure soueraigne Lorde and Lady, Philippe and Marye by the grace of God, kinge and Quene of England, Spayne, Fraunce, both the Sicilles, Jerusalem, and Jrelande, defendours of the faith, archidukes of Austria, dukes of Burgondie, Millaine and Brabant, counties of Haspurge, Flaunders, and Tyrol, and there continued and kepte vntyll the vij. day of Marche, then next folowinge, and enacted as foloweth..</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1558</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 248 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B01271</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9457</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S832</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">54532350</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 54532350</idno>
            <idno type="VID">180783</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B01271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 180783)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2134:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno quarto et quinto, Philippi &amp; Mariæ. Actes made at a Parliament begon and holden at Westminster, the .xx daye of January, in the fourth and fift yeare of the reigne of oure soueraigne Lorde and Lady, Philippe and Marye by the grace of God, kinge and Quene of England, Spayne, Fraunce, both the Sicilles, Jerusalem, and Jrelande, defendours of the faith, archidukes of Austria, dukes of Burgondie, Millaine and Brabant, counties of Haspurge, Flaunders, and Tyrol, and there continued and kepte vntyll the vij. day of Marche, then next folowinge, and enacted as foloweth..</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Mary I, Queen of England, 1516-1558.</author>
                  <author>Philip II, King of Spain, 1527-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xli [i.e. 82] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>in aedibus Iohannis Cavvodi Tipographi Regiæ Maiestatis.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. M.D.LVIII. [1558].</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint taken from colophon.</note>
                  <note>"Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis."</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁶ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Title in illustrated border (McK. &amp; Ferg. 81); initials.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: National Library of Wales.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Mary I, 1553-1558 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:180783:1"/>
            <p>
               <date>
                  <hi>Anno quarto et quinto, Philippi &amp; Mariae.</hi>
               </date>
            </p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>Actes</hi> made at a Parliament begon and holden at Weſtminſter, the .xx daye of Ianuary, in the fourth and fift yeare of the reigne of oure ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lorde and Lady, Philippe and Marye by the grace of God, kinge and Quene of England, Spayne, Fraunce, both the Sicilles, Ieruſalem, and Irelande, defendours of the faith Archidukes of Auſtria, Dukes of Burgondie, Millaine and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, counties of Haſpurge Flaunders, and Tyrol, and there continued and kepte vntyll the .vij. day of Marche, then next folow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, and enacted as foloweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maieſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of John Cawood (or Iohannis Cavvodi)</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:180783:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Acte for the confyrmation of letters patentes. Cap. i.</item>
               <item>An acte for the hauynge of Horſe, Armoure, and Weapon. Cap. ii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the takinge of muſters. Cap. iii.</item>
               <item>An acte that acceſſaries in murder and dyuers felonies, ſhall not haue the benefit of clergie. Cap. iiii.</item>
               <item>An acte touchinge the makinge of wollen clothes. Cap. v.</item>
               <item>An acte to enquyre of Frenchemen beynge deniſens. Cap. vi</item>
               <item>An acte to make vp the Iury with circumſtantibus, where the kynge and Quenes maieſties or the Quenes maieſtie is a party. Cap. vii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the puniſhement of ſuche as ſhall take away maydens that be inheritours, beynge within age of .xvi. yeares, or that mary them without the conſent of theyr parents. Cap. viii</item>
               <item>An acte for the continuation of certaine ſtatutes. Cap. ix.</item>
               <item>An acte for the confirmation of the Subſedye of the clergie. Cap. x.</item>
               <item>An acte of a Subſedye and one fyftene graunted by the temporal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Cap. xi.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Act_of_Parliament">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:180783:2"/>
               <head>¶ An Acte for the confirmation of Letters Patentes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE ſythen the .vii. daye of Iulye in the firſt yeare of the Quenes Maieſties reygne dyuers and ſondry Honors, Caſtels, Manoures, Lands, Tenements, Rentes, Reuercions, ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uices, and other hereditamentes, haue bene conueyed and aſſured to her high<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, her heyres and Succeſſoures by or from diuers and ſundrye perſons, &amp; bodies politike, aſwel for the diſcharge and ſatiſfaction of great debtes, and ſummes of monye, as for other good conſiderations. For the perfytte aſſuraunce confirmation and further ſuretye whereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>BE IT</hi> enacted ordeyned and eſtablyſhed by the kyng and Quenes Maieſtyes, the Lordes Spirituall and Temporal, and the commons in thys preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by thaucthoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame. That all Feoffementes, Fynes, Surrenders, aſſuraunces, conueyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and eſtates in any wiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueyed had or made, to or for our ſayd So<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueraygne Lorde and Lady, the kyng and quenes Maieſties, or to or for our ſayde ſoueraygne Lady the quene, by or from anye ſuche perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons, bodies politike or corporate, of any ſuch Honors, caſtels ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noures, La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, Tenements, Rentes, Reuertions, Seruices, or other hereditamentes, for anye debte, ſumme or ſummes of monye or other conſideration, whatſoeuer, ſhall ſtande remayne &amp; be good and auai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leable in the lawe to all intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to the true meanynge, intente and purporte of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAVINGE</hi> to all and euery perſonne and perſonnes, and to their heires bodyes politike and corporate, &amp; to their Succeſſoures, and to euerye of them, (other then ſuch perſon or perſonnes, and their heyres and wyues, and euerye of them bodies politike and corporate, &amp; their ſucceſſoures and euery of them, of or from whome, the kyng &amp; quenes highnes, or the quenes hyghnes onelye hath obteyned or purchaſed, the ſayde premiſſes, or anye percell thereof, by exchaunge, gyfte bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, fyne, Feoffement, recouery, dede, inrolled or otherwiſe) al ſuch right title, intereſt, vſe, poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, rentes, reuercions, Remainders, Olfi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ees, Fees, Commons, profyttes, and commodities, whatſoeuer which they or any of them haue might or ought to haue had of, in or to the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſes or any part thereof in as large and ample maner, forme and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dition to al intentes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtructions and purpoſes, as yf this acte had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer bene had ne made. Thys preſent Acte or any thing therein contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:180783:3"/>to the contrarye notwithſtandynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where aſwell our ſayd ſoueraigne lorde, &amp; Lady, as our ſayde ſoueraigne Lady the Quenes highnes, ſithens the ſaid .vii. day of Iuly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt yere of her maieſties reigne, aſwel for diuers &amp; gret ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of mony, as alſo for diuers &amp; ſondry other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderations, haue, &amp; hath bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gained, ſold, giuen or grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by their or her graces ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dry letters pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts indentures, or other writinges, ſealed vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great ſeale of England, or the ſeale of the Duchy of Lancaſter, aſwel to bodyes politike &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, as to diuers and ſondry other their louing &amp; obedient ſubiects, diuers and ſondry honors, caſtels, manors, landes, tenements, rentes, reuercions, ſeruyces, &amp; other hereditamentes, in fee ſymple, fee tayle, or for terme of lyfe, lyfes or yeares, as in the ſame ſeueral letters patents, indentures, &amp; other wrytynges, is mentioned &amp; declared. And to thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the ſame letters patents, indentures, &amp; other writinges, ſhulde be of good auayleable and perfit force &amp; effect, to al and euery her highnes louyng Subiectes, according to the true meaning &amp; effect of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>OVRE SAIDE</hi> Soueraygne Lorde and Ladye the kynge and Queene, are contented and pleaſed, that it be enacted by thauthoritie of thys preſent parliamente. And therefore by oure ſayd Soueraygne lord, and lady, the kyng and quenes maieſties, the laides ſpiritual and temporal, and the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in this preſent parliamente aſſembled, be it enacted and eſtabliſhed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſwel al and ſinguler letters patents, inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and other writinges Sealed vnder the greate Seale of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, or vnder the Seale of the Duchy of Lancaſter, and heretofore made or graunted by our ſayde ſoueraygne Lord and Lady, the kyng and Quene, or by our ſaid ſoueraigne lady the Quene, for any Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of monye, or for and vpon any other conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, as al other letters pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, hereafter to be made by our ſaide ſoueraigne lorde &amp; ladye, for any ſumme or ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of monye during the ſpace of Seuen yeares next enſuynge the makyng of this acte, to anye body politike, or corporate, or to any other perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſonnes, whatſoeuer, of any honors, caſtels, manors, lordeſhippes, graunges, Meſes, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, tenements, medowes paſtures, rentes, reuercions, ſeruyces, woodes, aduouſons, nominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, patronages, annuities, rightes, intereſtes, entrees, conditions, letes, courtes, liberties, priuileges, fraunchyſes, or of anye other heredi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tamentes, with their appurtenaunces, or of any parte or percell of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſealed with or vnder the great ſeale of Englande, or vnder the Seale of the Duchy of Lancaſter, of whatſoeuer kynde, nature, or qualitye they or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be or ſhalbe reputed knowen or taken, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their appur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenaunces or any part or percel of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhalbe good perfyt and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, and ſhal ſtand, be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reputed, demed, &amp; adiudged good perfit ſure auayleable &amp; effectual in the lawe, aſwel againſt the kynge and Quenes Maieſties, as againſte the queene her heires and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors according to the tenor of the ſaid letters pate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, the ſame to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrued demed &amp; adiudged moſt beneficial for the patentees
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:180783:3"/>and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tees of the ſame, according vnto the wordes &amp; purport of euery the ſaid letters patents, without any confirmation, licence, or tolleration of the quene, her heires or ſucceſſors, any miſnaminge, miſrecital, or non recitall of any the ſame honors, caſtels, maners, landes, teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes &amp; other the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes or any percel therof, or any lacke of fyndinge of offices, or inquiſitions of and in the premiſſes, wherby the title of the Quenes highnes therin oughte to haue ben founde before the makinge of the ſame letters patentes or other writinges, or any miſrecital, or none recitall of leaſes therof before made, as well of record as not of record, or any lacke of the certaintie, miſcaſtinge, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or ſetting forth of the yearly values and rates of the premiſſes, or of the yearly rentes reſerued of &amp; for the premiſſes or any percel therof, mentioned or conteined in any the ſaid letters patentes, or other writinges, or for that the premiſſes be, or any part thereof is valued to a more or leſſe value in the ſayd letters patentes or writinges, then the ſaid manors, landes, tenemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and other the premiſſes, then were or ſhalbe in yearly value, or any miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naming of the townes, Hamlettes, pariſhes, or counties wher the ſame ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Caſtels, manors, landes, tenementes, rentes, hereditamentes, and other the premiſſes and euery percell therof, or any percell therof lien or ben, or any lacke of the true naminge of the landes, tenementes, or hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, or of the natures, kindes, ſortes, or quantities of the ſayde poſſeſſions or hereditamentes or any percell therof, or any lacke of the true naminge of the corporation, or any lacke of atturnement, liuery, or ſeaſon, or any miſnaming of any the late tenauntes or fermours of the ſame ſo ſold or geuen, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſaid, that this acte nor any thinge therin conteyned ſhall not extend to make anye letters patents of any office or offices, to be of any other effect, force, or ſtrength the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame letters patents were or ſhuld haue ben before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> making of this act.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that all and ſinguler ſuche patentees, grauntees, and donees, and euerye of them, whiche at any time heretofore ſithens the ſayd ſeuenth day of Iuly haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned and gotten of our ſayd Soueraigne Lorde and Lady the kyng and Quene or of any of them, or at any time hereafter duryng the ſpace of ſeuen yeares, ſhall obtaine and get of our ſayd Soueraigne lord and lady the king and Quene that nowe be, or of any of them, by way of exchaunge, or for any ſumme or ſummes of monye, any letters patents of any monaſteries, abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, priories, nonneries, or other eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſions, or of any percell of them, or of any other manours Landes Tenementes or Hereditaments whatſoeuer, whiche at the date and makyng of any the ſame letters paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes ſo made, ſithens the ſaide ſeuenth daye of Iulye or hereafter to be made durynge the ſpace of ſeuen yeares as is aforeſayde, were or ſhalbe of better and more yearely valewe to the kynge and Quenes highnes or to anye of them, in yearly rent and ferme, then was, is, or ſhalbe conteined, mentioned or ſpecified in any ſuche letters patentes, or in the perticulers or rate thereof made or to be made by any auditour or auditours, ſurueyour or ſurueyours
<pb facs="tcp:180783:4"/>or other officer, that then euery ſuche patentee, grauntee, and donee, theyr heyres executours or aſſignes and euery of them, within one yeare nerte af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter office and other due profe order and decre therof made and had, or to be made and had within the ſpace and terme of tenne yeares nexte after this preſent parliament in the courte of the eſchequer, ſhall content and paye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the quenes maieſtie her heires and ſucceſſours, for the ſame ouerplus and more value of the ſame monaſteries, abbathies, priories, nonneries, manors landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes whatſoeuer, with their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purtenaunces, ſo ſolde, geuen, graunted, or exchaunged as is aforeſayde, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the rate of twenty yeares purchaſe, and accordinge to the yearely value and rate as the ſame manours, Landes, tenementes, and other heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes whatſoeuer, were at the time of the making of any ſuch letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes ſo made, or to be made in maner &amp; fourme aforeſayd. Any thyng co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in any ſuch letters patentes to the contrary in any wiſe notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alſo and be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that this acte or any prouiſion therein conteyned, ſhall not in any wyſe extend to confyrme, ratifie, or make good anye leaſe or leaſes, made or to be made by our ſayde Soueraigne Lorde and Lady the kynge and Quene, or by anye of them for terme of life, lifes, or for yeares, wherevpon the olde and accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med rentes or more, be not, or hereafter ſhall not be reſerued, and yearelye payable duringe the tyme and terme of euerye ſuche leaſe, nor that this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente acte ſhall in any wyſe extende to reuiue or make good anye letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes made of any office or offices to anye comptroller, cuſtomer, alneger, ſercher ne to anye letters patentes of the graunte of any other office or offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces heretofore graunted or made by the kinge and Quenes maieſtie, or any of them, whiche nowe be or at anye tune heretofore haue ben adnichilated, determined or made voide by iudgement, by auctoritie of parliament, or by decree, nor to anye patent to be made to anye perſon or perſons for terme of yeares, or during y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minoritie of any heyre of any manours Landes or tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, whereof any trauerſe hereafter ſhalbe tendred within three mone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes after any office founde and certified into anye of the kinges courtes of recorde, ne to make good anye letters patentes made by oure layde Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne lorde and Ladye or any of them, of anye office or offices to be of anye other effecte force or ſtrength then the ſame letters patentes were or ſhould haue bene before the makinge of this Acte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that this acte or any thinge therin conteined, ſhall not extende to any letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes whiche at any tyme heretofore ſithen the beginninge of the Quenes maieſties reigne haue ben made or hereafter ſhalbe made by the kynge and quenes highnes, or by the quenes maieſtie onely, to any perſon or perſonnes of any manours Landes, tenementes, rentes, reuercions, ſeruices, or other hereditamentes, by force of any information, ſuite, or ſuggeſtion, made, or to be made to her highnes, that the ſame manoures, landes, tenementes, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hereditamentes, ſo conteyned in any ſuche letters patentes, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed landes, nor to any letters patentes heretofore made by our ſayde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne Lorde and lady the kinge and Quenes maieſties, or any of them,
<pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:180783:4"/>to Rauſe Iackſon clerke, nowe maiſter of the hoſpitall of the Sauoye in the pariſhe of Saint Clementes Dacorum, without the barres of the new tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple London, and to his brethren, beyng perpetuall Chaplaynes of the ſame Hoſpitall, and to theyr ſucceſſoures, but that the ſame letters patentes and euery of them, ſhall ſtande, remayne, and be in the ſame force, ſtrength, and effecte, as they were before the makinge of this acte, any thinge in this acte mentioned to the contrary notwithſtandinge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where the manoure of Southwell in the countie of Nottingham, and alſo the Scite and procincte of the colledge of Southwell in the ſame countie together, with diuers other landes, tenementes, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to the ſayde late colledge lately belongynge or appertaininge, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyed and aſſured by indenture, fine, or otherwyſe, by or from Iohn Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount eſquier, vnto our late Soueraigne Lorde kinge Edward the Sixte and to his heyres and ſucceſſours, for the diſcharge and ſatiſfaction of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers great ſummes of money, wherein the ſame Iohn Beamounte was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>detted to the ſaid late king. Be it enacted and eſtabliſhed by the aucthoritie aforeſaid, that the ſaide co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ueyaunce and aſſuraunce ſhalbe perfect, good, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and auayleable againſt the ſaid Beamount and his heyres, to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, conſtructions and purpoſes, according to the purport, tenor, and true meaning of the ſame conueiaunces, and aſſuraunces. Sauing to al and eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry perſon or perſons, and bodies politike and corporate, their heires and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſours and euery of them, other then the ſaid Iohn Beamount, his wyfe, and his heyres, and all other clayming any eſtate or intereſte by or from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſithens the ſame conueiaunce and aſſuraunce, all ſuch right, ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, intereſt, poſſeſſion, eſtate, leaſes, rentes, ſeruices, commons, and all other profites and commodities whatſoeuer, as they or anye of them, ſhoulde, or might haue had if this acte had neuer ben had ne made. Anye thinge therein conteyned to the contrary, notwithſtandinge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ACTE</hi> for the hauing of horſe, armour, and weapon.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .ii. Chapiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR THE BETTER</hi> furniture and defence of thys Realme. Be it enacted by the kyng and quenes Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, with thaſſentes of the lordes ſpirituall and temporall and the commons in this preſent parliamente aſſembled, &amp; by aucthoritie of the ſame, that aſmuch of al &amp; euery acte and Statute concernyng onely the keping or fyndinge of horſe, horſes, or armoure, or of any of them heretofore made or prouyded, and all &amp; euery forfeyture, and penaltye, concernyng onely the ſame, ſhalbe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence forth vtterly voyde repealed and of none effect. And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that euery noble man, gentelman &amp; other tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral perſon, after the rate &amp; proportion hereafter declared ſhal haue &amp; kepe in a redines ſuch horſes, geldinges, Armoure &amp; other furniture for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wars, at the leſt, &amp; in ſuch ſort &amp; maner as is &amp; ſhalbe in this act hereafter expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and declared. That is to ſaye, all and euery perſon temporall, hauynge any honors, lordeſhippes, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures or
<pb facs="tcp:180783:5"/>woodes of eſtate of enheritaunce or freholde, to the clere yerely value of one thowſand pound or aboue, ſhall from &amp; after the firſt day of May, which ſhal be in the yere of our lord god, a thouſand .v. hundred fifty &amp; eight, haue, find, kepe ſuſteine &amp; mainteine w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in this realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, of their owne proper and at their owne proper coſtes and expences .vi. horſes, or geldyngs, able for dimilaunces, wherof .iii. of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the leaſte to be horſes, with ſufficiente harneſſes, ſteele ſadels and weapon, requiſit and apperteyning to the ſayde demylaunces, horſes or geldynges, and tenne light horſes or geldinges able and mete for light horſemen, with the furniture of harnes and weapon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite for the ſame. And alſo forty corſelettes furniſhed, fortye almayne ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uettes or in ſtede of the ſaid almaine riuettes, forty cotes of plate, corſeletes or brygandines furniſhed fortye pykes .xxx. longe bowes .xxx. ſhefes of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes .xxx. ſteele cappes or ſculles .xx. blacke billes, or halberdes .xx. haque buttes, and twenty morians or ſalettes. And euery perſon temporal hauing any honors, lordeſhippes, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures or woodes, of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſaid, to the clere yerely value of a thou ſande markes, or aboue, and vnder the clere yearelye value of a thouſande pound, ſhal haue, finde, ſuſteine and maintaine within this realme of their owne proper and at their owne proper coſtes and expences, foure horſſes or geldinges, able for dimilaunces whereof two at the leaſte to be horſes, with ſuffycyente harneſſes, and weaponne, and ſadels mete and requyſyte to the ſayde dymylaunces Horſes or Geldynges, and ſyxe lyghte horſes or geldinges, able and mete for light horſemen, with furniture of harnes, and weapon requiſite for the ſame. And alſo of armor and weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .xxx. corſelets furnyſhed .xxx. almayne ryuettes or in ſtede of the ſayde almaine ryuettes, xxx. cotes of plate, corſelettes, or brygandynes furnyſhed .xxx. pykes, twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye long bowes .xx. ſhefes of arrowes .xx. ſtele cappes or ſculles, ten blacke billes or halbertes, tenne haquebuttes, and ten morians or ſalletes. And euery perſon temporall hauing honors, lordſhips, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures, or wodes of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſaid, to the clere yerely value of foure hundred poundes or aboue, and vnder the clere yerely value of a thouſande markes ſhal haue, finde, kepe, ſuſteine and meynteyne as is aforeſayd two horſes, or one horſe and one geldyng able for dimilaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, with ſufficient furniture of harnes, ſtele ſadels and weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the ſame as is aforeſayde, and foure geldynges able for lyght horſemen with ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent harnes and weapon for the ſame, and alſo .xx. corſelettes furniſhed .xx, almayne riuettes furniſhed, or in ſtede of almaine riuettes, twenty cotes of plate corſelettes or bryga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dines furnyſhed, twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty pykes, fyftene long bowes fyftene ſhefes of arrowes, fyftene ſteele cappes or ſculles, ſixe haquebuttes, and ſixe moryans or ſalletes. And that euerye perſon temporal hauyng lord ſhippes, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures, or wods, of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſayde, to the clere yerely value of .CC. poundes or aboue, and vnder the clere yerely value of .CCCC. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, ſhall from the ſaid firſt day of May, haue kepe ſuſteine and mainteine .i. gret horſe or gelding, able for a dimilaunce, with ſufficient furniture of harnes, ſteeled ſadle, &amp; weapon
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:180783:5"/>for the ſame, &amp; two geldings, able for light horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> harnes and wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pons ſufficient, as is aforeſaid, for the ſame, and alſo ten corſelettes fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed, ten almaine riuettes, or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place of almaine riuettes, x. cotes of plate, corſelettes or brigandines furniſhed, x. pikes .viii. long bowes viii. ſhefes of arrowes .viii. ſtele Cappes or ſculles, three haquebutts, &amp; three morians or ſalettes. And euery perſon temporall hauing any lord ſhippes, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures, or woodes, of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſaid, to the clere yerely value of one hundred pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, or aboue, &amp; vnder the yearely value of .ii. hundrede pounds ſhal from and after the ſayde firſt day of May, haue, kepe, and maynteine (as is aforeſayd) two geldinges, able and mete for light horſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with ſufficient harnes, and weapon requiſit for the ſame. And alſo thre cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelettes furniſhed, thre almaine riuettes, or in ſtede of them ſoo manye cotes of plate, corſelettes, or brygandines furniſhed .iii. pikes .iii. long bowes, thre ſhefes of arrowes, thre ſteele cappes or ſculles, two haque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buttes, and two morians or ſallettes. And alſo euery perſon temporall hauing lordeſhippes, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures, or wooddes, of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſaid, to the clere yearely value of a hundred markes or aboue, and vnder the yearelye value of a hundred poundes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid firſt day of May, ſhal haue, kepe, mainteine and ſuſteine one gelding able and mete for a light horſema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the harnes &amp; weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſufficient &amp; requiſit for the ſame, two corſelettes furniſhed, two almaine riuittes, or in ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame two cotes of plate, or briga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dines furniſhed, two pikes, two lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g bowes, two ſhefes of arrowes .ii. ſteele cappes or ſculles .i. haquebut .i. morian or ſalet. And alſo euery perſon te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral, hauing lordſhips, manors, houſes, lands, meadowes paſtures or wods, of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſayd, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yerely value of .xl. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or aboue, &amp; vnder the yerely value of a hundred markes, ſhal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid firſt day of May, haue mainteine &amp; kepe .ii. corſelettes fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed .ii. almaine ryuettes, or in ſtede of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame .ii. cotes of plate, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelettes or briga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dines furniſhed, two pikes, one long bowe, one ſhefe of arrowes, one ſteele cap or ſcull .ii. haquebuttes .ii. morians or ſallets. And alſo euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral hauing lordſhips, manors, houſes, landes meadowes, paſtures, or wods of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſaid, to the clere yerely value of .xx. poundes or aboue, and vnder the yerely value of fourty poundes, ſhal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid firſt day of May, haue, kepe, &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne one corſelet furniſhed, one pike, one haquebut, one moria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſaller, one long bowe, one ſhefe of arrowes, &amp; one ſteele cap or ſcull. And alſo euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral hauing lordſhipes, manoures, houſes, landes, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, paſtures or wods, of any ſuch eſtate as is aforeſaid, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cleare yerely value of .x poundes or aboue, &amp; vnder the yearelye value of .xx. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſhal fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; after the ſaid day haue, kepe, &amp; ſuſteine one almaine ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitte, cote of plate or brygandyne furnyſhed, one haquebut .i. morian, or ſallet, &amp; one long bowe, &amp; one ſpefe of arrowes, one ſteele cap or ſcul. And alſo euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> temporal hauing lordſhips, manors, houſes, la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des,
<pb facs="tcp:180783:6"/>meadowes, paſtures or woodes, of ſuch eſtate as is aforeſayde, to the clere yerely value of fyue poundes or aboue, &amp; vnder the yerely value of x. poundes, ſhal from and after the ſayd firſt day of May, haue, kepe, &amp; ſuſteyne one cote of plate furniſhed, one blacke byll, or halbert, one long bowe, one ſhefe of arrowes, and one freele cap, or ſcull. And alſo euerye perſonne temporal, hauyng goodes or cattells to the value of one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande markes or aboue, ſhall from the ſayde firſte daye of Maye, haue fynde, kepe, ſuſteyne, and mainetayne as is aforeſayde, one horſe, or gel dynge able for a demylaunce, with ſufficient harnes, ſtele ſadle, &amp; wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, requiſite and conuenient for the ſame, and one geldinge able and mete for a light horſeman, with harnes and weapon ſufficient and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite as is aforeſayd for the ſame, or eightene corſelets furniſhed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtede of the ſayd horſſe, and geldyng, and furniture of the ſame at hys choyſe. And alſo ſhall from the ſame day haue, fynd, kepe, and mayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne of armoure and weapon, two corſeletes furniſhed, two almaine ryuettes, or for the ſame almonryuettes, two cottes of plate, two corſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lettes, or two brygandynes furnyſhed, two pykes, foure longe bowes, foure ſhefe of arrowes, foure ſtele cappes or ſculles, and three haque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buttes, with thre morians, or ſalletes. And alſo euery perſon temporal hauynge goodes or cattels, to the values hereafter in this preſent act, ſpecyfyed and declared, ſhall from and after the ſayde firſt day of May haue fynde, kepe, ſuſteyne and maynetayne ſuch geldynges, armoure, weapon and furniture forwarre as is hereafter declared. That is to ſaye, hauynge to the value of foure hundred poundes or aboue, and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der the value of a thouſande markes, one geldynge able and meate for a lyghte horſeman with ſufficient harnes and weapon requiſite, and mete for the ſame or .ix. corſelettes, furnyſhed at his election, and alſo ſhal haue, fynde, and kepe one other corſelette furniſhed, one pike, two almayne ryuetes, or plate cotes or brygandines furnyſhed, one haque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>but, two longe bowes, two ſhefes of arrowes, and two ſtele cappes or ſculles. And hauynge in goodes and catteles, to the valewe of two hundrede pounde or aboue, and vnder foure hundred, one corſelet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed one pyke two almayne ryuetes, plate cotes, or brygandynes, fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyſhed one haquebut, one murryan or ſalet, two long bowes and two ſhefe of arrowes, and two ſcules or ſtele cappes. And hauyng in goods and cattells to the value of a hundred poundes or aboue, and vnder .ii. hundred, one corſelette, furnyſhed and one pyke, one payre of almayne ryuyttes, one plate cote, or payre of brygandine furnyſhed, two long bowes, and two ſhefes of arrowes, and two ſculles. And hauynge as is aforeſayde, in goodes and catteles, to the value of fourtye poundes, or aboue, and vnder a hundred poundes, two payre of almon riuettes, or two cotes of plate or brygandynes, furnyſhed, one longe bowe and one ſhefe of arrowes, one ſtele cappe or ſcull, and one blacke byll, or hal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bert. And hauynge as is aforeſayde in goodes and cattelles to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lewe
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:180783:6"/>of .xx. poundes or aboue, and vnder .xl. poundes, one payre of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne riuettes, or one cote of plate, or one paire of brygandines, two longe bowes, two ſhefes of arrowes, two ſculles or ſteele cappes, and one blacke byll or halbert. And hauinge as is aforeſayde to the value of tenne poundes or aboue, and vnder twenty poundes, one longe bowe, one ſhefe of arrowes, with one ſtëele cappe or ſcull, and one blacke byll or halbert. And alſo that euery perſonne temporall, not beynge aboue charged by this acte, hauinge, or that hereafter ſhall haue any annuitie or annuities, or yearely fee or fees for terme of life, or of any eſtate of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritaunce, or any copyholde or copyholdes, for terme of lyfe, or of anye eſtate of inheritaunce, to the cleare yearelye value of .xxx. poundes or aboue, ſhalbe charged and chargeable with ſuch furniture of warre as is aforeſayde, in euery degree, qualitie, and condition, according to the proportions and rates before expreſſed, limitted, and appointed for goodes and cattels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that euerye perſonne whiche by vertue of the acte made in the parliamente holden at weſtminſter in the .xxxiii. yeare of the reigne of kynge Henrye the eyght, was bounde (by reaſon that his wife ſhoulde weare ſuche kynd of apparell or other thing, as in the ſame ſtatute is ſpecially mentioned and declared) to kepe or fynde one greate ſtoned trottinge horſe and is not by this act before charged, to haue, mainteyne, and kepe any horſe or geldinge, ſhall from the ſayde fyrſte daye of Maye, haue, kepe, and maynteyne one geldinge, able and mete for a light horſeman, with ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient harnes and weapon for the ſame, in ſuche maner and fourme as euery temporall perſonne hauinge lordeſhippes, houſes, landes, mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, paſtures or woodes of ſuche eſtate as is aforeſayde, of the clere yearely value of one hundred markes, is charged or appoynted to find haue and maynteyne by this preſent acte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND BE IT</hi> further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that yf any perſonne chargeable by this acte, as is aforeſayde, ſhall by the ſpace of any thre whole monethes after the ſayde fyrſt daye of Maye, lacke or wante the ſayde number and kindes of horſes, geldinges, armoure, weapon, and furniture aforeſayde, or any of them, after ſuche rate, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, maner, and fourme as is in this acte aboue limitted, declared, and appoynted. That then euery ſuche perſonne ſhall forfeyt and looſe for euery ſuche thre monethes that he ſhall ſo lacke and want the ſame number and kyndes of horſes, geldinges, armoure, weapon, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture, or any parte thereof, for euery horſe or geldynge ſo lackyng, ten poundes, and for euery dimilaunce and turniture of the ſame, thre pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and for euery corſelet and furniture of the ſame .xl.s. and for euery almayne ryuette, cote of plate, or brigandine, and the furniture of the ſame .xx.s. and for euery bow &amp; ſhefe of arrowes, byl, halbert, haque but ſteele cappe, ſcull, moryan and ſalette .x.s. the one moytie of which ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:180783:7"/>forfeytures, ſhalbe to the kinge and Quene oure Soueraygne Lorde and Ladye, and to theyres and ſucceſſours of the ſame our ſoueraygne ladye, and the other moytye to him or them that wyll ſue for the ſame in any courte of recorde, by byll, playnte, action of debte, or informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in the whiche byl, playnt, action, or information, no wager of lawe, eſſoyne, or protection ſhall be allowed or admitted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND BE IT</hi> further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that the inhabitauntes of euery citie, boroughe, towne, pariſhe, and hamlette within this realme, other then ſuche as are ſpeciallye charged before in this acte, ſhall haue, fynde, kepe, ſuſteyne, and mainteyne, at theyr com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon charges and expences, ſuche harnes, and weapon, and as muche therof as ſhalbe appoynted by the comiſſioners of our ſayd ſoueraigne lorde and ladye, and of the heyres and ſucceſſours of the ſame our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lady, for the muſters or vewe of armour within ſuche citie, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe, towne, paryſhe or hamletre, there to be kepte, in ſuche place as by the ſayd comiſſioners ſhall be apoynted. And the numbers and kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des therof to be wrytten and compriſed in a payre of indentures, to be made betwene the ſayde commiſſioners or two of them at the leaſte, and twelue, eyghte, or foure of the chiefeſt of euery ſuche citie, borough towne, pariſhe, or hamlette, wherof one part to remayne with the cheif officer of the ſame citie, borough, towne, paryſhe, or hamlette: and the other part to remayne with the clerke of the peace of the ſhyre or coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye where euery iuche citie, towne, borough, paryſhe, or hamlette ſhall ſtande or be. And if the ſame inhabitauntes of euery ſuch citie, borough towne, paryſhe, or hamlette, other then ſuche as are ſpeciallye (as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde) charged, ſhall lacke or wante ſuche harnes or weapons, or any parte thereof, as ſhall be vnto them appoynted by the ſayd comiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for the muſters or vewe of armoure, as is aforeſayde, by the ſpace of any thre monethes together next after any ſuch appointment made: that then the ſame inhabitauntes ſhall forfeyte for euery the ſayd thre monethes for euery ſuche harnes or weapons ſo lackyng after the rate aboue limitted, the one moytie therof to be to our ſayde ſoueraigne lord and ladye, and to theyres and ſucceſſours of our ſaid ſoueraygne lady, and thother moytie to hym or them that wyll ſue for the ſame in any of the courtes of recorde of our ſayd ſoueraygne lorde and Ladye, and of the heyres and ſucceſſours of the ſame oure ſoueraigne Ladye, by byll, playnte, action of debte, or information, wherein no wager of lawe, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyne or protection ſhalbe admitted or allowed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND BE IT</hi> further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that the lord Chauncellour of Englande for the tyme beynge, ſhall haue full power and aucthoritie by vertue of this preſente acte, frome time to time to graunte out commiſſions vnder the great ſeale of England, to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of peace within euery ſhyre or countie of this realme, or to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them as by his diſcretion ſhall be thought mete and conueniente
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:180783:7"/>for the appointinge and limittinge of the ſayd harneſſes and weapo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, to be founde, kept, and mainteyned, in euery ſuch citie, borough, towne pariſhe, and hamlette, at the common charges of the inhabitauntes thereof, as is aforeſayde.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes, that this acte or any thinge therein conteyned ſhall not extende to take awaye or diſcharge any tenaunt, or fermour, of his ſeruice or couenaunte towardes his Lorde, for the fyndinge of horſe, armoure, or weapon, or for doynge of ſeruice by him ſelfe or anye other, whiche, by the tenure of his lande or ferme, he is bounde to do, at the time of makinge of this acte, but that he ſhall yelde, paye, and doe the ſame in as large ample maner and fourme, as though this act had neuer bene had ne made.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of peace, of euery Shire, ſhal haue power and aucthoritie by ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of this acte, from time to time, to make ſearch and vewe of and for the ſayd furnytures of horſes, geldinges, armour and weapon, to be founde mainteined and kept by any perſon aboueſaid, hauynge lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppes, manors, houſes, landes, meadowes, paſtures or woodes to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clere yerely value of .CC. poundes or vnder, and not aboue the yearely value of .CCCC. pounds, or to be found, mainteined or kept by any per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon or perſons chargeable by this act, by reaſon of hys or their goodes, cattels, annuities, fees, or copyholdes as is aforeſayd, and to heare and determine at their quarter Seſſions all and euery the defaultes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted or done contrary to this acte, within the countye, where ſuche Seſſions ſhalbe kept, by inquiſition, preſentment, byl, or informatyon before them exhibited, or by examination of two lawefull wytnes, at the diſcretion of the ſame Iuſtyces, &amp; to award proceſſe therevpon as though they were indicted before them by verdict of .xii. men or more. And vpon the conuiction of the offender by informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſuit of anye other then the kinge or the quene, or of theires or ſucceſſours of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quene to make eſtreates of the one moitie of the ſaid forfeytures to be leuyed to thuſe of oure ſayd ſoueraygne lorde and lady, or of theirs or Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſors of the ſame our ſoueraigne lady, as they vſe to doo of other fynes iſſues, and amercyamentes, growynge in the Seſſyons of peace, and to awarde execution of the other moytie for the compleynaunte or informer agaynſte the offender, by <hi>fieri facias</hi> or <hi>capias,</hi> as the kinges Iuſtices at weſtminſter, may doo and vſe to doo. And yf any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiction ſhal hereafter happen at thonely ſute of oure ſayde ſoueraygne lorde and ladye, or of the heires or ſucceſſoures of the ſame our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lady, that then the whole forfeytures to be eſtreated and leuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their vſes onelye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND BE IT FVRTHER</hi> enacted by the aucthorytie aforeſayde, that whenſoeuer anye perſonne ſhall at anye tyme hereafter be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uicted by vertue of this acte, for anye defaulte or thinge mentioned
<pb facs="tcp:180783:8"/>in thys acte, that then the ſame perſon ſhal not otherwiſe or eftſones be vexed, troubled, ſued or conuicted for the ſame defaulte or thing, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhalbe ſo conuicted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> be it moreouer enacted by the auchtoritie aforeſayde, that yf anye Souldioure ſhall at anye tyme hereafter make ſale of his horſe, harnes, and weapon, or anye of them contrarye to the fourme of the ſayde ſtatute, made in the ſaide ſeconde and thirde yeares of the ſaide late kinge, that then not onely the ſame Souldiour ſhall incurre the penalties of that ſtatute, but alſo the ſayde ſale made by ſuche ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioure to any perſon or perſonnes knowing him to be a ſouldior, ſhalbe voyde and of none effecte, agaynſt him or them that founde or ſet forth the ſayde horſe, harneſſe, and weapon, or any of them, to, or for the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture of ſuche ſouldioure to ſerue with the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, that no perſon ſhall be impeached or troubled for any offence done contrary to this acte, onleſſe preſentmente or ſute therof be had, made, or taken w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in one yeare next after thoffence done, any thing in this act to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary therof in any wyſe notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwaye and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that if at any time hereafter it ſhal fortune any perſon or perſons afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde, to be ſued or impeached for any forefeyture or penaltie, for not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge, ſuſteyninge, or kepinge ſuch furniture of corſelets, pykes, haque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buttes, or morians, as by this acte is before limitted, rated, and apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and for his or theyr excuſe and aunſwere, ſhall alleage and pleade that the ſame furniture ſo lacking, coulde not by him or them conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently be had, gotten, or prouided, for want and lacke of the ſame with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this realme, accordinge to the tenure and purporte of this acte, the ſame matter of want and lacke as is aforeſayde, ſhall be allowed, and taken for a good and ſufficient aunſwere and barre in the lawe, in caſe it be true, and if the ſame be denied or trauerſed, that thervpon an iſſue ſhalbe ioyned, and that the triall ſhall be of euery ſuche iſſue onelye had by the certificate to be made by the Lord Chauncellour, Lorde Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, the Lorde preſident of the Councell, the Lorde Stewarde of the Kynges and Quenes moſte honorable houſeholde, the Lorde pryuye Seale, the Lorde Admirall, and the lorde Chambrelayne of the ſayde houſeholde, or by thre of them, in wrytinge vnder theyr ſeales, or the ſeales of thre of them, this preſente acte, or anye ſtatute, lawe, or vſage heretofore had to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alſo and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that no perſonne or perſonnes chargeable by vertue of this Acte, to or for the fyndynge or hauynge of anye Horſe, Geldynge, Armoure, Weapon, or furnyture for the warre, as is aforeſayde, ſhall be charged with the ſame, or with any of them both, for his manours, houſes, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, meadowes, paſtures and woodes, and alſo for his goodes, catels, fermes, leaſes, copyholdes, rentes, annuities.</p>
               <pb n="viii" facs="tcp:180783:8"/>
               <p>Prouided alſo and be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that this acte or any thinge therein conteyned, ſhal not in any wyſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend or be adiudged or interpreted, to abrogate, repeale, or make voyde any part, ſentence, matter, clauſe, article, or thinge, conteyned or ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in the ſtatute, made in the .xxxiii. yeare of the raygne of the late no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prince of worthy memory kinge Henry the eight, for or concerning the hauing of long bowes and arrowes, &amp; the vſing, order, exerciſyng, and mayntenaunce of archery, and ſhotinge in longe bowes, but that the ſame ſtatute, and euery article, clauſe, ſentence, and thinge therein conteyned and ſpecified, touching, or in any wyſe concerninge the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge of longe bowes, arrowes, vſinge, order, exerciſinge, or mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of archerye, and ſhotinge in longe bowes, ſhall ſtande and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in force, and be obſerued, perfourmed, and kepte, accordynge to the tenure, effecte, and true meaning of the ſayd acte, vpon the paynes conteyned in the ſame, as this acte had not bene hadde ne made, this preſent act or any thinge therin conteyned to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandinge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alſo, that yf it ſhall fortune the ſayde furniture of armure aforeſayd, or any parte therof, at any time hereafter to be loſt or ſpente in any ſeruice of defence of this realme, or elles the horſes or geldinges aforeſayd, to be kylled or diſtroyed, or els by ſome other occaſion to be dead, that in ſuch caſe or caſes, no perſon or perſones ſhalbe charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any forfeiture or penaltie aforeſayde, for not hauinge ſuche quantitie or number of armour, horſes, or geldinges as is aforeſayde, ſo that he or they within one yeare next after ſuch loſſe or want, do ſupply the ſame againe in al points, according to the true meaning and purport of this act, any thing in the ſame act to the contrary therof notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo, that the want of any gauntlet or gauntlets, ſhal not be demed, accoumpted, or taken for anye tacke or wante of furnyture for a corſelet, any wordes before expreſſed, ſoundinge to the contrarye notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that euery perſon and perſons charged with the fyndinge of any haque but, and his or theyr ſeruaunt or ſeruauntes, ſhall and may exerciſe and vſe ſhotinge in the ſame haquebutte, at ſuche markes as are limitted and appointed by the ſtatute made in the .xxxiii. yeare of the raygne of king Henry the eyght, or at theyr owne proper games, ſo that they cary not, or vſe not the ſame haque but in any hyghe waye, vnleſſe it be comynge or goynge to or from the muſters, or marching towardes or from the ſeruyce of defence of the realme, any clauſe or article in the ſayde acte of the .xxxiii. yeare, to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes, that this acte ne any thinge therin conteyned, ſhall extende to charge any perſon or perſons, dwellinge or abydinge within the countreis of Northwales, and Southwales, and within
<pb facs="tcp:180783:9"/>the countye Palentine of Lancaſter and Cheſter, or either of them, with the findinge or hauinge of any haque but, but that they and euery of them, ſhall and maye at theyr wyll, libertie, and pleaſure, haue and kepe, in ſtede and place of euery haquebutte, charged by this acte, one longe bowe, and one ſhefe of arrowes, ouer and beſides ſuche other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and munition as is by the lawes of this realme limitted and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted, anye thinge in this acte to the contrarye notwythſtandinge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes that the Lorde Chauncelour of England, or keper of the greate ſeale for the tyme beinge, ſhall and maye from time to time by vertue of the kinge and Quenes highnes commiſſion, name aſſigne, and appointe comiſſioners in euery citie, boroughe, and towne corporate, wherein there be Iuſtices of the peace, as well in Englande as in Wales, ſo many of the ſame Iuſtices of peace, with ſuche and as manye other perſonnes, to be ioyned with them dwellinge oute of the ſayd cities, boroughes, and townes corporate, as he or they ſhall thinke mete, to take viewe of armour in euerye of the ſame cities, boroughes, and townes corporate, accordinge to this preſente acte, and alſo to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne what harnes and armoure ſhall be prouided and kepte by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes of euery ſuche citie, boroughe, and towne corporate, as is aforeſayde, accordinge to this preſent acte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ACT</hi> for the takinge of muſters.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .iij. chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE</hi> heretofore commaundement hath ben geuen by the kinge and Quenes maieſties, and other the progenitours of the Quenes maieſtie, kynges of this realme, to diuers and ſondry perſonnes, to muſter their maieſties people and ſubiects of this theyr realme of England, and to leuye a number of them for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of theyr maieſties and of this realme, in theyr warres, ſuche as were moſt hable and likelieſt to ſerue well in the ſame, whiche ſeruice hath ben greatly hyndered, as well for that a greate number hath ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented them from the ſayde muſters, whiche ought to haue come to the ſame, as alſo for that manye of the mooſt hable and likelye men for that ſeruice, haue bene through frendſhippe or rewardes, releaſed, forborne, and diſcharged of the ſayd ſeruice, &amp; ſome other not being able or mete, taken, appointed, and choſen thervnto, and yet the ſame diſabilitie and vnaptnes notwithſtanding, the ſame vnable &amp; vnmete perſons vpon ſummes of mony, or other kind of rewardes, or exactions by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> payd, to ſome ſuche as had the order of the ſaide muſters, haue ben alſo relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and diſcharged of the ſayd ſeruice, to the great impoueryſhmente of
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:180783:9"/>the ſubiectes, and cheyfely to the great peryl and daunger of this noble realme, in the hinderaunce of the true and neceſſary ſeruyce thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOR</hi> remedy wherof, be it enacted by the king and quene our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lord and lady, with thaſſent of the lordes Spirituall and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, and by thaucthoritie of the ſame, that yf anye perſon or perſones, that ſhal be commaunded, at any time hereafter, generally, or ſpeciallye, to muſter afore any ſuch as ſhall haue aucthoritie or commaundement for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame by, or from the kyng and quenes Maieſties, or by theires or ſucceſſors of the quenes maieſtie, or by any lieutenaunte, wardeyne or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſonnes aucthoryſed for the ſame, do willyngly abſente hym or them ſelfes from the ſame muſters, hauyng no true and reaſonable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe of ſyckenes, or other laweful impediment, or at their apparaunce at ſuch muſters, do not bryng with them ſuch their beſt furnyture of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raye, and armoure, as he or they ſhal then haue for hys or their owne perſon in a redynes, ſhall for euery ſuch defaulte and offence, haue and ſuffer impriſonment by the ſpace of ten dayes, without bayle or maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryce, by the commaundemente of ſuche as ſhall haue aucthoritie as is aforeſayd, to take the ſame muſters, onleſſe he or they ſoo offendyng as is aforeſayd, doo agree to or with the ſaid commiſſioners, or two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to paye to thuſe of the kyng and quene our ſoueraygne lord and ladye, or of the heires and ſucceſſoures of the ſame oure ſoueraygne ladye, for euery ſuch offence, fourty ſhyllynges for a fyne, whiche ſayde fyne after agrement for the payment of the ſame as is aforeſayd, ſhalbe certified and eſtreated into the court of the eſcheker at Weſtmynſter, by ſuch as ſhall haue power to take the ſayd muſters as is aforeſayd, or by two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vnder their ſeales or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeales of two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, within the ſpace of two monethes next after ſuch agrement, to pay the ſayde fyne had or made, and the ſame fyne ſo eſtreated to be leuyed in ſuch fourme as fynes aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by the Iuſtyces of aſſiſe, or of Gaole deliuerye, in their circuites are vſed to be leuyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND <hi>BE IT</hi> FVRTHER</hi> enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that if any perſon or perſonnes which at any time or tymes hereafter ſhall be commaunded or appoynted by the kyng and Quene our Soueraygne Lord and lady, or by the heires and ſucceſſours of the ſame our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne Lady, by their commiſſion, letters, or otherwyſe authoryſed, to leuye muſter or make any men to ſerue in their warres, or otherwyſe for the defence of thys realme, do by any meane exact, leuy, receaue, or take, or cauſe to be taken any ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me or ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes of mony, or other rewarde or thing whatſoeuer, of any perſon or perſons, for ſeruice in the warrs, or that ſhalbe appointed, named or muſtred to ſerue in ani ſuch ſetuice, or for the ſparyng, releaſyng or diſchargyng of ſuch perſon or perſones from the ſayde ſeruice, that then euery ſuch perſon that ſo ſhall offende in exactyng, receauyng or takyng by any waies or meanes anye ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me
<pb facs="tcp:180783:10"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="ix" facs="tcp:180783:10"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180783:11"/>or ſummes of monye, or other reward, or thyng whatſoeuer as is afore ſaid, ſhal for euery ſuch offence forfeite .x. times ſo much as he ſhal ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue exacte or take.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayd, that yf any ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pytayne, pety capitayne or other, hauynge charge of men for ſeruyce in warre, ſhal for any aduauntage, lucre or gayne by hym to be taken, or receyued, dyſcharge or lycence, any of the ſouldyours, or men appointed to ſerue in the warres, vnder his rule or order, to depart from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſeruyce, or ſhall not paye vnto his ſouldioures, and to euerye of them, their full and whole wages, conducte and coate monye, within tenne dayes next after that ſuch capitayne, pety capitayne, or other hauynge charge of men as is aforeſayd, ſhall haue receyued the ſame, that then the party ſo offendyng in geuyng any ſuche lycence or dyſcharge as is aforeſayde, ſhal loſe &amp; forfeyt for euery ſuch offence, ten tymes the value of the thing ſo taken or receyued, and ſhal alſo paye to euery ſouldiour from whom he ſhall ſo withhold any the ſayd wages, conduct, or coate mony; treble the ſumme ſo withholden, the one moytie of al which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feytures, other then ſuch as before by this act is lymitted or geuen to the ſould your or ſouldyors as is aforeſayd, for their wages, coate or con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ducte mony withdrawen, ſhalbe to the king and the quenes maieſties, and theirs and ſucceſſoures of the quenes maieſtye, and thother moitie there of to hym or them that wyll ſue for the ſame, by action of debte, byll, playnt, information or otherwyſe, in any court of record, in which action or ſute no eſſoygne protection or wager of law, ſhalbe allowed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that all Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of aſſiſes in their circuites, and al Iuſtyces of peace, within the lymittes of their commiſſion, in their aſſiſes and ſeſſyons, and Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes of leetes, lawedayes, and libertyes, at their leetes and lawdaies ſhal and maye from tyme to tyme enquire, here, and determyne euerye of the ſayd offences, commytted or done contrary to thys acte, wythin the precynctes of their commyſſion, leete or lybertye, and yf any perſon or perſons ſhalbe before the ſayde Iuſtyces of aſſiſe, Iuſtices of peace, or any of them, preſented or indicted of any thoffe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces aforeſaid that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid iuſtices of aſſiſe, or iuſtices of peace, before whom ſuche indyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or preſentment ſhalbe taken or had, ſhal and may by the aucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of this act, award ſuch proces againſt euery ſuch perſon or perſons ſo indited as vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inditements of treſpas is vſed and accuſtomed to be made, &amp; if any ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons ſo indited, do appere before the ſaid iuſtices &amp; confeſſe the ſame, or plede to the ſame indytementes, &amp; after by verdycte of .xii. menne ſhal be of any the ſayde offences conteyned in ſuch inditeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or inditements conuicted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſaid Iuſtyces before who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any ſuch conuyction ſhalbe ſo had, ſhal &amp; may award ſuch perſon or perſons ſo conuycted vnto pryſon, there to remayne without bayle or maynepryce, vntyll ſuch tyme as he or they haue payd, or ſatiſfyed the
<pb n="x" facs="tcp:180783:11"/>moytie of the forfeiture aforeſayd, vnto the kyng and quenes maieſties vſe, and thother moitie therof vnto hym or them that ſhal come before the ſayd Iuſtyces and geue euidence agaynſt the partye to be conuic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at the time of the ſayd conuiction, and by whoſe euydence he ſhalbe of the ſaid offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce conuicted. And yf any ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uiction ſhalbe had w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any euydence openly giuen by any perſon or perſons, that then the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye conuicted as aforeſayd ſhal remayne in priſon as is aforeſayd, vntil he haue ſatiſfyed the hole forfeiture to the king and quenes maieſties vſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it further enacted by thauctoritie afore ſayd, that yf any the offences aforeſayd, touching captaines, pety cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynes, or other hauyng charge of men, ſhalbe committed durynge the time that any army or number of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being vnder a lieuten aunt ſhalbe aſſembled and continue together, or by any captaine, pety captaine, or other hauyng charge of men that ſhal ſerue vnder any lord warden, or other cheiftayne, that then vpon complaint thereof, the lord lieutenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or the lord warden, or other cheyftayne, durynge the tyme of anye hys or their commyſſyon ſhall and maye heare, order, and determyne the ſame offences, by hys or theyr dyſcretyons.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes that thys acte, nor any thyng therein conteined ſhall not in any wiſe extend to take awaye or diſcharge any tenaunte or fermoure of hys ſeruice or couenaunt, towardes hys lord, for the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of horſe, armor or weapon, or for doynge of ſeruyce by hym ſelfe, or by any other, whych by the tenure of hys lande or otherwyſe is bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to do before the makyng of thys acte, but that he ſhal yelde, do and paye the ſame in as ample maner and forme as though this arte had ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ver bene had or made.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alſo and be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd that yf any ſuch capytayne, pety captaine, or other hauynge charge of men as is aforeſayd, ſhalbe at anye tyme hereafter conuycted, or or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered by vertue of thys acte, for anye of hys offences aforeſayde, that then the ſame Capytaine, petie Capitaine or other hauing charge of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as is aforeſaid, ſo conuicted, ſhal not otherwiſe or eftſones be vex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed, troubled, ſued, or conuicted for the ſame offence, whereof he ſhal be ſo before conuicted or ordered.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where one braunch or article conteyned in the ſtatute made in the ſeconde and thyrde yeare of the reygne of the late kynge Edwarde the ſyxte, intituled, an acte touchinge the true ſeruyce of Captaynes, and Souldyoures, whereby the departure of anye Souldyoure ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge as in the ſayde acte is expreſſed, wythoute lycence of the lyeu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunte or other offycer or offycers named in the ſayde acte, or in their abſence, of their deputies, was made felonye is of noo force, ſtrengthe, ne effecte, at thys preſente, by reaſonne of the acte of repeale of certayne treaſonnes felonyes and primynyre made in
<pb facs="tcp:180783:12"/>the firſt ſeſſion of the parliament holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtminſter, in the fyrſtyere of the Quenes maieſties reygne. Be it for good and reaſonable conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratyons enacted and eſtablyſhed by thaucthoritie of thys preſent parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, that the ſayd braunch or article, and euerye ſentence and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therin conteyned, be from henceforth holy reuyued, and recontynu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and be and remayne in full ſtrength and effect to al intentes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions and purpoſes, the ſayde acte of repeale notwithſtandynge. And that al and euery other article, clauſe, prouyſo, and matter conteined in the ſame acte, ſhall ſtand, remayne, and be in their full force, ſtrengthe, and effecte. Any thing in this acte conteined to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> yet neuertheleſſe wherin the ſayd acte it is prouyded, that no perſon or perſones, ſhould be charged for the takynge or receyuynge of any gyfte or rewarde of anye of hys or their tenauntes or frendes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the releyfe, ayde, or helpe of the ſame perſonnes beynge com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to ſerue in warres, or otherwyſe to fynd men on horſebacke, or on fote, within thys realme or withoute, nor for the gyfte, rewarde, ayde or helpe reſerued, or couenaunted, to be payde or gyuen to any per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon appoynted to ſerue in warres, or to fynde horſe or men, to ſerue by reaſon of any graunt, couenaunte reſeruation, cuſtome or tenure, any thyng in the ſayd acte to the contrary notwithſtanding, as by the ſaid acte and prouyſo more playnely it doth and maye appeare. Be it enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thaucthoritie of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> no perſon or perſons ſhal or may by coulour of the ſaid prouiſo, or of any wordes or matter therin conteyned, exact or demaund, or leuy any ſumme or ſummes of mony, horſe, armoure, or any other thyng, other then ſhalve employed furth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with in the preſent ſeruyce of thoſe warres, of the kynge and queenes maieſties, her heires or ſucceſſoures, for whych it is leuyed, the whyche ſumme or ſummes of mony, horſe, armoure, or other thyng, or as much thereof as ſhal not be ſpent, loſt, or conſumed in the ſayd ſeruyce, ſhalbe rendred and reſtored to ſuch perſon or perſones, as payde or delyuered the ſame, vpon the penaltyes and forfeytures, conteyned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid acte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, that no perſon or perſons, inhabitynge within any cytye, borough, or towne corporate, being a countye of it ſelfe, or in whych any Iuſtices of peace be or herealter ſhalbe, by charter, ſhalbe compellable by vertue of thys acte, to make his or their apparaunce, with ſuch furniture as is aforeſayd, at any muſter hereafter to be had, or taken out of the Suburbes, precinct, or lyberties of the ſame Citye, Borough or Towne, nor before any perſon or perſons, aucthoryſed by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion or otherwiſe as is aforeſaid, onleſſe the maior, or other hed of fycer, of ſuch citie, borough, or towne, &amp; one other diſcrete inhabitaunt of the ſame at the leaſt be ioyned in the ſame commiſſion or other auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie as is aforeſayd, with the ſame other perſon or perſons ſo auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed, any thing before mentioned to the contrary notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:180783:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ACTE</hi> that acceſſaries in murder and dyuers felonies, ſhall not haue the benefit of clergie.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .iiii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>OR THE</hi> due punyſſhmente of ſuche as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, counſell, or hire any perſon or perſons, to com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit, perpetrate, or do any petie treaſon, wylful murdre, or any of the offences in this preſente acte mentioned. Be it enacted by the aucthoritie of this preſente par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamente, that all and euerye perſonne and perſonnes that after the fyrſte daye of Marche next comminge, ſhall maliciouſly commaunde, hyre, or counſell any perſon or perſons, to committe or do any petye treaſon, wylfull murder, or to do any robberye in any dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge houſe or houſes, or to committe or do any robbery in or nere any high waye in the realme of Englande, or in any other the Queues do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, or to commit or do any robbery in any place within the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Englande agaynſt Scotlande, or wylfully to burne any dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge houſe, or any parte thereof, or anye barne then hauynge corne or grayne in the ſame, that then euerye ſuche offender or offenders, and euery of them beynge outlawed thereof, or beynge thereof arraygned and found gyltie by the ordre of the lawe, or beyng otherwyſe lawfully attaynted or conuicted of the ſame offence, or beynge arraygned ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of do ſtande mute of malice or frowarde mynde, or do chalenge perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye aboue the nombre of twenty perſons, or wyll not aunſwere dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly to ſuche offence, ſhall not haue the benefite of his or theyr clergye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted, that euery lorde and lordes of the parliament, and piere and piers of the realme, hauing place and voyce in the parliament, vpon euery inditement for any of the offences aforeſayd, ſhalbe tryed by theyrpiers, as hath bene accuſtomed by the lawes of this realme.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ACT</hi> touchinge the makinge of wollen clothes.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .v. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE</hi> in the parliament holden at weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter, in the fift and ſixt yeare of the reigne of our late ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueraigne lorde kinge Edward the ſixte, there was by great deliberation and aduiſe one good acte made for the true &amp; perfect making of wollen cloth within this realme, ſythence the makyng wherof, diuers clothiers found them ſelues agreued, alleging that it is vnpoſſible for them to ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame act in all poyntes, &amp; haue in this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t praied ſome mitigation therof, it is therfore at theyr ſpecial inſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; requeſt ordered, eſtabliſhed, enacted, &amp; prouided, in maner &amp; fourme folowing.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:180783:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="xi" facs="tcp:180783:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:180783:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN PRIMIS,</hi> that euery white cloth &amp; clothes comonly called longe Worceſters, &amp; all like clothes of like making mentioned in the ſaid act, which by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame was limited to weigh .ixxxiiii. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, being wel ſcou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, thicked, milled, and fully dryed, ſhal weigh .ixxv. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, euery white cloth which ſhalbe made in the counties of Wylteſ. Glouceſter, &amp; Somerſet, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or els where of like makinge, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing apointed by the ſaid acte to weigh .lxiiij. pounds, ſhal weigh being well ſcoured, thicked, milled, and fully dried .lxj. poundes at the leaſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> euery broade cloth made in the ſhyres of Kent and Suſſex, or at the towne of Reding, or any of them, or els where of like makynge, mentioned in the ſayd acte, whiche by the ſame was limitted to weigh lxxxx. poundes at the leaſt, ſhall weygh beinge well ſcoured, thicked, mylled, and fully dried .lxxxvi. poundes at the leaſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> that euery courſe ſhort cloth made in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhyres of Suff. Norff. and Eſſex, or any of them, or els where of like ſort, &amp; euery courſe clothe to be made within the Shyre of Kent, not exceadinge the price of ſyxe poundes, all whiche by the ſayde Acte are appoynted to conteyne .vii. quarters of a yarde at the leaſt in breadth, ſhall conteyne and be at the water, beyng thorough wette, ſixe quarters and a half within the liſte through and by all the whole cloth at the leaſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> euery yarde of cloth commonly called handy warp, being wel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcoured, thicked, mylled, and fully dried, ſhall conteyne the breadth ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified in the ſaid act, &amp; ſhal weigh two poundes and a half at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as many perſons do counterfet the making of Cok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, Bocking and Braintree clothes comonly called handiwarpes, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding there vnto ſuch like liſtes as the makers of ſuche clothes do, to the great deceipte of the king and Quenes maieſties ſubiectes. Be it ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enacted, that no perſon or perſons from the firſt day of May nexte coming, ſhal adde vnto any cloth or clothes, any ſuch like liſte or liſtes, except the warpe therof be ſponne vpon the rocke or diſtaffe, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine of forfeyture of the ſame cloth or clothes, or the very value therof. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided alwayes that the clothe makers within the citie of Worceſtour may make ſuche liſtes as they haue done heretofore.</p>
               <p>Item that no perſon or perſons inhabiting within the weſtriding in the countie of yorke, ſhal make or cauſe to be made any broade clothe or clothes called pewkes, tawneis, violets, or grenes, except the wolther of before it be conuerted into yarne, be fyrſt died, litted, and coulered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the couler blue, of the value of two pence a pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pain of forfeiture of euery ſuch colored cloth, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value therof, wherof the wol ſhal not be firſt died, litted, &amp; colored w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the couler blue of .ij. d. a. li. as is aforſaid.</p>
               <p>Item that euerye ordinarye karſey mentioned in the ſaid acte, ſhall conteine in length in the water betwixte .xvi. and .xvii. yardes, yarde and ynche, and being wel ſcoured, thicked, milled, dreſſed, &amp; fully dried ſhall weighe .xix. poundes the peece at the leaſte. And euerye karſeye
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:180783:14"/>called ſortinge karſey, mentioned in the ſayde Acte, beynge well ſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, thicked, mylled, dreſſed, and fully dryed, readye to be ſhewed, ſhall weyghe .xxii. poundes at the leaſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> that euery Deuonſhyre karſey called Doſſone, the whiche is appoynted by the ſame ſtatute to weygh beynge drye .xiiij. poundes at the leaſte, ſhall weygh beinge well ſcoured, thicked, mylled, and fullye dryed, after the rate of euery yarde one pounde at the leaſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> that one article mentioned in the ſayde ſtatute concernynge welſhe cottons touchinge the length and weight, ſhalbe clearely void, and euery gode of welſhe lininge ſhall conteyne and be three quarters of a yarde in breadth in the water, and ſhall weygh one pounde and a halfe quarter, and euery yarde of cotton beyng fully wrought and cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toned, ſhall weygh one pounde at the leaſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> be it further enacted, that no perſon or perſonnes whiche ſhal buye to ſell agayne by waye of retayle or otherwiſe, anye of the ſayde welſhe lininges, ſhall dreſſe or worke, or cauſe to be dreſſed or wrought within his or theyr dwellynge houſe or houſes, or in any other place by him ſelfe, or his ſeruaunt or ſeruauntes, anye of the ſayde welſhe linin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but ſhall put the ſame to ſome ſuche perſon or perſons, as ſhalbe of the arte or ſcience of Sheremen, Cottoners, or fryſers, to be by theim wrought and dreſſed, vpon payne of forfeyture for euery welſhe cotton or lyninge, fryſed or cottoned to the contrary .vj. <abbr>s.</abbr> viij.
<abbr>d.</abbr>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> that all and euerye cotton or cottons called Mancheſter, Lanckeſhire, and Cheſſhyre cottous, and all clothes called Manche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Rugges, or Mancheſter Fryſes, maye be deuyded into two halfe peeces, and ſhall conteyne and be after the rate of ſuche breadth and weyght, as in the ſayd actis limitted and apoynted to a whole peece of euery of the ſeueral peeces of cottons &amp; rugges aforeſayd any thing in the ſaid former ſtatute to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> if any cloth or karſey of the ſeuerall kindes of makinges, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the ſaid former act, or this eſtatute, do excede the ſeueral len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthes mentioned in the ſame, that then euery yarde ſo excedinge, ſhall weygh after ſuch rate as euery yarde of ſuche cloth or karſeys contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſayd ſeuerall lengthes, ſhall or ought to weygh, vpon payne of forfeyture for euery yarde, not weyinge after ſuche rate .v.s. And if any ſuche cloth or karſeys ſhall lacke of ſuch weyght as by the ſayd ſtatute or this acte it ought and is appoynted to haue, then the maker thereof or other perſon in whoſe handes or poſſeſſion the ſame ſhall be founde, ſhall forfeyte for euery pounde lacking aboue .iiij. poundes .v.s. and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for euery pounde exceadinge not aboue .iiij. poundes .ij. <abbr>s.</abbr> in maner and fourme as in the ſayd former acte is appointed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> one article mentioned in the ſaid ſtatute, wherein the alneger is prohibited to ſet his ſeal to any cloth or karſey which ſhal proue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, bandy, ſqually, in or by warpe or wofe, or els ſhal happen to be euell
<pb facs="tcp:180783:15"/>burled or waſted in the mylle, or otherwyſe to be full of holes, mylbrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, or to be hoolye, ſhalbe voyde and of none effecte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM</hi> it is enacted that if at any time after the fyrſte daye of Maye, anye clothe or karſey, thoroughe the defaulte or necligence of the kar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, ſpinners, or weauers, or any of them, ſhal, or do proue eyther pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey, cockeley, bandye, ſqually, or rowye, by warpe or woofe, or els ſhall happen to be euell burled, or waſted in the myll, or elles thoroughe the defaulte or necligence of the myll man, or otherwyſe, to be full of holes, mylbrackes, or to be hooly, that then the maker of euery ſuche clothe or kerſey ſo beynge defectiue or faultie as is aforeſayde, ſhal fixe vnto eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ende of the ſayd clothe or karſeye ſo beynge defectiue and faultye, and offred to be ſolde, one ſeale of leade, in the whiche ſeale ſhalbe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graued this worde (faultye) vpon payne of forfeyture of ſuche clothe or karſey, or the value thereof ſo offred to be ſolde, wherevnto ſuche ſeale ſhall not be ſet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> the article mentioned in the ſayde former acte of retourninge of defectiue clothes, karſeyes, friſes, or cottons beyng tranſported ouer the ſeas by the marchauntes, ſhalbe vtterly voyde. But neuertheles be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that if it ſhall fortune hereafter any marchaunte or marchauntes, to tranſporte anye clothe or clothes, karſeys, fryſes, or cottons, whervnto the ſeale with this word (faultye) was not annexed at the tyme of the ſale therof by the clothier, and the ſame clothes, karſeys, fryſes, or cottons ſo tranſported, or anye of them to be founde faultie or defectiue, and the ſame marchaunt or marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes therof, within two yeares after ſuche ſale, to brynge a certificate, ſealed with the ſeale of any towne or companye in the parties beyonde the ſeas, or ſigned by a Notarye there, after the accuſtomed maner, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſienge and declarynge therby the loſſe and damage whiche the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes ſhall haue ſuſteyned by ſuche defectiue and faultie clothe or clothes ſo tranſported, that then the clothier or clothiers, or other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of whome the clothe or clothes was boughte, theyr executours or adminiſiratours, ſhall within ſixe wekes nexte after requeſte made by the ſayde marchaunte, his executours, adminiſtratours, or aſſignes, well and truelye ſatyſfye coutente and paye, to ſuche marchaunte, his executours or adminiſtratours, or aſſignes, all and euery ſuche ſumme and ſummes of money as ſhal ſo be mentioned, expreſſed, and declared in the ſayd certificate, vpon payne of forfeyture to the partye greued, for euery none payment vpon ſuche requeſte, double the value of ſuche ſumme or ſummes mentioned in the ſayde certificate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, that ſuche marchaunte ſhall not in anye wyſe haue by vertue of this act, any recompence for lacke of length, breadth, or weyght, of, or for any cloth, whervnto the ſeale of any citie-borough or towne corporate ſhalbe fixed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> yf any perſonne ſhall by him ſelfe, or by any other perſonne by
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:180783:15"/>him procured cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfet, ſet to, or take away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any cloth, karſey, friſe, rugge, or cotton, any ſeale appoynted to be fixed to any clothe, karſeye, fryſe, rugge, or cotten, eyther by this acte, or by the ſayde former eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, that then euerye ſuche perſonne ſo offendinge, ſhall incurre and haue like penalties, forfeitures, and puniſhmentes, as in the ſayde for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer acte is apoynted and limitted for the like offence.</p>
               <p>And for the better execution as well of this preſente acte, as of the ſayde former eſtatute, and to the intente that all kinde of karſeys, cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, friſes, rugges, and other wollen cloth, made in any towne ſhalbe the better knowen, it is further enacted, that the ſeal of euery borough or towne corporate, appoynted, or to be appoynted for the ſealynge of anye ſuche kynde of cloth, ſhall be fixed to all and euery ſuche kynde of clothe, beynge well and ſubſtaunciallye made within ſuche Citie, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe, or towne corporate, whyche clothe ſo Sealed with the ſeale of anye Citie, Boroughe, or Towne corporate, ſhall not be ſearched, tryed, or viewed by anye Searcher or Sealer of anye other Citie, Boroughe, or Towne corporate, by vertue of his ſayde office, anye thynge in thys acte, or in the ſayde former eſtatute to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge.</p>
               <p>Item, be it further enacted by the auctoritie aforeſayde, that euerye perſonne and perſonnes, not dwellinge and inhabitinge within anye Citie, Borough, or corporate towne, and makinge any of the clothes or karſeys aforeſayde, maye lawfullye bringe the ſame to the nexte Citie, Boroughe, or corporate towne, where anye ſuche kynde of clothes or karſeys be or ſhalbe commonlye made, there to be ſealed in maner and fourme as is before expreſſed.</p>
               <p>Item, yf any Searcher or Sealer apointed, or to be appointed by vertue of this preſente acte, or of the ſayde former Statute, ſhall ſette the Seale of anye Citie, Boroughe, or Towne corporate, to any cloth, whiche ſhall not conteyne ſuche lengthe, weyghte, and breadth, as in the ſayde former Statute, or in this preſente acte is appoynted, that then the Mayer and Cominaltie, or Baylyf and Comynaltie, or other corporation of the Towneſhippe, by whatſoeuer name or names it or they ſhalbe incorporated, where ſuche cloothe, karfeye, fryſe, cotton, or rugge ſhalbe ſo ſealed, ſhall forfeyte and loſe the hole value of the cloth ſo fealed.</p>
               <p>It is alſo enacted by the aucthoritie of this preſente parlyamente, that the ſayd Searchers or Sealers, and euery one of them, ſhall haue full power and aucthoritie by vertue of this Acte, in the daye tyme, to entre into all and euerye houſe and houſes, of euerye perſonne or perſonnes, where he or they ſhall thinke mete to ſearche, and to trye all and euerye kynde of cloothes, karſeyes, fryſes, and rugges as they ſhall fynde defectyue, eyther in lengthe, breadthe, or weyghte, and the ſame to trye by water and weyghte, and alſoo to ſearche
<pb facs="tcp:180783:16"/>and ſeaſe as forfeyte all and euery cloth and clothes made of other co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours then in the ſayde former acte is appointed, fryars gray, crane co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loure, purple, and olde medley coulours, mooſte commonly vſed to be made before twenty yeares laſt paſt, onely excepted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> yf anye manner of perſonne or perſones, at any tyme after the fyrſte daye of Maye nexte comminge, ſhall deny, withſtande, or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde any cloth or clothes, karſeys, fryſes, rugges, or any of them, from the ſayde Sealers or Searchers, or any of them, or wyll not ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to enter into theyr ſhops, warehouſes, houſes or places wher theyr clothes, karſeys, fryſes, or rugges ſhall be, the ſame to be ſearched and tryed as is aforeſayde, that then euerye ſuche perſon or perſons ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyinge or withſtandinge, for euery ſuche withſtandyng, withholding or deniall, to forfeyt and loſe .x. poundes.</p>
               <p>Be it lykewyſe further enacted, that it ſhall not be lawfull for any of the ſayde Searchers, or Sealers, or anye other perſonne, to ſearche anye manner of wollen cloothe or karſeye, wherevnto the Seale of a Citie, Boroughe, or Towne corporate, ſhall be fyxed, within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon clothe markette of London, commonlye called Blackewell hall, or in anye common clothe faire, or clothe markette of anye other Citie, Boroughe, or Towne corporate, in and durynge the tyme of the fayre or markette, anye Acte or Statute to the contrarye notwythſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>BE IT</hi> further enacted, that all and euerye article, clauſe, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence in the ſaydeformer Statute made in the fyfte and ſixte yeare of the reygne of oure ſayde late Soueraigne Lorde, kynge Edwarde the Syxte, beinge not repugnaunte or contrary to anye article, clauſe or ſentence conteyned in this preſente acte, ſhall ſtande in full force and effecte.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes, that no perſone or perſonnes ſhall incurre the daunger, penaltye, or forfeyture limitted and appointed for any offence in the ſayde former acte, the which is already mittigated or otherwiſe appointed by this preſent acte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye clothier ſhall cauſe euerye clothe whiche he ſhall put to ſale, frome and after the feaſte of the Natiuitie of Sainte Iohn Baptiſte necte commynge, to be marked with the letter M. crowned, wrought in the cloth, vpon payne to forfeyte .xx.s. for euerye clothe, beynge ſolde or put to ſale by anye ſuche clothier after the ſayde feaſt not marked with the ſayde lettre M. as is aforeſaide.</p>
               <p>And moreouer be it enacted by the auctoritie aforeſayd, that no per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon or perſons after the ſaid feaſt of the natiuitie of S. Iohn Baptiſt, ſhal ſel or put to ſale within the realme of England, any coloured cloth of any other colour or colours then are hereafter in this act mentioned that is to ſaye, ſcarlet, red, crimſon, morrey, violet, pewke, brownble vs
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:180783:16"/>blacke, grene, yellowe, blue, oriche tawny, ruſſet, marble, gray, ſad new coulour Azner, watchet, ſhepes couloure, Lyon colour, motleye, yron gray, friers graye, crane colour, purple, and olde medley colour, moſte comonly vſed to be made aboue and before .xx. yeares laſt paſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> where as diuers aunciente cities, boroughes, and townes corporate within this realme of England, hath ben in times paſt well and ſubſtauncially inhabited, occupied, maynteyned, and vpholded, as well by reaſon of makinge of broad wollen clothes and karſeys, as alſo by diuers other artificers, inhabitinge then in the ſayd townes, at whiche time alſo the vyllages and huſbande townes flouryſſhed, and huſbandrye and tyllage was well mainteined, to the great benefite of the realme, and all the people therin, foraſmuch as diuers yeares paſte, ſuche perſons as do vſe the feat or miſtery of cloth making, not conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted to liue as artificers, and with the trade wherein they haue bene brought vp, do daylye plante themſelues in villages and townes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge no cities, boroughes, nor corporate townes, and there occupying the ſeate and place of a huſbandman, do not onely ingroſſe diuiers fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and paſtures into theyr handes, diſpleaſing the huſbandman, and decaying the ploughes and tyllages, but alſo drawe with them out of cities, boroughes, and townes corporate, all ſorte of artificers, wherby not onely diuers auncient cities, boroughes, and townes corporate, are vtterlye decayed, deſtroyed, and depopulated, but alſo huſbandrye and tyllages very muche decayed, to the great hurte, damage, and pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iudice of this realme, and the people therin, yf ſpedy remedy be not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſene. And foraſmuche alſo as the weauers and workemen of clothiers when they haue ben traded vp in the trade of cloth making and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge .iij. or .iiij. yeares, do forſake theyr mayſters, and do become clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiers and occupiers for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, without ſtocke, ſkyll, or knowledge to the great ſclaunder of the true cloth makinge, beſides a greate num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of inconueniences whiche do growe to the common welth of this realme therby, as dayly experience teacheth. Be it therefore ordeyned and enacted by thauctoritie of this preſent parliamente, that from and after the firſt daye of Maye next comminge, no perſonne or perſonnes whatſoeuer, ſhall vſe or exerciſe the feate or miſterye of makinge, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, or rowinge of wollen clothes, longe or ſhorte, or karſeyes, pyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned whites, or playne ſtreites, to thintente to put the ſame to ſale, but onely in a market towne where cloth hath commonlye ben vſed to be made by the ſpace of ten yeares laſt paſt, or in a citie, borough, or towne corporate, vpon payne of forfeyture for euery ſuche wollen cloth or kar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſey, made, wouen, or rowed out of ſuch citie, borough, towne corporate or market towne, fyue poundes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> it is further enacted, that from and after the fyrſt day of May no perſon whatſoeuer, ſhall weaue or make, or put to weauinge or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinge any wollen clothes or karſeys laſt rehearſed, to be ſolde, vnles
<pb facs="tcp:180783:17"/>ſuche perſon ſhall haue bene apprentice to the occupation of makinge, weauinge, and rowinge of clothe or carſeys, or haue ben exerciſed ther in by the ſpace of ſeuen yeares before, vpon payne of forfeyture of ſuche cloth, or the value thereof.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by the auctoritie aforeſayde, that all and euery paynes, penalties, and forfeytures to be due by force of this ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, or of the ſayd former acte being not otherwyſe appointed, ſhall be deuided equally into two partes, whereof the one ſhalbe to the quenes highnes, her heires and Succeſſours, and thother vnto him that will ſeaſe (in caſes where ſeaſer is limitted or appointed) or elles to him or them that wyll ſue for the ſame paynes, penalties, and forfeytures, or any of them, by action, byll, playnte, information, or otherwiſe, in anye courte of recorde, wherein no eſſoyne, protection, wager of lawe, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction ſhall be admitted, allowed, or obeyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, that it ſhalbe lawfull to anye perſon, nowe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge or exerciſinge the feate or miſterye of makynge, weauynge, or rowinge of clothe or karſey, to inhabite and dwell where he now doth, and there to vſe the makinge, weauinge, or rowinge of cloth or karſey, as he hath done heretofore, any thinge in this acte to the contrary not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandinge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, that it ſhall be laweful to all and euery perſon or perſons, whiche nowe do, or hereafter ſhall inhabit or dwell in anye of the Shires of Northwales or Southwales, Cheſſhyre, or Lancka ſhyre, Weſtmerland, Cumberland, Northumberlande, Byſhoprike of Durham, Cornewall, Suffolke, Kent, the towne of Goddelmyne in the countye of Surrey, or yorkeſhyre, beyng not within twelue myles of the citie of yorke or in any the townes or vyllages nere adioyninge the water of Stroude in the county of Glouceſter, where clothes hath ben vſually made by the ſpace of twenty yeares laſt paſt, and hauynge bene prentice to the occupation of clothe makinge, or exerciſed in the ſame by the ſpace of ſeuen yeares, to ſet vp, vſe, and exerciſe the feate or myſtery of makinge, weauinge, or rowinge of clothe oute of a citie, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough, or markette towne, as heretofore they myghte haue done, anye thinge in this acte to the contrary not withſtandinge.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo, that it ſhalbe lawfull to any perſon, nowe vſynge or exerciſinge, or that hath vſed or exerciſed the feate or myſterye of clothe makinge, the ſame to contynus, vſe, and exercyſe, althoughe he hathe not bene therevnto apprentice, or haue exerciſed the ſame by the ſpace of ſeuen yeares, anye thinge in this Acte to the contrary notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes &amp; be it alſo further enacted by thaucthoritie afore ſayd, that it ſhall be lawful to euery perſon and perſons, to ſell &amp; put to ſale by retaile or otherwyſe, all &amp; euery ſuche coloured cloth and clothes as he or they nowe haue, as frelye as he or they maye lawfully ſell anye
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:180783:17"/>clothes of the collours in thys preſent acte allowed to be ſolde, vntyll the feaſt of Saynt Mychaell tharchaungell nect enſuyng, Thys acte or the ſayd former ſtatute, in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ACTE</hi> to enquyre of the behauor of french men being Denizens.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .vi. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N THEIR</hi> moſt humble wyſe, ſhewen vn: to your moſt royall Maieſtie, the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and all other your moſt louyng and obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Subiectes, the commons in your moſte high courte of parliament aſſembled, that where at a parlyament hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtminſter, in the .xiii. yere of the reigne of king Rychard the ſecond, it was for ſondrye good conſiderations, ordeyned and enacted, that no alyen frenchman, ſhould haue or enioye any bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce within thys realme, but that they ſhoulde be auoyded forthewith out of the ſame, before a certeyne time in the ſayde acte limytted, as in the ſame acte is more playnely conteyned. And that at what hower, any pryores alyens, conuentuall or other benefice or offyce, geuen by tytle of the kyng, did voyde by laches, or deathe of the ſayde pryor, and other occupyers, that than (duryng the warres) honeſt perſons Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe, ſhould be put therin, in the place of them to accomplyſhe diuyne ſeruyce, and none of the enemyes aforeſayd. And yet notwithſtandyng the ſayd ordynaunce, the ſayde alyens frenchmen, by euell imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and brocage, to contynue the euyll myſchyfes of the ſayd ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce dyd purchaſe letters patentes of the kynge to be denizens, and lyeges of the kynge, and ſo ſware to continue the ſame, to thuitent to occupye and enioye the ſayd benefices, and by that meanes dyd occupye greate number of benefices, agaynſte the ſayd ordynaunce, by meanes where of the alyens french were increſed, to the deminiſhing of the Subiects of the kynge and the treaſure of the kynge and the Realme dyd carrye oute of thys Realme, and the councell of the kynge did diſcouer to the enemyes of fraunce, to the great damage of the kyng and the Realme. For remedy whereof at a parliament holden at Weſtminſter, the fyrſte yeare of the reigne, of the moſt worthy prynce of famous memory, king Henry the fyfte, the ſame king conſideryng the myſchyfes aforeſaid, by thaucthoritie of the ſame parlyamente, wylled that the ſayd ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhould be ſaufely holden and kepte, and put in due executyon, (certaine pryor aliens excepted) and that they ſhoulde put in ſuretye, not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer nor cauſe to be dyſcouered, the councell nor the ſecretes of the
<pb facs="tcp:180783:18"/>Realme. And where ſythence the makynge of the ſayde Actes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyamente, ſondrye other good lawes and actes, haue benne made, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in the tyme of kynge Rycharde the thyrde, as in the tyme of kyng Henrye the Eyghte, in whych actes, it is prouyded, lymytted, ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and declared, vnder what ſorte the ſayde Alyens, and euerye of them ſhoulde vſe themſelfes within thys Realme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where alſo by one acte of Parlyament made at Weſtmynſter, in the two and thyrtye yeare of the raygne of the ſayde late kyng Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye the Eyghte, it was enacted amongeſt other thynges conteyned in the ſayde acte that al maner of Straungers borne oute of hys gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces obeyſaunce, whyche before that tyme were made Denyzens, or that after that ſhoulde be made Denyzens, from and after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyrſt daye of September then nexte commynge, ſhoulde be bounden, and be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyente, by, and vnto all the foreſayde actes and ſtatutes, made in the fyrſte yeare of the ſayde kynge Rycharde the thyrd, and in the fourtene and one and twentye yeares of the ſayde kynge Henrye the Eyghte, and to all the contentes of the ſame, and to all other actes, and ſtatutes of thys Realme before that tyme, made or from henceforth to be made. And that alſo in al and euery Letters Patentes, of or for anye Deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen from and after the laſte daye of the ſame Parlyamente, ſoo holden in the ſayde two and thyrtye yeare, to be made to anye ſtraunger, not beynge borne vnder the kynges obeyſaunce, there ſhoulde be contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in euerye ſuche Letters Patentes, a prouyſo that he or they to whome ſuche Letters Patentes, ſhalbe ſoo made and graunted, ſhoulde be bounden and be obedyente by and vnto all the actes, and Statutes, of thys Realme, as is aforeſayde, and to all and euerye the contentes of the ſame, as by the ſame actes more playnelye it dothe and may appeare.</p>
               <p>Yet Sythence the makynge of the ſayde ſeuerall Actes, a greate number and multytude of the frenche nacyon, haue aryued into thys Realme, aſwell nere to the Seaſyde, as elſe where, and vnder a fayned falſe and vntrue promyſe or othe of alegyence, and faythe promyſed to be by them borne to thys Realme, they haue of late yeares ſithence the ſayde two and thyrtye yeare of the Reygne of the ſayde late kynge Henrye the Eyghte, by ſynyſter and vndue meanes obteyned, dyuers and ſondrye ſeuerall Letters Patentes, whereby they be made Deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens, and by force thereof doo emoye the lybertyes and pryueleges of thys Realme, and yet contrarye to the true meanynge of the ſayde Letters Patentes, in theyr condytions and behaunures, they doo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne Frenche, and daylye from tyme to tyme do diſcouer the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell, ſtate and priuities of this Realme, and compaſſe, Imagyne, and procure ſondrye myſchyfes and damage to be done by the frenche na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:180783:18"/>to thys Realme, contrarye to the ſayde Actes of Parlyamente, and contrarye to their ſayde letters patentes, and the prouyſo contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOR</hi> remedy whereof, and for the auoydyng of the imminent peryll that for want of due prouydence, may enſue to your moſt royal perſon, (whome our Lord GOD, longe preſerue to reygne ouer vs) and to thys your hyghnes Realme, by the malicious and ſecrete practyſes of the ſayd Denizens, we moſt humblye beſech your moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, to haue vigilante care and tender conſyderatyon, of youre owne ſuretye, and preſeruation of thys youre Realme, and hauynge good and ſure experience of your accuſtomed honorable and mercyfull diſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſition and inclination, do alſo mooſte humblye beſech the ſame, that by youre royall aſſente, it maye be enacted by thaucthoritye of this preſent parlyament, that al french men, and all and euery other perſonne and perſonnes, borne in any place, beyond the Seas, which at the tyme of the byrth of any ſuch perſon or perſones, was vnder the french kinges obeyſaunce, not beynge Denizens, other then ſuche as the kynge and Quenes highnes, or the quene onely ſhall ſpecyally lycence, lymit, and appoynte to remayne within thys Realme, ſhall departe oute of thys Realme, and out and from the dominions and terrytories of the ſame, there to remayne and contynue withoute retorne into thys Realme, durynge the time and contmuaunce of the warres, betwene the french kynge and oure Soueraygne Ladye the quene, or her heires or ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoures. And that our Soueraygne Lorde and Ladye, the kynge and the queene, or her hyghnes onelye, by the aucthoritie of thys Acte, by their letters patentes, vnder the great Seale of Englande, ſhall and maye haue full power and aucthoritie, from time to tyme, duryng the lyfe of the quenes hyghnes (whych almyghty GOD long proſper and contynue) after offyce founde or other due profe, of the myſdeamenor of anye ſuch Denizen, committed contrary to the lawes of this realme to repeale and make voyde all and ſynguler letters patentes, or aſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of them, as to her hyghnes ſhall ſeme good, made ſythence the ſayd two and thyrtye yeare of the Raygne of Kynge Henrye theyghte, to anye alyen or ſtraunger borne frenche, and vnder the obeyſaunce of of the frenche kynge, concernynge onelye the makynge of ſuche alyen, or Straunger Denyzen, the ſame Letters Patentes of repeale, to be proclaimed and vſed in maner and fourme folowynge, that is to ſaye, that euery ſuch Letters Patents of repeale, ſhal conteine the names &amp; ſurnames of euery ſuch alien Straunger, whoſe letters Patents ſhal ſoo be repealed, and ſhalbe ſolempnlye and openly redde and proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the kynge and Queenes Courte of Chauncerye, betwene the howres of nine, and a leuen, before none, one day in anye one terme to be kepte at Weſtmynſter, and in ſuche and aſmanye termes
<pb facs="tcp:180783:19"/>and counties of this realme, as ſhalbe limitted, or appoynted, or other wiſe ſeme mete to the quenes maieſtie, at any tyme hereafter, durynge her highnes ſayd lyfe, and that al and euery ſuch letters patentes, to be repealed in maner and forme aforeſayde, from, and immediately after xxx. dayes nexte enſuynge ſuch repeale, ſhall touchyng onelye the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of ſuch alyen or ſtraunger denizen, be voyde and of none effecte, and not before.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> be it further enacted by thauchorytie aforeſayd, that ſuch ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens and ſtraungers denizens, whoſe patentes the queenes hyghnes hereafter ſhal fortune to allowe or confirme, or whom her hyghnes ſhal lycence to remayne and tarry in thys Realme, ſhalbe bounden to the kynge and Queenes maieſties, by recogniſaunce, not to dyſcouer nor cauſe to be diſcouered the councell nor the ſecreates of thys Realme, and further to be bounde and obedyente vnto and by the lawes and ſtatutes of the ſame, and yf any ſuch alyen borne frenche, and vnder the obeyſaunce of the french kyng, as is aforeſayde, ſhall refuſe to know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege any ſuch recogniſaunce, that then the ſayde confirmation, allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce, and lycence, ſhalbe voyde and of none effect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes that yf any ſuch alyen as is aforeſayd, ſhal haue purchaſed any Manour, Landes, Tenementes, or hereditamentes, of anye eſtate of inherytaunce, within thys Realme, ſythence the tyme that he was made denizen, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> any Manor, Landes, Tenementes, or hereditamentes within this realme, were gyuen to any ſuch alien, of any eſtate of inherytaunce, by any letters patents, or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame letters patentes, whereby he was made denizen, that the ſame Manor, lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, tenementes, and hereditamentes, after the deceaſe of ſuche alien, whoſe letters patentes, of makyng denizen, ſhalbe as is aforeſaid, repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſhall and maye diſcende, remayne or come vnto ſuche his heyre or heyres, as bene borne within thys realme, and as be inheritable to the ſame, or to ſuch other perſon or perſonnes that ſhoulde by the lawes of thys realme, haue and enioye the ſame, or any part thereof, yf thys acte or no ſuch repeale had bene made in ſuch maner and forme as thoughe no ſuch repeale were had or made, the ſame repeale or any thing in this acte to the contrary not withſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo that it ſhalbe lawefull to the Quenes maieſtie, her heyres and ſucceſſoures, immediatelye from and after the departure of euery ſuch denizen, out of thys Realme, to receyue and take the cleare yerely iſſues, reuenues, and proffyts of al ſuch Manours, Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes, Rentes, Fees, Annuityes, and Heredytamentes, whereof any ſuch Denyzen were ſeaſſed or hadde at the tyme of thys acte, or at the tyme of hys departure oute of thys Realme, as is aforeſayde, for and durynge the lyfe of euerye ſuche Denizen, in as ample and large maner and forme, and in ſuche qualytye, condytyon, and degree, as
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:180783:19"/>anye ſuche deniſen mighte lawfullye haue receyued and taken at the tyme of the makyng of this preſent acte, and not otherwiſe, any thinge in this acte conteyned to the contrary notwithſtandinge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ACTE</hi> to make vp the Iury with circumſtantibus, where the kynge and Quenes maieſties or the Quenes maieſtie is a party.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .vii. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE</hi> in the parliament holden at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter the .xiiij. day of Ianuary in the .xxxv. yeare of the reygne of the mooſt noble and victorious Prince king Henry the eyght, late kynge of Englande, amongeſte other thinges it was enacted and eſtablyſhed, for the ſpedye tryall of Iſſues ioyned betwene party and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, in anye of the kynges courtes of recorde holden at Weſtminſter, to be tryed by the verdicte of twelue menne, before the Iuſtices of aſſiſe, or <hi>niſi prius,</hi> that in euerye wrytte of <hi>habeascorpora,</hi> or <hi>diſtringas,</hi> with a <hi>niſi prius,</hi> delyuered of recorde to the Sheryffe or other miniſter or miniſters to whome the makynge of the retourne ſhall apparteyne, where a full Iurye ſhall not appeare before the Iuſtices of aſſiſe or
<hi>niſi prius,</hi> or elles where after appearaunce of a full Iurye, by chalenge of any of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, the Iurye is lyke to remayne vntaken for default of the Iurours, that then the ſame Iuſtices vpon requeſt made by the partyes playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfe or demaundaunte, ſhall haue aucthoritie by vertue of the ſayd act, to comaunde the Sherif or other miniſter or miniſters, to whome the makynge of the ſayde retourne ſhall appertayne, to name and apoynte as often as nede ſhall requyre, ſo many of ſuche other hable perſones of the ſayde countye then preſent at the ſayde aſſiſes or niſi prius, as ſhall make vp a ſull Iurye, whiche perſones ſo to be named and enpanelled by ſuche Sherif or other miniſter or miniſters, ſhalbe added to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer pannell, and theyr names annexed to the ſame, as by the ſayde act more at large appeareth, whiche Statute was made to endure tyll the ende of the nexte parlyamente, and after was and is frome tyme to tyme contynued, and doeth nowe remayne, ſtande, and be in effecte, whiche acte doth not extende to any Iury enpanelled, to trye an yſſue ioyned betwene the kynge and the partye, or betwene ſuche as purſue any matter for the kynge and them ſelues.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore enacted, ordeyned, and eſtablyſhed by the kynge and Quenes maieſties the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the
<pb facs="tcp:180783:20"/>commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, and by the aucthoritie of the ſame, that frome and after the lyrſte daye of Iune next cominge, the Iuſtices of aſſiſe and <hi>niſi prius,</hi> before whome anye tryall ſhall be made, by vertue of anye wrytte of
<hi>habeas corpora,</hi> or <hi>diſtringas,</hi> with a <hi>niſiprius,</hi> where a full Iurye ſhall not appeare, or after appearaunce of a full Iurye by chalenge the Iurye is lyke to remayne vntaken, for defaulte of Iuriours, ſhall haue aucthoritie by vertue of this Acte, vpon requeſt made for the kynge and Quene her heyres or Succeſſoures, by anye aucthoriſed therevnto, or aſſigned by the Iuſtices of the Courte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whome the ſayde enqueſte ſhall be taken, or vppon requeſte to be made by the partye that foloweth as well for the kynge and Queene, her heyres and Succeſſours, as for hym ſelfe vppon anye penall Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute or hys or theyr Attourney, to commaunde the Sheryffe, or other miniſter or miniſters, to whome the makynge of the ſayde retourne ſhall appertayne, to name and appoynte, as often as nede ſhall require ſo manye of ſuche other hable perſonnes of the ſayde Countye then preſente at the ſayde aſſiſes, or <hi>niſi prius,</hi> and to adde and annexe the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes to the former pannell, as ſhall make vppe a full Iurye of twelue menne for the tryall of euerye ſuche Iſſue. And that all and euerye clauſe, ſentence, article, and prouiſo compriſed in the ſayde former acte, ſhall be taken, enterpreted, and expounded, to geue the lyke and the ſame aduauntage and commoditie to the kynge and Quenes maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, her heyres and Succeſſoures, and all ſuche perſonne and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonnes as ſhall purſue anye action, byll, playnte, or information for the kynge and Quenes maieſties, her heyres and Succeſſours onelye, or for them and the partye, as the partye playntyfe in anye other action ſhoulde or myghte haue by vertue of the ſayde Acte, in ſuche fourme and condition, to all intentes and purpoſes, as yf ſuch actions or ſuites for the kynge hadde bene ſpecially and perticulerly mentioned and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the ſayde Acte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN</hi> Acte for the puniſhemente of ſuche as ſhall take awaye maydens that be inheritours, beynge within the age of ſixtene yeares, or that marye them without the conſente of theyr parentes.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .vij. chapter.</head>
               <pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:180783:20"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE</hi> maydens and women chyldren of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, gentlemen, and others, as well ſuche as be heyres apparaunte to theyr aunceſtours, as others, ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uynge lefte vnto them by theyr father or other aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre and freindes, landes, tenementes, and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, or other greate ſubſtaunces in goodes and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telles moueable, for and to thintente to aduaunce them in marryage ſomewhat lyke, accordynge to theyr degrees, and as myght be mooſte for their ſuertye and comforte, as well for theim ſelues, as of all other theyr freinds and kynneſfolkes, be often tymes vnwares to theyr ſayd freindes or kynneſfolkes, by flattery, tryfelynge gyftes, and fayre pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of manye vnthryftye and lighte perſonages, and thereto by the intreatye of perſones of lewde demeanoure and others, that for rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des bye and ſell the ſayde maydens and chyldren, ſecretlye allured and wonne to contracte matrimonye with the ſayde vnthryftye and lyght perſonages, and therevpon either with ſlyghte or force, oftentymes be taken and conueyed awaye from theyr ſayde parentes, freindes, or kynneſfolkes, to the high diſpleaſure of almyghtye God, diſpargement of the ſayde chyldren, and the extreame contynuall heuynes of al theyr freindes, whiche vngodlye dealynge for lacke of wholeſome lawes to the redreſſe thereof, remayneth a great familier and common miſcheife in this oure common welth.</p>
               <p>For remedye whereof be it enacted by the kynge and Quenes ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſties, the lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and the commons of this pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent parliamente aſſembled, and by the aucthoritie of the ſame, that it ſhall not be lawfull to anye perſon or perſons, to take or conuey awaye or cauſe to be taken or conueyed awaye any mayde or woman chylde vnmaried, beynge within the age of ſixtene yeares, out, of, or from the poſſeſſion, cuſtodye, or gouernaunce, and agaynſt the wyll of the father of ſuche mayde or woman chylde, or of ſuche perſonne or perſonnes to whome the father of ſuche maide or woman chylde, by his laſte wyll and teſtamente, or by any other acte in his life tyme hath or ſhall apoint aſſigne, bequeth, geue, or graunte the ordre, kepynge, education, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernaunce of ſuche mayde or woman chylde, excepte ſuche takyng and conueyinge awaye as ſhalbe had, made, or done, by, or for ſuche perſon or perſonnes, as without fraude or couyn be, or then ſhall be the maſter or myſtres of ſuche mayde or woman chylde, or the gardeine in ſocage or gardeyne in chyualrye, of or to ſuche mayde or woman chylde.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that yf anye perſon or perſons aboue the age of .xiiij. yeares, ſhall from and after the fyrſte daye of Apryll nexte commynge, vnlawfullye take or conueye or cauſe to be taken or conueyed any mayde or woman chylde vnmaried beyng within the age of .xvi. yeares, out, of, or from the poſſeſſion, and agaynſt the wyll of the father or mother of ſuche chylde, or oute or from
<pb facs="tcp:180783:21"/>the poſſeſſion, and agaynſt the wyll of ſuche perſonne or perſonnes as then ſhall happen to haue by anye lawfull wayes or meanes, the ordre kepynge, education, or gouernaunce of anye ſuche mayden or woman chylde, that then euery ſuche perſon &amp; perſons (ſo offendinge) beynge thereof lawfully attaynted, or conuicted by the ordre and due courſe of the lawes of this realme, other then ſuche of whom ſuche perſon taken awaye ſhall holde any landes or tenementes by knightes ſeruyce, ſhal haue and ſuffer impriſonmente of his and theyr bodies by the ſpace of two whole yeares without bayle or maynprice, or elles ſhall pay ſuche fine for his or theyr ſayde offence, as ſhalbe aſſeſſed by the counſel of the Quenes highnes her heyres or ſucceſſours in the Starre Chambre at Weſtminſter.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by the auctoritie aforeſayde, that yf anye ſuch perſon or perſones after the ſayd day, ſhall ſo take away, or cauſe to be taken awaye as is aforeſayde, and deflower anye ſuche mayde or woman chylde as is aforeſayde, or ſhall agaynſte the wyll, or vnknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of or to the father of any ſuche mayde or woman chylde, yf the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be in life, or agaynſte the wyll, or vnknowinge of or the mother of any ſuche mayde or woman childe (hauinge the cuſtodye and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of ſuche chylde, yf the father be deade) by ſecrete letters, meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, or otherwiſe, contracte matrimony with any ſuch mayden or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man chylde, except ſuche contractes of matrimonie as ſhall be made by the conſente of ſuche perſon or perſonnes as by the title of wardſhippe ſhall then haue, or be intituled to haue the mariage of ſuche mayde or woman chylde, that then euerye ſuche perſon or perſons ſo offendyng, beynge thereof lawfully conuicted as is aforeſaid, ſhal ſuffer impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of his or theyr bodies by the ſpace of fyue yeares, without bayle or mayneprice, or elles ſhall paye ſuche fyne for his or theyr ſayd offence as ſhalbe aſſeſſed by the ſayd counſel in the ſaid ſtarre Chambre. The one moytye of all whiche fynes ſhall be to the kynge and Quenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties, her heyres and Succeſſoures, the other moytye to the parties greued.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by the ſayde aucthoritie, that the kynge and Quenes highnes honourable Councell of the Starre Chamber by byll of complaynte, or information, and Iuſtices of aſſiſe by inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition or indictemente, ſhall haue aucthoritie by vertue of this acte, to heare and determine the ſayde offences, vpon euerye whiche indicte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and inquiſitions ſuche proceſſe ſhalbe awarded and lye, as v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon an indictement of treſpace at the comon lawe.</p>
               <p>And further be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that if any woman chylde or mayden, beynge aboue the age of twelue yeares, and vnder the age of ſixtene yeares, do at any time conſent or agree to ſuch perſonne that ſo ſhall make any contracte of matrimonye, contrarye to
<pb n="xix" facs="tcp:180783:21"/>the forme and effecte of this eſtatute, that then the next of the kynne of the ſame woman chyld or mayde, to whom thinheritaunce ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cende, retorne, or come after the deceaſe of the ſame woman chylde and mayde, ſhall from the tyme of ſuch aſſent and agrement, haue, holde, &amp; enioye al ſuch la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, and hereditaments, as the ſame woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chylde and mayden, hadde in poſſeſſion, reuertion, or remaynder, at the tyme of ſuch aſſent and agrement, durynge the lyfe of ſuch perſon that ſhall ſo contracte matrimony. And after the deceaſe of ſuche perſon ſoo contractynge matrimony, that then the ſayd landes, tenementes, and heredytamentes, ſhall diſcend, reuert, remayne, and come to ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons as they ſhoulde haue done in caſe thys acte had neuer byn hadne made, other then to him onely that ſo ſhal contracte matrimony.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted, that this act nor any thing therin conteyned, ſhall extende to take awaye or diminyſhe any lyber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye, cuſtome, or aucthoritie touchynge or concernyng anye Orpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or Orphantes, whych nowe be, or hereafter ſhalbe within the Citye of London, or any other citie, boroughe, or towne, where Orphantes are commonlye vſed to be prouyded for, either by graunte, or by cuſtome, but that the lorde Maire of the ſaid citie of London, and the aldermen of the ſame for the time being, and al and euery other heade offycer or officers, of anye other citie, borough, or towne, wher ſuch Orphantes be prouyded for, ſhall and maye haue and take like rule, order, kepynge and charge of ſuch orphant and orphantes, and of all their landes, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nementes, goodes, and cattels, as heretofore they or any of them law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullye had or vſed, or lawfully might haue had and vſed, yf this act had not bene made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ACTE</hi> for the continuation of certayne Statutes.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .ix. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE IN THE PARLIAMENT</hi> BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon and holden at London, the thyrd day of Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, in the .xxi. yere of the reigne of our moſt drede Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lord of moſt famous memory, kyng Henrye the eight, and from thence adiourned to Weſtminſter, and there holden &amp; continued by diuers prorogations, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the diſſolution therof, one acte was made and eſtabliſhed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint of caryage &amp; conueying of horſes and mares out of this realme. And alſo one other act was ther made for the true winding of wolles. And one other act was there made to reſtraine kylling of wainlinges, bullockes. Stiers &amp; heyfers, being vnder the age of two yeres, which ſaid ſeueral actes were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made to endure &amp; continue vnto the nexte parliamente, as by the ſaide ſeuerall actes, more playnelye appeareth.
<pb facs="tcp:180783:22"/>And where alſo in the ſame Parliamente one other acte was made and eſtablyſhed for attayntes, to be ſued for the puniſhment of periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye vpon vntrue verdictes, which acte laſt before rehearſed, was then made and ordeyned to continue and endure to the laſte day of the next parliamente, as by the ſame acte more playnely at large is ſhewed and maye appeare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where alſo in the parlyament begonne and holden at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynſter the eyghte daye of Iune, in the eyght and twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty yeare of the reygne of oure ſayde moſt dreade Soueraygne Lorde, kynge Henrye the eight, and there continued and kept vntyll the diſſolution thereof. It was ordeyned and enacted, that all and ſynguler the ſayde actes aboue remembred, and euerye of them, ſhoulde continue and endure in their force and ſtrength, and alſo be obſerued and kepte vntyl the laſte daye of the nexte parliament, as by the ſame acte amongeſt other thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges therein conteyned, more playnelye appeareth. And where alſo in the Parliamente begonne and holden at Weſtmynſter, the eyght and twentye daye of Apryll, in the one and thyrtye yeare of the reygne of oure ſayde late mooſte dreade Soueraygne Lorde, kynge Henrye the eyght, and there continued vntyll the eyght and twentye day of Iune then nexte folowynge, it was ordeyned and enacted by thaucthorytie of the ſame parlyamente, that all and ſinguler the ſayde ſeuerall actes aboue remembred, and euery of them, and al clauſes, artycles, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyſions in them, and euerye of them conteyned, ſhoulde contynue and endure in their force and ſtrength, and alſo be obſerued and kept vntill the laſte daye of the nexte Parlyamente, as by the ſame Acte amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges other thynges therein conteyned, more playnelye appeareth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where in the Parlyamente holden at Weſtmynſter, in the fiue and thyrty yeare of the Reygne of oure ſayd late Soueraygne Lord, kynge Henrye the Eyghte, one acte was made for the preſeruation of woodes, to endure for ſeuen yeares then nexte folowynge, and from thence to thende of the nexte Parlyamente, as by the ſame acte more playnelye it dothe and maye appeare. And where alſo at the Parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente holden at Weſtmynſter, in the ſeuen and thyrtye yeare of the raygne of the ſayde late kynge Henry the eyghte, and there continued and kepte vntyll the diſſolution thereof, it was ordeyned and enac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that all and ſinguler the ſayde actes aboue mentioned, and euerye of them (excepte the ſayde acte made for the preſeruation of woodes, as is aforeſayde) ſhoulde contynue and endure in their force and ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthe, and alſo be obſerued and kepte vntyll the laſte daye of the nexte Parlyamente, then nexte folowynge, as by the ſame Acte amonges other thynges therein conteyned, more playnelye appeareth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where alſo at the Seſſyon of the Parlyamente ended at
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:180783:22"/>Weſtminſter the .xiiij. daye of Marche, in the thyrd yeare of the raygne of oure late Soueraigne Lorde kynge Edwarde the Sixte, one acte was made for the true courryinge of leather, which acte was made to endure to the ende of the nexte parliaments, as by the ſame acte more playnelye appeareth.</p>
               <p>And where alſo at the Seſſion of a parliament ended at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the fyrſte daye of February, in the fourth yeare of the raigne of our ſayde late Soueraigne Lorde kynge Edwarde the Sixte, one Acte was then and there made concerninge the buyinge of rother beaſtes. And alſo one other acte was then and there made, touchinge the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge and ſellynge of butter and cheſe, whiche ſayde ſeuerall actes were then and there made to endure and contynue vnto the ende of the next parlyamente, as by the ſame ſeuerall actes more at large it doeth and maye appeare.</p>
               <p>And where alſo at the Seſſion of a parliamente by prorogation holden at Weſtminſter the .xxiii. daye of Ianuarye in the fyfte yeare of the raygne of our ſayd late Soueraygne Lord kyng Edwarde the Syxte, one other acte was then and there made, agaynſte regratours and foreſtallers, to endure vnto the ende of the nexte parliamente, whiche all and ſynguler the ſayde actes aboue mentioned together, with the ſayde acte for preſeruation of woodes, at a parliamente hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at Weſtminſter the fyrſte daye of Marche, in the ſeuenth yeare of the raygne of oure ſayde Soueraygne Lorde kynge Edwarde the Sixte, and there continued and diſſolued the laſte day of the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Marche, and all clauſes, articles, and prouiſions in theim, and euerye of them conteyned, were there reuiued and continued, to ſtand in theyr force and ſtrengthe vntyll the laſte daye of the nexte parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente.</p>
               <p>And where alſo at the Seſſion of a parlyament holden by proroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at Weſtminſter the .xxiiij. daye of October, in the fyrſte yeare of the raigne of oure mooſte gratious Soueraigne Ladye the Queenes maieſtie, and there continued and kepte vntyll the diſſolution there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, one acte was there made and eſtablyſhed, agaynſte vnlawfull and rebellious aſſembles, to endure to the ende of the nexte parliamente, as by the ſame acte more playnelye doth and maye appeare.</p>
               <p>And where alſo at the ſame Seſſion of parliament laſt before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, all and ſinguler the actes aboue mentioned, and before that tyme continued at ſondry parliamentes, as is aforeſayde, and all clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, articles, and prouiſions in theim and euerye of theim conteyned, were there reuiued and continued to ſtande in their force and ſtrength vnto the laſt day of the next parliament.</p>
               <p>And where alſo at a parliament begon and holden at Weſtminſter
<pb facs="tcp:180783:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>the .xij. daye of Nouember, in the fyrſte and ſeconde yeares of the reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of oure mooſt gratious Soueraigne Lorde and Ladye the kyng and Quenes maieſties, and there contynued and kepte vnto the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the ſame, beynge the ſixtenth daye of Ianuarye then nexte enſuynge, one acte was then and there made agaynſte ſeditious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and rumours, to endure to the ende of the nexte parliamente, as by the ſame acte moore playnelye it doeth and maye appeare. And where alſo in the ſayde Parlyamente laſte before recited, all and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler the Actes aboue mentioned that were before that tyme conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued at ſondrye parliamentes as is aforeſayde, and all clauſes articles and prouiſions in them and euerye of them conteined, were by auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the ſayde parliamente, there reuiued and continued to ſtande in theyr force and ſtrengthe, vnto the laſte daye of the nexte Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where at a parliamente begonne and holden at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the one and twentye daye of October, in the ſeconde and thyrde yeares of the reygnes of our aforeſayde Soueraygne Lorde and La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye the kynge and Quenes maieſties, and there continued vntyll the diſſolution of the ſame, beynge the nynth daye of December then next enſuinge, one Acte was then and there made for the kepynge of milche kyne, and for the breadynge and rearinge of calues. And one other Acte for the reedifyinge of decayed houſes of huſbandrye, and for the encreaſe of Tyllage, the ſayde three ſeuerall actes to endure tyl the laſt day of the next parliament. Foraſmuche as all and ſinguler the ſayde ſeuerall actes aboue mentioned be good and beneficiall for the comon wealth of this realme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>BE IT</hi> therefore enacted, ordeyned, and eſtablyſhed by the king and Quenes maieſties, oure Soueraygne Lorde and Ladye, with the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente of the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſente parliament aſſembled, and by the aucthoritie of the ſame, that all and ſinguler the ſayde ſeuerall actes and eſtatutes aboue mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and rehearſed, and euerye of theim, and all clauſes, articles, and prouiſions in them and euery of them conteyned, ſhall be reuiued, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued, ſtande, and endure in theyr full force and ſtrength, to all inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, and ſhall be obſerued and kepte in all thinges vntyll the laſte daye of the nexte parliamente.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſaid that this preſente acte of continuaunce of ſtatutes, or any thinge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in conteyned, ſhall not in any wyſe extende, to repeale or make voyde one acte of parliamente, entituled, an acte for the ſale of dyuers wynes and ſpyces broughte in by marchauntes, made and ordeyned in this preſente parliamente, nor any clauſe, article, or matter therein contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but that the ſame Acte, and euerye thynge therein conteyned ſhall be of as good ſtrengthe, force, and effecte, to all intentes,
<pb n="xxi" facs="tcp:180783:23"/>and purpoſes as if thys acte of continuaunce of ſtatutes, had not bene had nor made, any thynge herein conteyned to the contrarye in anye wyſe notwithſtandynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where in the parliamente begonne and holden at Weſtmyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the .xxi. day of October, in the ſecond &amp; third yeares of the reignes of our ſayde Soueraygne lord and lady, kyng Philippe and Queene Mary, and there continued and kept vntyll the .ix. daye of December, then next enſuynge, one acte was then and there made, entytuled, an acte for the releife of the pore, the ſayd acte to endure to the latter ende of the fyrſt ſeſſion of the next Parliament. Foraſmuch as the ſayd acte is good and beneficiall for the comen welth of this realme, be it there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore enacted, ordeyned, and eſtablyſhed, by the aucthoritie of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Parliament, that the ſayde acte, laſte aboue mentioned and rehearſed, and all clauſes, articles, and prouyſions in the ſame conteyned, ſhalbe reuyued, contynued, ſtande and endure, in full force and ſtrength, to all intentes and purpoſes, and ſhalbe obſerued and kept, in al thynges, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyll the laſt day of the next parlyament.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ACTE</hi> for the confirmation of the Subſedy of the cleargye.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .x. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HERE THE PRELATES</hi> and Clergy of the prouynce of Canterburye, haue moſt louyngly and lyberally for certayne conſiderations, geuen and grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the kyng and quenes Maieſties, a Subſedye of eyghte ſhyllynges of the pounde, to be taken and leuied of all and ſynguler the Spiritual promocions, within the ſame prouynce, durynge the tearme of foure yeares now next enſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inge, in ſuche certayne maner and forme, and with diuers exceptions and prouyſyons ſpecyfyed and conteyned in a certayne inſtrument, by them thereof made and delyuered to the queenes hyghnes, vnder the Seale of the moſt reuerend father in God, Reginald Poole Cardinal Archbyſhoppe of Canterburye, and prymate of al Englande, as in the ſame inſtrument exhibyted in thys preſent parliament, more playnelye doth appeare, the tenor whereof enſueth in theſe wordes.</p>
               <p>The Prelates and clergye of the prouynce of Canterburye, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge lawefullye congregated and aſſembled in a conuocation or Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node vpon greate and weyghtye cauſes to them purpoſed, and amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt them well wayed and debated, conſideryng their moſte bounden duetyes to the kynge and quenes Maieſtyes, the great and ample be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefytes they haue receyued of their munificency and bountyfull good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for an euident declaration of their good hartes and myndes, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyally
<pb facs="tcp:180783:24"/>nowe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the imminent neceſſitie for the defence of the Realme requyreth preſente ayde and remedye, with one vnyforme agreament, accorde, and conſent together, with mooſte hartye good wyll, haue gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and graunted, and by theſe preſentes, doo geue and graunte to the kynge and Queenes Maieſtyes, one entyre Subſedye, in manner and forme folowynge. That is to ſaye, that euerye Archebyſhoppe. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe, Abbotte, Pryor, Abbateſſe, or Pryoreſſe, Deane, Archedeacon, Prebendarye, Prouoſt, mayſter of Colledge, mayſter of Hoſpytalles, parſon and Vycare, and euerye other perſon and perſons, of whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer name or degree he or they be, enioyinge anye Spyrytuall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocyon or other temporall poſſeſſyons, to the ſame Spyrytuall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions annexed, nowe not deuyded nor ſeperated by Acte of Parly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amente or otherwyſe, from the poſſeſſyon of the Cleargye, ſhall paye vnto the kynge and Queenes Maieſtyes, for euerye pounde that he or they maye yearelye dyſpende by reaſonne of the ſayde Spyrytuall promotion, the ſumme of Eyghte ſhyllynges. And for the true and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne knoweledge of the yearelye vallewe of the ſayde promotyons, and euerye of them, whereof payment ſhalbe made, the rate, taxation, valuation, and eſtymation, remaynynge of Recorde, in the kynge and quenees Maieſtyes late courte of the fyrſte Frutes and Tenthes, and nowe in their Courte of the Eſchequer, for the paymente of the Diſme of the Cleargye, concernynge all ſuche promotions, as be in poſſeſſyon of the cleargye, or anye other, not deuyded by acte of Parlyamente, or otherwyſe as is aforeſayde, ſhalbe folowed and obſerued without ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge anye other valuatyon, rate, taxation, or eſtymation, then in the ſayde Recorde is compryſed and mentioned.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> where by the great bountye and godly diſpoſition of the kyng and Queenes Maieſties, certayne relygyous houſes, haue benne of late erected and endowed with Spyrituall and Temporall poſſeſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the taxe whereof is not ſpecyfied in the Recordes of Thexcheker, or elſe where within anye of their Maieſties Courtes, ſuche taxe and valuation of the poſſeſſyons of the ſayde Relygyous houſes, ſhalbe fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed for the paymente of thys Subſedye, as the Byſhoppe of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſſe within the whyche the ſayde relygyous houſes be Scituated, ſhall vpon dewe ſearche and examination, certifye vnder hys Seale, into the Exchequer before the fyrſte daye of Maye nexte enſuyng, in whiche taxe the ſaide Byſhoppe ſhall and maye make all ſuche allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunces as by the acte of Parliamente, made in the ſixe and twentye yeare of the late kynge of famous memorye Henrye theight, of and for the grauntynge of the perpetuall Tenthe, were appointed, graunted, and aſſigned in the valuation and taxe of all Eccleſiaſticall and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall promocions, for the due and true paymente of the late perpetuall
<pb n="xxii" facs="tcp:180783:24"/>tenthe, and alſo ſhall and maye further allowe all ſuche Summes of monye, as are geuen, aſſygned, or appoynted to the fyndyng and main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tenaunce of poore menne, Scoole mayſters, vſſhers, gramaryens, cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſters and other offycers and mynyſters, ſeruynge and founde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayde Monaſteryes, and religyous houſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes that foraſmuche as the tenthe parte of the ſayde valuation and taxe afore mentyoned, ſhalbe for a tyme vpon certayne reaſonable conſyderations and reſpectes yearelye payde by the Cleargye, ſoo that there remayneth onelye nyne partes to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbente cleare, thys Subſedye of Eyghte ſhyllynges of the pounde, ſhalbe vnderſtande and mente onelye of the ſayde nyne partes, and of no more, where and ſoo longe as the Tenthe is or ſhalbe payde.</p>
               <p>Alſo the ſayde Prelates and Cleargye further doo graunte, that thys Subſedye of eyghte ſhyllynges of the pounde, of the yearelye va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of euerye promocion, taxed as is aforeſayde, ſhalbe payde to the kynge and Queenes Maieſtyes, within foure yeares nexte enſuynge the date hereof, That is to ſaye, two ſhyllinges of euery pounde, in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of the ſayde foure yeares.</p>
               <p>The fyrſt paymente thereof to be due at the fyue and twentye daye of Marche, whyche ſhalbe in the yeare of oure Lorde GOD, a thouſande fyue hundrede fyftye and eyghte, and the Seconde pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente thereof to be due, at the fyue and twenty daye of Marche, then nexte folowynge, whyche ſhalbe in the yeare of oure Lorde GOD, a thouſande fyue hundred fyftye and nyne.</p>
               <p>The thyrde paymente thereof to be dewe the fyue and twentye daye of Marche, then nexte folowynge, whyche ſhalbe in the yeare of oure Lorde GOD, a thouſande fyue hundred and ſyxtye.</p>
               <p>And the fourthe and laſte paymente thereof to be due at the ſayde fyue and twentye daye of Marche then nexte enſuynge, whyche ſhalbe in the yeare of oure Lorde GOD, a thouſande fyue hundred ſyxtye and one, to be delyuered and payde yearelye, by ſuche perſonne and perſonnes as in thys preſente graunte ſhalbe appoynted, to haue the collection thereof, to be payde into the receypte of the kynge and Queenes Maieſtyes Eſchequer, or to ſuche perſonne or perſonnes, place and places, to whome and where it ſhall pleaſe theyr hyghnes to appoynte for the receypte thereof, before or at the Tenthe daye of Iune, in euerye of the ſayde foure yeares, withoute payinge any thing to the receyuer or receyuours, or to anye other offycer or perſonne by theyr Maieſtyes to be aſſygned, for anye dyſcharge, acquyttaunce, or <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> vpon paymente and receypte of the ſame Subſedye, to be geuen and delyuered, but onelye twelue pence for the acquyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:180783:25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM</hi> the ſayd prelates and clergye, doo alſo graunte that euerye preiſt and all other ſpirituall perſons, hauyng a pention by reaſon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolution of any the late monaſteryes, colledges, free chappeles, chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teryes, fraternities, guyldes, and hoſpytalls, or of anye other ſpirituall dignitie, and corporation, nowe diſſolued, and extinguiſhed within the ſayd prouynce of Canterburye, ſhal lykewyſe paye to their highneſſes eyght ſhyllynges of euery pounde of the ſayd pencyons, within the ſaid foure yeares, at ſuch dayes and tymes, as is before ſpecified, and that for the ſure and aſſertayned payment thereof, deduction and retention of the ſayde eyght ſhyllynges, ſhalbe made yerely in the handes of the payers of the ſayd pencion, after the rate of two ſhillynges of the pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, euery of the ſayd foure yeares, to be deliuered and payde vnto their ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſties vſe, at ſuch tyme and to ſuch perſones as the Subſedy of eyght ſhyllynges of the pound aforeſayd, ſhalbe payd vnto.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM</hi> that euery ſtypendarye preiſt, receyuyng annuall ſtipende of eyght pounde by the yeare, and vnder, (beinge no perpetuitie) within the ſayde prounce, ſhall paye vnto their Maieſties vſe ſixe ſhyllynges eyght pence yearely, during the ſayd foure yeares, at ſuch tyme and to ſuch perſones as the ſaide Subſedy ſhalbe payde, and vnder the ſame penaltyes as the reſt of the clergie doo paye for their promotions. And that euery preiſt receyuyng aboue eight pounde yearely and not aboue ten pounde, to pay lykewyſe tenne ſhyllynges. And that euerye preyſte receyuynge aboue tenne pounde, and not aboue twentye markes, to paye thyrtene ſhyllynges foure pence yerelye, durynge the ſayde foure yeares at ſuche tyme and to ſuche perſonnes as the ſayde Subſedye ſhalbe payde. And that euery preiſte takynge ſtypende aboue twentye markes, to paye lykewiſe two ſhyllynges of the pounde, euerye yeare duringe the ſayde foure yeares, in ſuch maner and forme as the reſte of the clergye doo paye for their promotion ſpirituall, and for defaulte or lacke of payment by the ſaide ſtipendaryes, that euery perſon, vycarre or other ſpirituall or temporall perſon, proprietarye, or fermour, hiring anye preiſt to ſerue in anye place, ſhalbe anſwerable for the paiment of the ſaide preyſte in that behalfe, after the ſaide rates, and ſhal and may make retencion of his and their wages quarterly, of ſoo muche as the ſayde ſtipendaries be charged with, by this preſente commiſſion and graunte euerye of the ſayde foure yeares.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM</hi> the ſayde prelates and clergye, further doo graunt that euery Archebyſhoppe and Byſhoppe, and the Sea beinge vacante, euerye Deane and Chapter of that Sea voyde, ſhalbe Collectoures of thys Subſedye, within their proper Dyoceſſe, durynge the ſayde foure yeares.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> to thintente the kynge and quenes Maieſties maye be ſurely and duelie anſwered and payde of the ſayde Subſedie, in maner and fourme aforeſayde, and the Collectoure of the ſame throughlye char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:180783:25"/>and diſcharged accordinge to the tenour of this graunte.</p>
               <p>The ſayde prelates and Cleargie do ordeyne and decree with one aſſente and conſente, that euerye Collectoure of the aforeſayde Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidye, and of euerye parte and percell thereof, and theyr lawfull depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye or deputies, ſhall haue full power and aucthoritie agaynſte euerye perſonne and perſonnes lyable, charged and bounde to paye the ſayde Subſidye or anye parte thereof, denyinge, refuſinge, or delayinge to paye the ſame, or makynge anye defaulte in the paymente thereof, at the daye or dayes that it oughte to be payde (after lawfull warnynge to them geuen perſonallye, or at theyr Churches or manſions) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede with the cenſures of the Churche, that is to ſaye, by ſuſpention, excommunication, or interdiction, and alſo by ſequeſtration of the frui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctes and profits of theyr benefices or promotions ſpyrytuall, in whoſe handes ſoeuer they be, and to make ſale of the ſame fruictes, and by all other lawfull remedyes by theyr diſcretions thoughte conueniente, to coarcte, conſtrayne, and compell them and euerye of theim, to the full and vndelayde ſatiſfaction of the ſayde Subſedye, and euerye parte and percell thereof, and ſhal alſo haue lyke power and aucthoritie, both to abſolue or cauſe to be abſolued, all perſonnes ſo payinge, from al the ſayde cenſures and other paynes, and alſo to releaſe and reuoke al ſuch proceſſe as ſhall be made agaynſte them, or any of them, after they ſhall haue fullye ſatiſfyed the ſayde Subſidye accordingelye. And vpon full paymente or ſatiſfaction of the ſayde Subſidye or anye parte thereof, all ſuche acquittaunce or acquittaunces, whiche ſhall be made by the collectour or his lawfull deputie, ſhall be ſufficiente for the diſcharge of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes, and it is ordeyned and decreed, that all and euery perſonne and perſonnes, refuſinge or neglecting to paye the ſaid Subſedye at tyme conueniente, as is aforeſayde, ſhall for his or theyr fyrſte defaulte or necligence in not payinge the Subſedye, accordynge to the purporte and tenoure of this graunte, beare all the charges and reaſonable expences of the ſayd Collectoure or his deputye, in coming goynge, and demaundinge of the ſame, and for the ſeconde tyme lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe offendynge in none paymente, to paye to the ſayde Collectoure, or his deputye the fourth parte of the ſayde Subſedye, ouer and aboue the ſayde ſumme vpon him or his churche or perſonne allotted and tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whiche he is bounde to paye, and charged by this acte of free graunte.</p>
               <p>Alſo the ſayde prelates and clergye do further ordeyne and decree, that yf anye perſonne or perſonnes aboue named, chargeable to this Subſedye, or anye parte thereof, after the ſayde cenſures and proceſſe executed agaynſt him or them, yet ſtyll obſtinately refuſe, neglecte, or make delaye to paye the ſame, or anye parte thereof as is beforeſayde,
<pb facs="tcp:180783:26"/>that then after lawfull monition geuen vnto him or them, refuſing, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glectinge, or delayinge by the ſayde Collectours, or theyr lawfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putie or deputies, perſonallye, or at theyr Churches, doo ſtyll by the ſpace of thyrtye dayes refuſe, or negiecte to make payment of the ſayde Subſidye, that then, and in euerye ſuche caſe, it ſhall be lawfull to the ſayde collectoure or his lawfull deputie, euerye ſuche perſonne ſo refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge, neglectinge, or delayinge and contempning theſe former proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to depriue, amoue, and deſtitute from his or their benefice, ſpyrytu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promotion, or pention Eccleſiaſticall, anye appellation, inhibition, or other remedy, ordinary or extraordinary notwithſtanding: the ſaid perſonnes ſo refuſinge, to be and remayne for euer without hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe to ſuche theyr promotion as he or they ſhalbe depriued of, for the cauſes aforeſayde, by anye new preſentation of him or them to be made to the ſame. And that it ſhall be lawfull to the patrone of the ſayde be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice or benefices, or other Eccleſiaſticall promotions, frome whiche the ſayde perſonne or perſonnes ſo neglectinge to paye ſhall be depry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, to preſente vnto, or conferre euerye ſuche benefice or promotion Spirituall, as yf the ſayde Incumbente or Incumbentes were decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM</hi> the ſayde prelates and clergye further do ordeyne and decree, that of ſo muche as the ſayde Collectours ſhalbe charged with in their accoumptes, clearelye to be payde into the receipte of the ſayde Eſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer, or to ſuche perſonne or perſonnes as it ſhall pleaſe the kynge and Quenes maieſties to appointe for the receypte of the ſame, ſhall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to the ſayde collectoure vpon his ſayde accoumpte for the ſame, for euerye pounde ſixe pence, by waye of rewarde, or in liewe of his charges, collection, portage, conueying, and payinge of the ſayd Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes that no Spyrytual promotion, or any landes, poſſeſſions, or reuenues annexed to the ſame, beynge charged by thys graunte or acte of the prouince of Canterburye, or anye goodes or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telles growinge, beynge, or renewynge of the ſame, or apparteyninge to the owners of the ſame Spirituall promotions, ſhall be charged or made contributorye to anye .xv. or anye other Subſidye all readye graunted, or within fyue yeares nexte enſumge the date of this preſent to be graunted by the laitye to the kynge and quenes highneſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>ITEM,</hi> the ſayde prelates and cleargye further graunte, that all Deanes, Archedeacons, Dignities, Prebendaries, preachers, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye Canons, of all Cathedrall and Collegiate Churches within the ſayde prouynce, ſhall be charged with this Subſidye for theyr owne portions onelye, thereof to paye eyghte ſhyllynges of the pounde, with in the ſayde foure yeares, as is aboue rehearſed, and that thoſe porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of rentes and reuenues whiche theyr highnes. or any of theyr moſt
<pb n="xxiiii" facs="tcp:180783:26"/>noble progenitoures, or any other perſons, haue giuen vnto the ſayde cathedral or Collegiate Churches, for the mayntenaunce of pore men, Scoole mayſters, vſhers, gramariens, choriſters, and other offycers and mynyſters, not to be charged with anye parte of thys Subſedye.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alſo that euery parſon, vicar, or ſpirituall man, paying any pencion whereof no allowaunce is made in the valuation of hys ſayde benefice, in the recordes of the ſayde late Courte of fyrſte frutes, or Eſchequer, or otherwyſe, ſhal and maye retayne two ſhyllynges of euerye pounde, of euerye ſuche pencion, euery yeare durynge the ſayde foure yeares, to his owne releyfe, in conſideration that he is charged to paye hys Subſedye of eyght ſhyllynges of the pounde, out of euery pounde of the ſayde pention. Any thinge to the contrary notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alſo that where certayne landes, tenementes, rentes, tythes, pencyons, porcions, frutes, and other hereditamentes, lately be lougynge to diuerſe cathedrall churches, and other places eccleſiaſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, within the ſayde prouynce of Canterburye, or anye other yearelye paymentes, goyng out or beyng paid oute of the ſayde Landes, Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and other the premiſſes, or anye of them, whiche were geuen and aſſygned to be beſtowed, and ſpente to and vpon the fyndyng and maintenaunce of certaine chauntryes, anniuerſaryes, obyttes, lightes, lampes, and other lyke thyngs, intentes, and purpoſes, be of late come into the handes and poſſeſſion of the kynge and Quenes Maieſtyes, our Soueraygne Lorde and Ladye, by force of a ſtatute therof made in the fyrſt yeare of the reygne of our late Soueraigne lord king Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde the ſyxte, as by the ſame Statute more plainelye appearethe. That the ſayde cathedrall churches and the deanes or preſydentes, and chapters of the ſame, and all other places and perſones to whome the ſayde landes, rentes, and all other the premiſſes or anye of them did lately apperteyne, ſhal not be charged to and with anye contributyon or paymente of thys Subſedy, of and for that parte or portion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto the kynge and queenes maieſties, be and hath bene entituled or poſſeſſed of. nor of, and for anye the ſayde yearelye paymentes, goinge oute or payde oute of the premiſſes, or any parte thereof. But that thys ſayde Subſedye ſhalbe vnderſtande to be chargeable and dewe onely of all and ſinguler landes, tenementes, rentes, tithes, pencions, porty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, frutes, and other hereditamentes, which do yet ſtyll remayne, not diſſeuered from the handes and poſſeſſion of the ſaide cathedrall chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and other the places and perſonnes aforeſayd. And that deduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and allowaunce be made to them and euerye of them, in the pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſayde Subſedye, out of the valuation, taration, and eſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, made for the payment of the ſayde Diſme, remayninge of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, in the kyng and quenes maieſties court of the Eſcheker, for that
<pb facs="tcp:180783:27"/>rate and portion or yearelye paymente which is come into the handes and poſſeſſion of our ſayd Soueraygne lord and lady, or otherwiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from the poſſeſſions of the ſayde cathedrall churches, and other places and parſons aforeſayd, by force of the Statute premyſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alſo that euerye parſon and vicar, whoſe benefyce is aboue the valuation of fyue poundes, and not aboue ſixe pound thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tene ſhillinges and foure pence, after the rate of the late perpetual te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th, ſhall paye euerye yeare of the ſayd foure yeares onely, Sixe ſhillinges eyght pence, as Stipendary preiſtes of eyghte pounde yearely wages benne charged to do by force of thys acte, and graunt, and none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe. And that al parſons and vycars, whoſe benefices be of the valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of fyue pound or vnder, after the rate of the ſayde late perpetuall Tenthe, ſhall not be charged nor chargeable with thys Subſedye, or anye parte thereof.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes that this Subſedye graunted by the cleargy ſhall not be demaunded or leuyed oute of anye benefice, houſe of ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentes, or colledge, ſcituate or ſet within the vniuerſities of Orforde &amp; Cambridge, or of anye benefice, or other reuenues, vnto anye houſe of Studentes, or colledge in Oxforde or Cambrydge, vnited, appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or appertayninge, or of the colledge of Eaton, nigh Windeſour, or of the Colledge of Wincheſter, founded by Wyllyam Myckeham, ſome tyme Byſhoppe of Wincheſter, or any pore men, women or chyldren li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge of almeſſe, in any Hoſpitalles, almeſſe houſes, almeſſe halles, or of gramer ſcooles, or of anye other churche or benefice, or of any other reuenues of the ſayde houſes, Colleges, or hoſpitalles, almeſſe houſes, or almeſſe halles, or gramer ſcooles, or to any of them annexed, appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pried or otherwyſe appertayning.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alſo that euery preyſt and all other late profeſſed rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions parſons, hauyng a pention by reſon of the diſſolution of the late Monaſteries, Colledges, free Chappells, Chauntryes, Frateruytyes. Guyldes, and Hoſpytalls, or anye other incorporation, within the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynce of Canterburye, and beynge of the ſumme of fortye ſhyllynges or vnder, and not aboue, ſhal not be charged or chargeable to the ſayde Subſedye or anye parte thereof, for anye ſuch pencion of fourtye ſhyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges or vnder. Anye thynge conteyned in this graunt to the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Fynallye the ſayde Prelates and Cleargye, beynge deſyrous that the ſayde Subſedye maye be entierlye contented and payde to thuſe of the kynge and Quenes Maieſties, within the ſayde foure yeares, do graunt, ordeyne, and decree, that yf it ſhal happen in thende of the ſayde foure yeares, anyde arrerages of the ſayde Subſedye to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde vnpayde by reaſon of the exilitie, and decaye of anye benefyces, or other ſpirituall promotions, lyable to thys Subſedye, That then it
<pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:180783:27"/>ſhalbe lawefull to euerye Archebyſhoppe and Byſihoppe, within their ſeuerall Dioceſſe, by the conſent of his cleargye, and the Sea beynge voyde, to the Deane and Chapter of that Sea voyde, to aſſeſſe &amp; taxe all and ſinguier the eccleſiaſticall promocions, within their ſayde ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Dioceſſe, to become contributors to the full ſatiſfaction of the ſayd Subſedye, the ſame to be collected, leuyed, and payde the nexte yeare immediatelye enſuynge the ſayde forth yeare, at the dayes and vnder the paynes, forme, &amp; qualities aboue limitted. Anything in this graunt to the contrarye notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> for the true and ſure payment of thys Subſedye, graunted by the ſayde Prelates and Clergye of the prouynce of Canterburye, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge to the tenor, purporte, effecte, and true meaninge of this preſent inſtrument. The ſayde Prelates and Cleargye mooſte humblye deſire and requyre the kynge and Queenes mooſte excellente Maieſties, that it maye be enacted by aucthortie of this preſente Parlyamente, that the prouyſyons conteyned in the foreſayde graunte, ſhall ſtande good and effectuall to all intentes and purpoſes, mentioned in the ſayde graunte. And that all proceſſes and penalties, and all other clauſes, touchynge the payment of the ſayde Subſedye, and the leuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge and collection of the ſame, and of euerye percell thereof, may be by the ſayde Prelates and Cleargye, and their lawefull deputies, put in due execution accordynge to the true meanynge thereof, withoute in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currynge anye penaltyes or daungers of anye lawes and ſtatutes of thys Realme.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> for the true and ſure paymente of the ſayd Subſedye, graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſaid prelates and cleargy, of the ſayd prouynce of Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, accordyng to the tenor, effect, and true meanyng of the ſaid inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente. Be it enacted by the kynge and Quenes Maieſties, with thaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente of the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in thys preſent parlyamente aſſembled, and by thaucthoritie of the ſame, that the ſayde gifte and graunt, and euery matter, ſumme of mony, proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, clauſe, and ſentence in the ſayde inſtrument conteined be ratified, eſtablyſhed, and confirmed by thaucthoritie aforeſayd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> furthermore be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that euerye perſonne that ſhalbe appoynted to the collection and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therynge of the ſayde Subſedye, ſhall haue full power and aucthoritie to leuye take and perceyue the ſame Subſedye, by thaucthoritie of the cenſures of the churche, in maner and forme as in the ſayde inſtrument of graunt is conteyned, without daunger of the lawes of this realme or by diſtreſſe vpon the poſſeſſion of the fermours or occupyers of the landes, and tenementes, chargeable by the ſayd inſtrumente, for or to the paymente of any ſumme or ſummes of monye, or otherwyſe by the diſcretion of the collector thereof. And that no repleuye, prohibition, or
<pb facs="tcp:180783:28"/>ſuperſedias ſhalbe allowed, or obeyed for any perſon or perſones, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng defaulte of payment of the ſayd Subſedy, contrary to the tenor of the grauntes thereof, vntyll ſuche tyme as they haue truely ſatyſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and contented all ſuche parte and porcions, as to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that behalfe apperteyneth. And that euerye ſuche fermoure and fermoures, theyr executours and aſſignes, that ſhall fortune hereafter, to be charged to and with the paymente of the ſayd Subſedy, or anye parte therof, ſhal by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, be allowed and retayue in his handes, as muche of his yerelye rente and ferme, as the ſumme which he ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to paye for his Lorde or Leſſor ſhall extende vnto, except the ſaid fermor or fermours, their executors and aſſignes, by the leaſe &amp; grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te that they haue of anye parte of the landes, and tenementes, chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thys ſaide Subſedye, or by force of anye couenaunte or artycle, therein conteyned, be bounden and charged to paye the ſame, and ther of to diſcharge their leaſſor and landlord, durynge the terme mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſayd leaſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted by thaucthoritie of thys preſent parliament, that euery laye perſon hauyng a ſpirituall promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion chargeable by this acte, and alſo hauynge temporall poſſeſſions, goodes, cattells, and debtes, chargeable to this Subſedye graunted by the temporaltye, ſhalbe charged, taxed, and ſet for hys ſayd ſpiritual promocions with the cleargy, and for his ſaid temporall poſſeſſions, &amp; cattells, with the temporaltye, and not otherwyſe, anye thinge before mentioned to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted, by thaucthoritie of thys preſent parly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, that the ſayd archebyſhoppes, and Biſhoppes, and other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonnes chargeable to and with the collection of the ſayd Subſedye of eyghte ſhyllynges of the pounde, within the ſayd prouynce of Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burye, ſhall haue vppon euery payment thereof made in the Queenes courte of the eſcheker, or ells where the kyng and quenes Maieſtyes ſhall appoynte the ſame to be payed, a ſufficiente acquittaunce in wry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge, of ſuche perſon or perſones, as their maieſties ſhall appoynt for the receipte thereof, the ſame acquittaunce witneſſing the ſame receipt, of as much of the ſame ſumme of the ſame Subſedy, as ſhall be by any of them ſo receiued, and euery ſuch acquitaunce, in wryting, ſealed, and Subcribed with the name or names of euery ſuch perſon or perſones, that ſo by their highneſſes appoyntment ſhall receyue anye of the ſayd Summes of monye, ſhalbe as good and effectuall in the lawe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a ſufficiente diſcharge, to all intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, as if it were made by acte of Parlyamente. And that euerye perſonne and perſonnes, which ſhal haue and receaue anye ſuche acquytaunce, ſhall paye but onelye two pence, for euerye of the ſame acquyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunces.</p>
               <pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:180783:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEIT</hi> alſo further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that all and euerye graunt and grauntes of all and euery Summe and Summes of moneye whiche hereafter ſhall be graunted to the kynge and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Maieſties by the cleargye of the prouince of yorke, ſhall be of the ſame ſtrengthe, force, and effecte, in all thinges as the ſayde graunte made by the ſayde prouince of Canterburye, and ſhall be taxed, certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, collected, leuied, and gathered accordinge to the tenoure, fourme, and effecte of this preſente acte of parliamente, to all intentes, conſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and purpoſes, in ſuch maner as thoughe it were ſpecially, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, and perticulerlye expreſſed and rehearſed in this acte by expreſſe wordes, tearmes, and ſentences in theyr ſeuerall natures and kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that all prouiſos before rehearſed, conteyned in the ſayde graunte of the prelates and cleargy of the prouynce of Canterburye, and the lyke or the ſame prouiſions hereafter to be conteyned in the graunte of the prelates and cleargye of the prouince of yorke, ſhall be good and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, and to be obſerued and kepte in euerye poynte and article, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the true purporte and meanynge of the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>AN ACTE</hi> of a Subſidie, and one fiftene graunted by the temporaltie.</head>
               <head type="sub">The .xi. Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E THE KINGE AND</hi> Quenes Maieſties Mooſte humble, faythfull, and obediente ſubiectes, the Lordes ſpyrytuall and temporall, and the commons in this preſente parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, callynge to oure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce the great and manyfold charges, whiche theyr graces haue all readye ſuſteined by the reaſon of thys preſent warre that their highnes haue had, and yet haue agaynſt the frenche kynge and the Scottes, the auncyent enemies of this Realme, and perceiuinge alſo that the malyce of the ſame Frenche kynge and Scottes are ſuche, that they haue and dayly do practiſe by all diſhonorable wayes and meanes, with the ayde and power of all theyr confederaties and alies, to anoye theyr Maieſties, and this theyr Realme, and other the dominions of the ſame, and by al lykelyhode, yf oportunitie of tyme and place ſo permitte, doo mynde to
<pb facs="tcp:180783:29"/>make ſome inuaſion into ſundrye partes of this realme, as well vpon the Sea coſte as els where, whiche yf it ſhoulde happen, woulde be no ſmall annoyaunce as well to theyr Maieſties, as to the hole eſtate of this realme. For the wyſe preuention and reſiſtence whereof (leaſt any ſuch ſhuld happen to be attempted) theyr highnes ſhalbe enforced, not onely to mayneteyne a conueniente number, and nauye of ſhyppes v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the narrowe Seas, but alſo a great power and number of ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to continue in diuers and ſundrye partes of the borders and froun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiers of this realme, redye prepared to all purpoſes, to reſiſt al ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious attempts or inuaſions, and to defende the libertye and honour thereof, whiche cannot be put in order and readines, withoute greate Summes of monye, to be defraied and emploied for the ſame. And fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thermore conſidering that the ſame ſhall not be onely for the ſuertye of their maieſties perſonnes (whom we pray to god maye longe raygne ouer vs,) and likewiſe for the ſuretye of this Realme, and theyr Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties louynge Subiectes of the ſame, but alſo maye be a greate ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure, feare, and diſcourage to the ſayde frenche kynge and Scottes, and all theyr confederates, and alies, to attempte anye ſuch inuaſion or other enterpryſe. Haue graunted vnto our ſaid Soueraigne lady, her heyres and Succeſſours, one Subſedye, and one .xv. and tenth, to be taxed, rated, and leuied of our goodes, cattels, landes, and tenementes in maner and fourme as hereafter in this preſent acte is limitted and conteined: And albeit that we doubte not but that our ſaid moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraigne lorde and lady aſſure them ſelues, that we their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious mooſte louinge ſubiectes, knowe the ſame to be farre vnder the charges whiche theyr maieſties are lyke to ſuſteyne in this behalfe. Yet neuertheleſſe we moſte humblye beſeche theyr highnes to accepte this oure gifte, as a declaration of our true and moſt faythfull hartes, who be, and by gods aſſiſtence alwayes ſhalbe, by all wayes and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and in all reſpectes, ready to ſerue with all conformitie and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for the preſeruation of theyr mooſt royall perſonnes, and defence and ſuretie of this theyr maieſties realme and dominions, as to the du tye of good and obedient ſubiectes apperteyneth.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we the ſaid lordes and comons, for the great and vrge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t conſiderations aforeſayd, by one hole aſſent, by auctoritie of this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t parliament, do geue and graunt to our ſayde Soueraygne Lady, the quenes highnes, her heires and ſucceſſoures, towardes the ſayd great coſtes, and ineſtimable charges, one hole .xv. and tenth, to be payd, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; leuied of the moueable goodes, cattels, and other thinges vſuall to ſuch .xv. and tenthe, to be contributorye and chargeable within the Shires, Cities, Boroughes, Townes, &amp; other places of this their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties realme, in maner and fourme afore time vſed, except the ſumme of ſixe thouſande pounde thereof fullye to be deducted of the Summe
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:180783:29"/>that one hole .xv. and tenth atteyneth vnto, in releif, comforte and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the pore cities, townes, &amp; boroughes of this her ſayd realme, waſted, deſolate, or diſtroyed, or ouer greatly empoueriſhed, after ſuch rate as was and hath afore this time bene had and made vnto euerye Shire, and to be deuided in ſuche maner and forme as heretofore for one hole .xv. and tenth hath ben had and deuided.</p>
               <p>And the ſayd one hole .xv. and tenth, the exceptions and deducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons aforeſayde therevpon had, deducted, and allowed, to be payde in maner and fourme folowinge. That is to ſaye, the hole .xv. and tenth, to be payde to her aſſignes in the receipte of her highnes eſchequer, be fore the tenth daye of Nouember next comminge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that the knightes elected and retorned of, &amp; for the Shires within this realme for this preſente Parliamente, Citezens of Cities, and Burgeſſes of Boroughes and townes, where collectours haue bene vſed to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and appointed for the collection of any .xv. and tenth, before this tyme graunted, ſhall name and appointe before the laſte daye of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſte nexte comminge, ſufficient and able perſons, for the Collection of the ſayd .xv. and tenth, in euery of the ſayd Shyres, Cities, Boroughes and townes, the ſayde perſonnes then hauynge landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes, in his owne ryghte, of an eſtate of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce of the yearelye value of tenne poundes, or in goodes worth one hundreth poundes at the leaſte. And alſo ſuche perſon or perſons, ſo by them to be named and appointed for the collection of the ſayde .xv. and tenth, ſhalbe by them ſeuerally apoynted, and allotted into hundredes. Rapes, Wapentakes, cities, boroughes, and townes. And alſo the ſayd perſones ſo named and apoynted for the collection of the ſame .xv. and tenth, ſhalbe charged and chargeable vpon his or theyr accoumpte or accoumptes in the eſchequer, to be made with all ſuche ſumme or ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of mony, as the hundredes, rapes, wapentakes, cities, boroughes and townes where he or they ſhall ſo happen to be appointed amount vnto, and of no more ſumme or ſummes.</p>
               <p>And vppon the paymente of ſuche Summes of monye, as he ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be charged with, ſhall be diſcharged and haue his quietus eſt, the none accoumptinge, or none payment of any other his fellowes, or the inſufficiency of them or anye of them, notwythſtandynge. And the names and ſurnames of euerye of the ſayde Collectoures, for the ſayde xv. and tenth together, with the place allotted to theyr Collection and charge, the ſaid knightes, citizens, &amp; Burgeſſes for the Shyres, cities, and boroughes whervnto they be elected, named, and retourned, ſhal certifie before the kynge and quene in theyr chauncery, before the .xiii. daye of October no we nexte folowinge, accordinge to the tenure of this acte. And yf defaulte of anye ſuche certifieng be hadde or made, in
<pb facs="tcp:180783:30"/>fourme as is aboueſayd, then the lorde Chauncellour of Englande for the time beynge, ſhall immediatelye after, name and appointe Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures for the collection of the ſame .xv. and tenth, in manner &amp; fourme as the ſayde knightes of the ſhyre, citizens of cities, and Burgeſſes of Bouroughes ſhoulde haue doone, and as afore tyme haue bene vſed. The whiche ſayde collectours and euery of them ſhall haue like allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce vpon theyr accoumptes, for theyr fees, wages, and rewardes for the collection of the ſayde .xv. and tenthe, in as large manner and fourme as anye collectoure or collectoures of .xv. and tenth, haue had at anye ſeaſon in time paſte. And that the barons of the kynge and quenes Eſchequer for the time beinge, ſhall and may from time to time awarde ſuche proces for the ſpedye payment thereof agaynſt the colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoure and collectoures of the ſame, as by theyr diſcretions ſhall be thought conueniente.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwaye and be it enacted by the aucthoritie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente parliament, that the ſayde Lorde Chauncellour, knightes of the ſhyres, Citiſens of Cities, and Burgeſſes of Burroughes. Townes, and other places, hauynge aucthoritie by this preſente acte, to name and nominate the ſayde Collectoures, of, or for the ſayde fyftene and tenth, ſhall vpon theyr nomination and election hadde and made, take by aucthoritie of this preſente parliamente, ſufficiente recogniſaunce, or by obligation of euerye perſonne ſo by them to be named to be boun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den to the kynge and Queenes Maieſties in the double Summe of theyr collection, and to be endorced vppon ſuche condition, that yf the ſayde collectoure or collectoures, doo truelye contente and paye to the vſe of the kynge and Quene in theyr receypt of theyr Eſchequer before the ſayde tenth daye of Nouember nowe nexte enſuynge, ſo muche of the Summe of money, allotted and appointed to his collection, as the ſame Collectoure ſhall haue collected and gathered. And do lyke wyſe after the ſayde tenthe daye of the moneth of Nouember, contente and paye to the kynge and Quenes Maieſties vſes at the ſame receypte, the reſidue of his collection &amp; charge, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in one moneth next after ſuch tyme as he ſhal haue gathered and collected the ſame reſidue, that then the ſayde recognyſaunce or obligation to be voyde, or elles to ſtande in his full ſtrength and vertue, whiche recogniſaunce or obligations ſoo taken, the ſayde knyghtes of the Shyre, Citiſens and Burgeſſes, and euerye of theym, takynge anye ſuche recogniſaunces or oblygatyons, ſhall certyſye and delyuer to the Lorde Treaſurer and Baronnes of the ſame Eſchequer, before the ſayde tenth daye of Nouember nowe nexte enſuynge, vppon payne of forfeyture of ten pounde to the Quene for euerye recoguyſaunce or oblygation ſoo to be taken and not certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
               <p>And that euerye inche collectoure vpon requeſte to him made, ſhal
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:180783:30"/>make and knowledge the ſame recogniſaunce or obligation according lye, vpon like payne and forfeiture of tenne pounde to the Queene for his refuſall thereof. And that the Treaſurer or Barons of the eſcheker vpon the payment of the ſame collection, or at the ſayde daye, ſhal can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell and delyuer the ſayde recogniſaunce or obligation to the ſayde col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour or collectours, without any fee, or rewarde to be payde to anye perſon for the ſame.</p>
               <p>And furthermore for the greate and weyghtye conſiderations a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde, we the Lordes Spirituall and Temporall, and Commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, do by oure like aſſente and auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of this Parlyamente, geue and graunte to oure ſayde Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne Lady the Quenes Maieſtie, her heyres and Succeſſours, one entyer Subſedye, to be rated, taxed, leuyed, and payde at one hole and entyre paymente, of euerye perſonne Spyrytuall and Temporall, of what eſtate or degree he or they be, accordynge to the tenure of thys acte, in manner and fourme folowynge. That is to ſaye, as well of eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry perſonne borne within this realme of Englande, Wales, or other the Quenes dominions, as of all and euery Fraternitie, Guild, Corpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ration, Miſterye, Brotherheade, and Cominaltye, corporated or not corporated, within this Realme of Englande, Wales, or other the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dominions, beynge worth fyue pounde, for euerye pounde, as wel in coyne, and the value we of euerye pounde that euerye ſuche perſonne, Fraternitie, Guylde, Corporation, Myſterye, Brotherheade, and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynaltye, corporate or not corporate, hath of his or theyr owne, or any other to his or theyr vſe, as alſo plate, ſtocke of marchaundiſes, all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of corne and blades, houſeholde ſtuffe, and of all other goodes mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable, as well within the Realme as without, and of all ſuch ſummes of money as to him or them is or ſhalbe owyng, wherof he or they truſt in his or their conſciences ſurely to be payde (excepte and out of the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſes deducted ſuche ſummes of money as he or they owe, and in his or theyr conſciences truely intendeth to paye, and excepte alſo the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell of ſuche perſonnes, theyr wyues and chyldren belongynge to theyr owne bodies, ſauynge Iuelles, golde, ſyluer, ſtone and pearle) ſhall paye to and for the ſayde Subſedy, two ſhillinges eyght pence of euery pounde.</p>
               <p>And alſo of euerye alien borne oute of the Queenes obeyſaunce, as well Denizen as other, inhabitinge within the Realme, of euerye pounde that he or they haue in coyne, and the value of euerye pounde in plate, corne, grayne, marchaundiſe, houſeholdeſtuffe or other goodes Iuelles, Cattelles, moueable or vnmoueable as is aſoreſayde, as well within this Realme as without, and of al ſummes of monye to him or them owyng, whereof he or they truſt in his or theyr conſcience or con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſciences to be payde (excepte and of the ſame premiſſes deducted euery
<pb facs="tcp:180783:31"/>ſuche Summe or ſummes of mony which he or they doo owe, and in his or theyr conſcience or conſciences intendeth truely to pay) ſhal pay of and for euery pounde, to and for the payment of the ſayde Subſedy fyue ſhyllinges .iiij.d. for euery pounde.</p>
               <p>And alſo that euery alien and ſtraunger, borne oute of the queenes dominions, beynge denizen or not denizen, not beynge contrybutorye to anye of the rates aboueſayde, ſhall paye to and for the paymente of the ſayde Subſidy, eyght pence foreuery poll, and the mayſter, or he or ſhe with whome the ſame alien is or ſhalbe abidinge at the tyme of the taxation or taxations thereof, to be charged with the ſame for lacke of payment thereof.</p>
               <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that euery perſon borne vnder the quenes obeyſaunce, and euery corporation, fra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ternitie, guylde, miſterye, brotherheade, and cominaltie, corporate or not corporate, for euery pounde that euerye of the ſame perſonnes, and euery corporation, fraternitie, guylde, myſtery, brotherhead, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, corporate or not corporate, or anye other to his or their vſe hath in fee ſimple, fee tayle, for terme of lyfe, terme of yeares, by execution, wardeſhyppe, or by copye of courte roll. of and in any honoures, caſtels Manours, landes, tenementes, rentes, ſeruices, hereditamentes, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuities, fees, corrodies, or other yearelye profyttes, of the yearelye va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of twentye ſhyllynges, as well within aunciente demeane, as other places pryuyleged, as elles where, and ſo vpwardes, ſhall paye to and for the paymente of the ſayde Subſedy, foure ſhyllynges of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pounde.</p>
               <p>And euerye alien borne oute of the Quenes obeyſaunce, in ſuche caſe, to paye at the ſayd payment eight ſhyllynges of euery pound.</p>
               <p>And that all ſummes preſented and chargeable by this acte, either for goodes and debtes, or for landes and tenementes, and other the premiſſes, as is in this acte conteyned, ſhalbe at the ſayde payment ſet and taxed after the rate and portion, accordynge to the true meaninge of this acte (landes and tenementes chargeable to the dyſines of the clergy, and yearlye wages due to ſeruauntes for their yearelye ſeruyce (other then the kinge and Quenes ſeruauntes takynge yearelye wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of fyue poundes or aboue, onely except and forpryſed.) And that all plate, coyne, iuelles, goodes, debtes, and cattelles perſonnalles, beynge in the onelye cuſtodye of anye perſonne and perſonnes, to the vſe of anye corporation, fraternitie, Guilde, miſterye, brotherhead, or anye comminaltie, beynge corporate or not corporate, be and ſhall be rated, ſet, &amp; charged by reaſon of this act, as the value certified by the preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that certificate, to be ſworne of euerye pounde in goodes and debtes as is aboueſayde. And of euery pounde in landes, tenementes, annuities, fees, corrodies, or other yearely profittes, as is aboueſayde.
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:180783:31"/>And the ſommes that are before rehearſed, ſette, and taxed, to be leuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and taken of them that ſhall haue ſuche goodes in cuſtodie, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe charged for landes as is before rehearſed. And the ſame perſonne or perſonnes, and body corporate by thaucthoritie of this acte, ſhall be diſcharged agaynſte him or them that ſhall or oughte to haue the ſame at the tyme of the paymente or delyuerye thereof, or at his otherwyſe departure from the cuſtodye or poſſeſſion of the ſame, (excepte and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes forpriſed from the charge and aſſeaſſement of this ſubledye, all goodes, cattels, Iuelles, and ornamentes of Churches and Chappels, whiche haue bene ordeined and vſed in Churches or Chappels, for the honoure and ſeruice of almightie God.) And this payment of the ſayd ſubſedy ſhall be by aucthoritie aforeſayde, taxed, aſſeſſed, and rated ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge to this acte, in euerye Shyre, Rydinge, Lathe, Wapentake, Rape, Citie, Borough, Towne, &amp; euery other place within this realme of Englande and Wales, and other the Quenes dominions, before the laſte daye of Apryll next comminge.</p>
               <p>And the perticuler Summes of euerye Shyre, Rydinge, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe, Towne, and other places aforeſayde, with the perticuler na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of ſuche as are chargeable for and to the paymente of the ſayde Subſedye, to be taxed and ſette by the Commiſſioners to the ſame ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or two of theim at the leaſte, with the names of the hyghe col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoures, and in the ſame fourme ſhall be certified in the kynge and Queenes Eſchequer, before the laſte daye of Maye nexte commyng, with the names of the highe Collectoures of the ſame. And the ſayde Summes in manner and fourme aforeſayde, to be taxed for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of the ſayde Subſidye, ſhall be payde in the kynge and Quenes Receipte of theyr Eſchequer aforeſayde, to the vſe of oure ſayde Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Ladye, before the .xxiiij. daye of Iune nexte comminge. And the Summes of and for the ſayde Subſidie, ſhalbe taxed, ſette, aſked, and demaunded, taken, gathered, leuyed, and payde to the vſe of oure ſayde Soueraigne Lady, and her heyres and Succeſſoures in forme aboueſayde, as well within the liberties, fraunchiſes, Saynctuaries, aunciente demeane, and other whatſoeuer place, exempte or not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empte, as withoute (excepte ſuche Shyres, places, and perſonnes as ſhall be forpriſed in and by this preſente acte) anye graunte, charter, preſcription, vſe, or libertye, by reaſon of any letters patentes, or other priuiledge, preſcription, allowaunce of the ſame, or whatſoeuer other matter of diſcharge heretofore to the contrary made, graunted, vſed, or obteyned notwithſtandinge.</p>
               <p>And it is further enacted by the aucthoritye of this preſente parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, that euerye ſuche perſonne, as well ſuche as be borne vnder the queenes obeyſaunce, as euerye other perſon Straunger borne, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen or not denizen inhabitinge within this realme, or within Wales,
<pb facs="tcp:180783:32"/>or other the Quenes dominions, whiche at the tyme of the ſame aſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge or taxation to be hadde or made, ſhall be oute of this realme, and oute of Wales, and haue goodes or cattels, landes, or tenements, fees or anuities, or other profittes within this realme, or in Wales, ſhall be charged and chargeable for the ſame, by the certificate of the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes of the parties where ſuche goodes, cattels, landes, teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, or other the premiſſes then ſhall be, or in ſuche other place where ſuche perſonne or his factoure deputye or attourneye, ſhall haue his mooſte reſorte vnto within this realme or in Wales, in lyke manner as yf the ſayde perſonne were or hadde ben at the tyme of the ſayde aſſeaſſynge within this Realme. And that euerye perſonne abydynge or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge within this Realme, or withoute this Realme, ſhall be charged or chargeable to the ſame Subſedye, graunted by thys Acte, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordinge, and after the rate of ſuche yearelye ſubſtaunce, or valewe of landes and tenementes, goodes, and cattelles, and other the premyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as euerye perſonne ſo to be charged ſhal be ſet at the time of the ſaid aſſeaſſinge or taxation vppon hym to be made, and in none other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> furthermore be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that for the aſſeaſſinge and orderynge of the ſayde Subſedye to be duelye hadde, the Lorde Chauncelloure of Englande, or the keper of the greate Seale, the Lorde Treaſurer of Englande, the Lorde Stew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arde of the Kynge and Queenes Honorable Houſeholde, the Lorde preſident of the kynge and Quenes honorable Counſayle, the lord pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye Seale for the time beynge, or two of them at the leaſt, whereof the Lorde Chauncellour of Englande, or keper of the great Seale for the time beynge to be one, ſhall and maye name and appointe, of, and for euery Shyre and Rydyng, and other places aſwel within this realme as in Wales, and other the Quenes dominions, and alſo of and for eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye Citie and Towne, beynge a countye in it ſelfe, and of, and for the Iſle of Wyght, ſuch certeyne nomber of perſonnes, of euery of the ſaid Shires, Rydinges, Lathes, Wapentakes, Rapes, Cities, Townes, and Iſle of Wight, and euery other place, and other the inhabitauntes of the ſame, to be Commiſſioners with in the ſame, whereof they be inhabytauntes, and alſo of, and for the honorable houſeholde of the Quenes Maieſtie, and the Lady Elizabeths grace, in what Shyres or other places, the ſayde houſeholdes ſhall happen then to be. And the Lorde Chauncelloure and other with him before named in lyke ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, maye name and appoynte of euerye other ſuche Burroughe, and towne corporate, aſwell in Englande as in Wales, and other the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes dominions as they ſhall thinke requiſite, ſyxe, fyue, foure, three, or two of the heade officers, and other ſadde honeſte inhabitauntes of euery of the ſayde Cities, Burroughes, and Townes Corporate, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:180783:32"/>to the number and multitude of people beynge in the ſame. The whiche perſonnes yf anye ſuch be therevnto named, of the ſayde inhabytauntes of the ſayde Burroughes, and Townes Corporate, not beynge countyes in them ſelfes, ſhalbe ioyned and putte in as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſyoners, with the perſonnes named for ſuche Shyres, and Ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynges, as the ſayde Burroughes, and townes corporate, not beynge counties in them ſelues, be ſet and haue their being, whych perſons ſo named for &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid boroughes, &amp; townes corporate, not being coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, by reaſon of their dwelling in the ſame, ſhall not take vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to put any part of their commiſſion in execution for the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſſes oute of the ſayde Boroughes and Towne Corporate, wherein they beynge ſo named onelye for the ſame be dwellynge. And alſo not to execute the ſayde commyſſyon within the Burroughe or Towne Corporate, wher they be ſo dwellynge, but at ſuche dayes, and tymes, as the ſayde other commyſſyoners for the ſame Shyre, and Rydynge ſhall thereto lymytte and appoynte, within the ſame Burroughe or towne corporate, not beynge countye corporate, whereof they ſoo be, and not out of ſuche Burrough or towne, and in that maner to be ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and aſſyſtynge with the ſayde other commyſſyoners, in, and for the good executynge of theffecte of the ſayde commyſſyon, vpon paine of euerye of the ſayde commiſſioners ſoo named for euerye ſuche cytye Burrough, and towne corporate, not being a county, to make ſuch fine as the ſayd other comiſſioners in the commiſſion, of, &amp; for the ſaid ſhire or rydynge ſo named, or three of them at the leaſt, ſhal by theyr dyſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſette and certyfye into the kynge and queenes Eſcheker, there to be leuyed to the vſe of her Maieſtie, in like manner as ſuche or like Sommes hadde bene ſette and rated vpon euerye ſuche perſonne for the ſayde Subſedye. The whyche commiſſyoners ſo named of and for the ſayde Cityes, Burroughes, and Townes, not beynge countyes, &amp; onelye putte in the ſayde commyſſyon by reaſonne of theyr dwellynge in the ſame, ſhall not haue anye parte of the portion of the fees, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes of the commyſſyoners and theyr clerkes, in thys acte after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes ſpecyfyed. And the lorde Chauncelloure of Englande, and ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the kynge and Queenes great Seale for the tyme beynge, ſhall make and directe oute of the courte of Chauncerye, vnder the kinge &amp; quenes greate Seale, ſeuerall commiſſions. That is to ſaye, to euerye Shire, Rydynge, Lath, Wapentake, Rape, cytye, Towne, Burrough Iſle, and houſeholde, vnto ſuch perſonne and perſonnes, as by his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and other with hym afore named and appointed in lyke maner and fourme as is afore rehearſed, ſhall be thoughte ſuffycyente for the ſeaſſynge and leuyinge of the ſame Subſedye, in all ſhyres and places, accordynge to the true meanynge of thys acte. Whyche Commyſſyon for the paymente of the ſayde Subſedye, ſhall be dyrected and dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
<pb facs="tcp:180783:33"/>to the ſayde commiſſioners, or to one of them before the fyrſte daye of Apryll next comminge, and to euerye of the ſayde commyſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons tenne Sedules, conteynynge in them the tenoure of thys acte, ſhall be affiled, by the whyche commiſſyon the commyſſioners in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ſuche commyſſyon, named, accordynge to thys acte, and as manye of them as ſhall be appoynted by the ſame commyſſyon, ſhall haue full power and aucthorytye to putte the effecte of the ſame commyſſyon in execution.</p>
               <p>And that by the aucthoritie of this acte, after ſuch commiſſion to them dyrected, they maye by theyr aſſentes and agrementes, ſeuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues for the execution of their commyſſyon in hundredes, Lathes wardes, and rapes, Wapentakes, townes, pariſhes, and other places, within the lymyttes of theyr ſayde commyſſyon, in ſuche forme as to them ſhall ſeme expediente to be ordered, and betwene them to be com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moned and agreed, accordynge to the tenoure and effecte of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſyon to them therein dyrected. Vpon which ſeueraunce euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonne of this preſent parliament that ſhalbe commiſſyoner, ſhalbe aſſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned in the hundred wherein he dwelleth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwaies that no perſonne be or ſhal be compelled to be anye commiſſioner, to and for the execution of thys preſente acte, but onelye in the Shyre where he dwelleth and inhabyteth. And that eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye perſonne beynge aſſigned to the contrary therof, in anye wiſe ſhall not be compelled to putte in execution the effecte of thys acte, or anye parte thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> it is alſo enacted by the aucthoritie of this preſent parliament, that the commiſſioners and euerye of them whiche ſhalbe named, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and appoynted accordynge to thys acte, to be commiſſioners in euerye ſuche ſhyre, Ridinge, Lath, Wapentake, Rape, Cytye, towne, Burroughe, Iſle, and the ſame houſeholdes, or any other places, and none other ſhal truelye, effectuallye, and dylygentlye for theyr parte, execute the effecte of thys preſent acte, according to the tenoure therof in euery behalfe, and noo otherwyſe by anye other meanes, wythoute omiſſion, fauoure, dreade, malyce, or anye other thyng to be attempted and done by them or anye of them to the contrary thereof. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Commyſſyoners and as manye of them as ſhalbe appointed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame commiſſion, and none other for thexecution of the ſame Commyſſyon and acte, ſhall for the taxation of the ſame payment of the ſayd Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die before the, vi. daye of Apryll nexte commynge, by vertue of the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſions deliuered vnto them in fourme aboueſayde, directe their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall or ioynte precepte vnto eight, ſeuen, ſixe, fiue, foure, or thre or mo, as for the number of the inhabitauntes ſhalbe requiſite, of the mooſte ſubſtanciall diſcrete, and honeſt perſons inhabytauntes, to be named by the ſayde commiſſioners, or by as manye of them as ſhalbe appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:180783:33"/>by the ſayd commiſſion, of, and in hundredes, lathes, rapes, wapen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes, wardes, paryſhes, townes, and other places, aſwell within ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertyes, Fraunchyſes, auncient demeane, places exempted, and ſaintu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aryes as withoute, within the limittes of the ſhires, rydinges, lathes wapentakes, rapes, Cities, Townes, Burroughes, or Iſle aforeſayd, and other places within the limittes of theyr commyſſyon, vnto the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables, ſubconſtables, Baylyffes, and other like officers, or mynyſters of euery of the ſame hundredes, townes, wardes, lathes, wapentakes, paryſhes, and other places beforeſayd, as to the ſame Commyſſioners and euery number of them, or vnto three or two of them by theyr dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion in diuiſyon ſhall ſeme expedient, as by the maner &amp; vſe of that parties ſhalbe requiſite. Strayghtlye by the ſame precepte chargynge and commaundyng the ſame inhabytauntes, conſtables, and other of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fycers aforeſayde, to whome ſuche precepte ſhalbe ſoo directed, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in their proper perſonnes, before the ſayde Commyſſyoners, or ſuche number of them as they ſhall deuide them ſelfes, accordynge to the tenoure of the ſayde commiſſion, at certayne dayes and places, by the ſayde commiſſyoners or any number of them as is aforeſayd, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Cities, Burroughes, and townes Corporate, or withoute in anye other place, as is aforeſayd, by their dyſcretions, ſhall be lymytted ther vnto, to doo and accomplyſhe al that to them on the partye of the king and Queenes maieſties, ſhalbe enioyned touchynge thys acte. Commaundyng further by the ſame precepte, that he to whoſe handes ſuch precept ſhall come, ſhall ſhewe or deliuer the ſame to the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habytauntes or offycers named in the ſayde precept, and that none of them fayle to accomplyſhe the ſame, vpon payne of fortye ſhillinges, to be forfeyted to the Quenes Maieſtye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> it is further ordeyned by the aucthoritie of thys preſente Parlyamente, that euerye of the Commyſſyoners then beynge, in the Shire, and hauynge noo ſufficiente excuſe for hys abſence, ſhall at the daye and place prelyxed, for that parte wherevnto he was lymytted to appeare in hys proper perſonne. And there the ſame Commyſſyoners beynge preſente, or aſmanye as ſhalbe appoynted by the kynge and queenes Commyſſyon, ſhall call or cauſe to be called before them the ſayde inhabytauntes, and offycers, to whome they haue directed their ſayde preceptes, and whyche hadde in commaundemente there to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the ſayde precepte of the ſayde commyſſyoners, and yf anye perſon ſoo warned make defaulte, onles he then be letten by ſyckenes or lawefull excuſe, and that let then be wytneſſed by the othes of twoo credible perſonnes, or yf anye appearynge, refuſe to be ſworne in forme folowynge, to forfeyte to the kynge and queenes Maieſties, forty ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges, and ſoo at euerye tyme appoynted by the ſayd commyſſioners, for the ſayde taxations, vnto ſuch tyme, the number of euery ſuche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonnes,
<pb facs="tcp:180783:34"/>haue appeared and certified in fourme vnder written, and eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye of them, ſo makynge defaulte, or refuſynge to be ſworne, to forfeyt to the kyng and queenes Maieſties, fortye ſhyllynges. And vpon the ſame appearaunce had, one of the moſt ſubſtanciall inhabytauntes, or officer ſo beynge warned and appearynge before the ſayd commiſſyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſhalbe ſworne vpon a boke, openlye before the commiſſioners in fourme folowyng. I ſhal truely enquyre with my felowes, that ſhalbe charged with me of the hundrede, wapentake, warde, towne or other place, of the beſt and moſt value of the ſubſtaunce of euery perſon dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge and abydynge within the limittes of the places, that I and my felowes ſhalbe charged with, and of other, which ſhal haue his or their moſt reſorte vnto anye of the ſayde places, and chargeable with anye ſumme of monye, by this acte of the ſayd ſubſedye, and of all other arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles that I ſhalbe charged with touchyng the ſayd acte, and according to the intente of the ſame. And therevpon as nere as it maye be, or ſhall come to my knowledge, truely to preſente and certifye before you the names, ſurnames, and the beſte and vttermooſte ſubſtaunce and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues, of euerye of them, alwell of landes, tenementes, and other heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentes poſſeſſions, and proffytttes, as of goodes, cattells, debtes, and other thynges, chargeable by the ſayde acte, withoute anye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceylemente, loue, fauoure, affection, dread, feare, or malyce, as neare as god wyll geue me grace, ſo helpe me God and the holye contentes of this boke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> euery other perſon that ſhall appere there by the ſame pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes ſhal make like othe, and vpon the othe ſo taken as is aforeſayde, by the inhabytauntes and officers of euery hundred, ward, wape<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>take towne, or other place, the ſayd commiſſioners, ſhall openly there tede or cauſe to be red vnto them the ſayd rates, and openlye declare the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of their charge vnto them, in what maner and fourme they ought and ſhuld make their certificate, accordyng to the rates and ſummes thereof aboueſayde, and of all maner of perſonnes, as wel of alyens &amp; ſtraungers, denizens or not denizens, inhabytyng within thys realme as of ſuch perſonnes as be borne vnder the Queenes obeyſaunce char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geable to thys acte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> of the poſſeſſions goodes and cattels, of fraternities, guyldes, corporations, brotherhedes miſteries, and comminaltyes, and other as is aboueſayde, and of perſones beynge in the partyes of beyond the Seas, hauynge goodes or cattels, landes, or tenementes, within thys Realme as is aforeſayd. And of al goodes beyng in the cuſtody of any perſonne or perſonnes, to thuſe of anye other as is aboueſayde, by the whych information, and ſhewing the ſayde perſonnes ſhuld haue ſuch playne knowledge of the true intente of this preſent Acte, and of the maner of their certyfycate, that the ſame perſones, ſhall haue no reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:180783:34"/>cauſe to excuſe them by ignoraunce. And after ſuch othe and the Statute of the ſayde Subſidie, and the maner of the ſayde certificate to be made in writinge, conteyninge the names and ſurnames of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſonne, and whyther they be borne withoute the Queenes obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunce or within, and the beſt value of euery perſonne, in euery degre, as well of yerely value of landes and tenementes, and of ſuch lyke poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion and profittes, as the value of goodes and cattelles, debtes, and euery thing to the certificate requiſite and neceſſary to them declared, the ſayde Commiſſioners there beyng, ſhal by theyr diſcretions apoint and limitte vnto the ſayde perſonnes an other daye and place to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare before the ſayde commiſſioners, and charginge the ſayd perſons that they in the meane time ſhall make diligente enquirie by all wayes and meanes of the premiſſes, and then and there euerye of them vpon payne of forfeyture of .xl.s. to the kynge and Quenes Maieſties, to ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare at the ſayde newe prefixed daye, and place, there to certifie vnto the ſayde Commiſſioners in wrytinge, according to theyr ſayd charge and accordinge to the true intente of the ſayd graunt of Subſedy, and as to them in maner aforeſayde hath bene declared and ſhewed by the commiſſioners. At which daye and place ſo to them prefixed, yf anye of the ſayde perſons make defaulte, or appeare, and refuſe to make the ſayd certificate, that then euery of them ſo offendinge, to forfeyte to the kynge and Quenes Maieſties, forty ſhyllynges, except onelye a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable excuſe of his defaulte, by reaſon of ſyckenes, or otherwyſe by the othes of two credible perſonnes, there witneſſed be had. And of ſuche as appeare ready to make certificate, as is aforeſayd, the ſayd commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners there beyng ſhall take and receaue the ſame certificate, and eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye part therof, and the names and values, and ſubſtance of euery per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo certified. And if the ſame commiſſioners ſee cauſe reaſonable they ſhall examen the ſayde preſenters therof, and thervpon the ſayde commiſſioners at the ſayd dayes and place, by theyr agremente emon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them ſelfes, ſhal from time to time openly there prefixe a daye at a certayne place or places within the limittes of theyr commiſſion by theyr diſcretion, for theyr further proceding to the ſayd aſſeſſyng of the ſayde Subſidie, and therevpon at the ſayde day of the ſayde certificate as is aforeſayde taken, the ſame commiſſioners ſhall make theyr pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepte or preceptes to the conſtables, ſubconſtables, Baylyffes, or other officers of ſuche hundredes, wapentakes, townes, or other places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayde, as the ſame commiſſioners ſhall be of, compriſinge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyninge in the ſame precepte, the names and furnames of all perſons preſented before them in the ſayde certifycate, of whome yf the ſayde commiſſioners or as many of them as ſhalbe therevnto appoynted by the kynge and quenes commiſſion, ſhall then haue vehement ſuſpect to be of more greater value or ſubſtaunce in landes, goodes, cattelles, or
<pb facs="tcp:180783:35"/>ſummes of monye owynge to them, or other ſubſtaunce beforeſaſd, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon ſuche perſonne or perſonnes ſhalbe certified, the ſame commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners ſhall make theyr precepte or preceptes, directed to the conſtables, baylyffes, or other officers, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch precept ſhalbe directed, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the ſame conſtables, bailiffes, or other officers, to warne ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonnes whoſe names ſhalbe compriſed in the ſayd precept, at their ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or to theyr perſonnes, that the ſame perſons named in ſuche pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes, and euery of them, ſhall perſonally appeare before the ſayd com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſioners, at the ſame newe prefixed day and place, there to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by al wayes and meanes by the ſaide commiſſioners, of theyr grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt ſubſtaunce and beſt value, and of all and euerye ſummes of money owynge to them, and other whatſoeuer matter concernynge the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes or anye of them, accordynge to this Acte. At whiche daye and place ſo prefixed, the ſayde commiſſioners then there beynge, or as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them as ſhall be there vnto appoynted by the kynge and Quenes commiſſion, ſhall cauſe to be called the ſayde perſonnes, whoſe names ſhalbe comptiſed in the ſayde precepte, as is beforeſayde, for theyr exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination. And if any of thoſe perſonnes whiche ſhoulde be warned as is beforeſayde to be examyned, whyche at anye tyme after the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, and before the prefyred daye, ſhalbe within ſuch place wher he maye haue knowledge of his ſayde appearaunce to be made, make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faulte and appeare not, onles a reaſonable cauſe, or elles a reaſonable excuſe by the othes of two credible perſonnes before the ſayde commiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſioners be truely alledged for his diſcharge, that then euerye of them ſo makynge defaulte, to be taxed to the kynge and Queenes Maieſties, with and at the double ſummes of the rate that he ſhoulde or oughte to haue ben ſette at for and after the beſte value of hys landes, or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce vpon him certified, yf he had appeared, by the diſcretion of the commiſſioners there beynge. And whiche commiſſioners ſhall trauell with euery of the perſonnes ſo then and there appearynge, whoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes ſhall be expreſſed in the ſayde precepte or preceptes, and in whome anye vehement ſuſpecte was or ſhall be hadde, in fourme aforeſayde, by all ſuche wayes and meanes they can. And that euerye ſpirituall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at the ſayde taxations of the ſayde Subſedye, ſhall be rated and ſet accordinge to the rate aboueſayde, of, and for euerye pounde that the ſame ſpyrituall perſon or any other to his vſe, hath by diſcent, bargayne or purchaſe, in fee ſimple, fee tayle, terme of lyfe, terme of yeares, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, by warde, or by copy of courte rolle, in any manours, landes, tenementes, rentes, ſeruices, offices, fees, corrodies, annuities, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditamentes, after the true, iuſte, and yearelye value thereof, after, and accordinge as other the kynge and Quenes Maieſties ſubiectes, born within this realme be charged in ſourme aboue remembred. So that it extende to the yearely value of twentye ſhyllynges or aboue. And yf
<pb n="xxxiii" facs="tcp:180783:35"/>any perſon certified or rated by vertue of thys acte, be he commiſſioner or other to anye maner of value, doth finde hym ſelfe greued wyth the ſame preſentment, ſeaſſynge, or taxinge, and therevpon complayne to the commyſſyoners before whome he ſhalbe rated, ſeaſſed, or taxed, or before two of them. That then the ſaid commiſſioners ſhal by al waies and meanes examen perticulerly and diſtinctlye the perſonne ſoo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnynge, and other his neyghboures by their diſrretion, of euery his landes and tenementes aboue ſpecified, and of euerye his goodes, cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells, and dettes, aboue mentioned, and after due examynatyon and perfitte knowledge thereof had and perceaued by the ſayd commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, whiche ſhall haue power by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, the ſayde commiſſyoners or two of them, to whome any ſuche complaynt ſhalbe made, by theyr diſcretions vpon the oth of the ſayde perſonne ſoo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playnyng, maye abate, defalke, encreaſe or enlarge the ſame aſſeſſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t accordynge as it ſhall appeare vnto them iuſte vpon the ſame examy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. And the ſame Summe ſo abated, defaulked, encreaſed, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged, to be ſtreated in fourme as hereafter enſueth, ſo that he come be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the eſtreates of the ſame aſſeſſynge be deliuered by the ſayde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, into the kyng and Queenes maieſties eſcheker. And if it be proued by wytneſſe, his owne confeſſyon, or other lawefull wayes or meanes, within a yeare after any ſuch othe made, that the ſame perſon ſo taxed and ſworne was of any better or greter value in lands, goods or other thynges aboue ſpecifyed at the tyme of hys ſayd othe, then the fame perſon ſo ſworne did declare vpon his ſayde oth, that then euerye ſuch perſon ſo offending, ſhall loſe and forfeyte to the kyng and quenes maieſties ſo much in lawefull mony of Englande as the ſaid perſon ſo ſworne was ſet at or taxed to paye. And al perſons ſet, rated, and taxed as is aforeſayd, ſhalbe bound and charged by the ſame, and the ſomme or ſommes vpon hym ſet to be due towardes the payment of the ſayde Subſedy and to be leuied as hereafter ſhalbe ſpecified.</p>
               <p>And alſo it is enacted by the ſame aucthoritie, that euery perſon, to be taxed at the ſame taxation as is aforeſaid, ſhalbe rated taxed and ſet and the ſomme on him ſet to be leuied at ſuch place wher he and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mylye at the tyme of the ſame preſentment to be made, ſhall kepe hys houſe or dwellyng, or where he then ſhalbe mooſte conuerſaunte aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge and reſyaunte, or ſhal haue hys moſt reforte, and ſhalbe beſt kno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wen, at the tyme of the ſayde certificate to be made, and no where els. And that no commiſſyoner for thys Subſedy ſhalbe rated or taxed for his goodes, or landes, but in the Shire and other place where he ſhall be commiſſioner. And that yf any perſon chargeable to thys acte, the tyme of the ſayde aſſeſſyng, happen to be out of thys realme, and out of Wales, or farre from the place where he ſhalbe knowen, then he to be ſette where he was laſt abydynge in thys Realme, or within Wales,
<pb facs="tcp:180783:36"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="xxxiii" facs="tcp:180783:36"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180783:37"/>and beſt knowen, and after the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and value, and other profites of euery perſon knowen, by thexamination, certificate, and other ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wyſe as is aforeſayde. The ſayde commiſſioners or as manye of them, as ſhalbe appoynted by the kyng and quenes Maieſties commiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion, ſhall after the rate aforeſayd, ſet and taxe euery perſon, according to the rate of the ſubſtaunce and value of his lands, goodes, and other proffyttes, whereby the greteſt and moſt beſt ſomme accordyng to his mooſte ſubſtaunce, by reaſonne of thys acte myghte or maye be ſette or taxed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwaies that euery ſuch perſon, whych ſhalbe ſet or tax<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed for payment of, and to this Subſedy, for and after the yearely value of his landes, tenementes, and other real poſſeſſions or proffites, at the ſayde taxations, ſhal not be ſette and taxed, for his goodes and cattels, or other moueable ſubſtaunce, at the ſame taxation. And that he that ſhall be charged or tared for the ſame Subſedy, for his goodes, cattels, and other moueables at the ſame taxation, ſhall not be charged taxed or chargeable for his landes, or other real poſſeſſions, or proffits aboue ſayd, at the ſame taxation, nor that anye perſon be double charged for the ſayde Subſedy, neither ſet or taxed at ſeuerall places, by reaſon of thys acte, any thing conteined in this preſente acte notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> that it be ordeyned by the ſame aucthoritie of thys preſent parlyament, that no perſon hauynge two manſions, or two places to reſorte vnto, or calling him ſelfe houſeholde ſeruaunte, or waitinge ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt to the kyng and quenes Maieſties, or other lord or lady, maiſter or maiſtres, be excuſed vpon hys ſaying from the raxe of the ſaid Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedy in nether of the places, where he may be ſet, onleſſe he bring a certi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fycate in writyng from the commiſſioners, wher that he is ſoo ſette in dede at one place. And if any perſon that ought to be ſet by reſon of his remouyng or reſorting to two places, or by reaſon of his ſaying that he ells wher was taxed, or by reaſon of any priuilege by his dwellynge or abydynge in any place not beyng forpryſed in thys acte, or otherwyſe by hys couine or craft happen to eſcape from the ſayde taxations, and be not ſet, and that proued by preſentment examination or informatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> before the ſame commyſſyoners, or aſmanye of them as ſhalbe by the ſame commiſſion appointed, or by the Barons of the kyng and quenes maieſties eſchequer, or two iuſtyces of the peace of the countye where ſuch perſon dwelleth, then euerye ſuch perſon that by ſuche meanes or otherwyſe wyllinglye by couine ſhall happen to eſcape from the ſayde taxation or payment aforeſayd, and not be rated, taxed, or ſette, ſhalbe charged vpon the knowledge and proffe thereof with and at the dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble value that he ſhoulde or ought to haue bene ſet at afore, accordynge to hys behauour, the ſame double value to be taxed gathered, and pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed of hys goodes and catcells, landes, and tenementes, to wardes the
<pb n="xxxiiii" facs="tcp:180783:37"/>ſayde Subſedy, and further to be puniſhed accordyng to the diſcrety<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the barons, iuſtices and commiſſyoners before whom he ſhalbe conuycted for hys offence and deceite in that behalfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> further be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that the ſayde commyſſioners of euery commiſſion ſhall accordyng to their diuiſions and after they be deuided haue full power and aucthoritie by this act, to ſet tax and ſeſſe euery other commiſſioner ioyned with them in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch commiſſion and diuiſion. And ſhal alſo aſſeſſe euerye aſſeſſoure, within their diuyſyon for hys and their goodes, landes, and other the premiſſes as is aboueſayd, by the whych ſayde commyſſyon the ſayde commiſſioners, ſhall indifferently ſet taxe and ſeſſe them ſelfes and the ſayd aſſeſſoures, and that aſwell the ſummes vpon euerye of the ſayde commyſſyoners and aſſeſſoures, ſoo ſeſſed, rated, and taxed as the ſummes made and preſented by the preſenters ſworne as is aforeſayd, ſhalbe writtenne certifyed and eſtreated. And the eſtretes thereof to be made with other the inhabytauntes of the parties, within the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites of the ſame commiſſion and diuyſyon, ſo to be gathered and leui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in lyke maner as it ought or ſhould haue bene, yf the ſayd commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner had not bene in the ſayde commiſſion. And that all perſons of the eſtate of a Baron or barons, and euery eſtate aboue ſhalbe charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their frehold and value as is aforeſayd, by the chauncellor or keper of the gret Seale, Treſurer of England, lord preſident of the kynge and quenes maieſties pryuy councell, and lord prynye Seale, for the tyme beynge, or other perſons by the kyng and quenes maieſties auctorytie, to be limitted, and they to be charged for the ſaid ſeueral paymentes of the ſayde Subſedye after the forme of the ſayde graunte accordynge to the taxation aforeſayde, and the ſummes vpon them ſette with the names of the Collectoures appoynted for the gatheringe and pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge of the ſame, to be eſtreated, delyuered, and certyfied at dayes and places aboue ſpecyfyed, by the lorde Chauncelor, treſorer, lord preſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the councel, and lord pryuy Seale for the tyme being, or ſuch other perſons, as ſhalbe limitted by the kyng and quenes maieſties, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the taxes and aſſeſſes of the ſayd ſimmes vpon and by the ſayd aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſynge and certificate as is aforeſayd made, the ſayde commiſſioners or as many of them as ſhalbe there vnto appointed by the kynge and quenes maieſties commiſſion, ſhal with al ſpede and withoute delaye, by the writinge eſtreted of the ſayd taxe thereof, vnder the Seale and ſignes manuel of the ſayd commiſſyoners, or of as manye of them as ſhal be appointed at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leſt to be made, ſhalbe deliuered vnto ſufficient &amp; ſubſtantiall inhabitauntes conſtables, ſubconſtables, Baylyffes, and other offycers, ioyntly of hundredes, townes, paryſhes and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces aforeſayde, within their limittes, or to other ſufficiente perſonnes inhabytauntes of the ſame onely by the diſcretion of the ſame commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners,
<pb facs="tcp:180783:38"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="xxxiiii" facs="tcp:180783:38"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:180783:39"/>and as the place and parties ſhall requyre, aſwel the perticuler names as ſurnames, as the remembraunce of all ſummes of monye, taxed and ſette of and vpon euery perſon aſwel man as woman char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable to thys acte, houſeholder and al other inhabitauntes and dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers within the ſayde pariſhes, townes, and places contributory to this acte of Subſedye. By aucthoritie of whiche writynge or eſtrete ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered, the ſayde offycers and other perfonnes ſo named and deputed ſeuerallye, ſhall haue full power and aucthoritie by vertue of thys acte immediatelye after the delyuerye of the ſayde wrytynge or eſtreate, to demaunde leuye and gather of euery perſon therein ſpecified, the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me or Summes in the ſame wrytinge or eſtrete compriſed. And for none paymente thereof to diſtrayne the ſame perſonne or perſonnes ſoo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge behynde by their goodes and cattells. And the diſtreſſes ſoo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to kepe by the ſpace of eyght dayes at the coſtes and charges of the owner thereof. And yf the ſayde owner do not pay ſuche ſumme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye as ſhalbe taxed by thys acte within the ſame .viii. dayes, then the ſame diſtreſſe to be apprayſed by foure, three or two of the inhabitaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes where ſuch diſtreſſe is taken, and alſo to be ſolde by the ſayd conſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and other collectoure for the paymente of the ſayde monye, and the ouerplus comynge of the ſale and kepynge thereof yf any be, to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatelye reſtored to the owner of the ſame diſtreſſe which ſayd offy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and other perſonnes, ſoo deputed to aſke, take, gather and leuye the ſayde Summes, ſhall anſwere and be charged for the portion one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them aſſigned or limitted, to be gathered, leuied and compryſed in the ſayde wrytinge or eſtrete to them as is before ſayde deliuered, to thuſe of our Soueraygne Lady the Quenes Maieſtie, and her heires and ſucceſſoures. And the ſayd ſumme in that writing or eſtrete com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pryſed to pay vnto the high collector or collectors of that place for the collection of the ſame in maner and forme vnderwritten, thervnto to be named and deputed, and the ſame inhabitauntes and offycers ſoo gatheryng the ſame perticuler ſummes, for their collection thereof, ſhal retaine for euery twenty ſhillynges, ſo by them receued and payd two pence, and that to be allowed at the payment of their collection by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be made, by the hygh collector or collectoures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>AND</hi> further be it enacted by the ſayde aucthoritie, that the ſaid commiſſyoners or the more parte of them as ſhall take vpon them thex ecution and beſynes of the ſayd commyſſion, ſhal for the ſame paiment of the ſayd ſubſedye, name ſuch ſufficient and able perſons, which then ſhall haue and poſſeſſe landes and other hereditaments, in their owne right of the yearely value of twenty poundes, or goodes to the value of two hundred markes at the leaſte, and the perſonnes feuerallye by the dyſcreſions of the ſame commiſſyoners, in ſhires, ridynges, lathes, wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentakes, rapes, cities, townes corporat, and other whatſoeuer places
<pb n="xxxv" facs="tcp:180783:39"/>aſwel w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in places priuileged as withoute, not beinge forpriſed within this act to be high collectors, &amp; haue the collection and receipt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid ſummes ſet &amp; leuiable within the precinct, limit, and bondes wher thei ſhalbe ſo limitted to gather and receiue. So euery of the which collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors ſo ſeuerally named, the ſaid co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners or two of them at the leſt ſhal w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alſpede and without delay after the ſayd whole ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the ſaid ſubſedy, be ſet by all the limits of the ſame theyr comiſſion, or in ſuche li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits as the high collectors ſhalbe ſo ſeuerally aſſigned, ſhal vnder their ſeales, and ſignes manuel deliuer one eſtreat indented in perchemente to euery of the ſaid high collectors, compriſing in it the names of al ſuch perſons as were aſſigned to leuy the ſayd perticuler ſummes, and the ſummes of euery hundred, wapentake, towne, or other place aforeſaid, with the names and ſurnames of the perſons ſo chargeable according to the eſtrete ſo firſt therof made as is aforeſaid, and deliuered, and the collectors ſo to be aſſigned, ſhalbe charged to aunſwer the hole ſumme compriſed in the ſaid eſtreat limitted to his collection as is aforeſayde.</p>
               <p>Prouided alwayes and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that the ſayd comiſſioners hauinge auctoritie by this acte to name and nominate the ſayde high collectors of the ſayd ſubſedy, ſhal immediat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the nomination and election, take by auctoritie of this preſente parliament, ſufficient recogniſaunces or obligations, without any fee, or rewarde to be payde therefore of euerye perſon ſo by them to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be high collectours, to be bound to the kynge and quenes maie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſties, in double ſumme of the ſumme of his collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and to be indorced and made vpon ſuch condition, that is to ſay, for the collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame paiment of the ſayd ſubſedy, that if the ſayd collector his heyres or exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors do truelye content and pay to the vſe of the quenes maieſtie, her heyres or executors, in receipt of the ſaid eſchequer before the ſaid .xxiiij day of Iune next cominge, ſo muche of the ſayd ſumme of mony allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and appointed to his collection, as he ſhall collecte and gather, and contente and paye the reſidue of his collection and charge within one moneth next after ſuch time as he hath gathered and collected y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame reſidue, that then the ſaide recogniſaunce or obligation to be voyde, or elles to ſtand in full ſtrength and vertue, whiche ſayd recogniſaunces or obligations ſo taken, the ſayd comiſſioners ſhall ſeuerallye certyfye and deliuer into the king and quenes maieſties eſchequer, with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall certificates of the ſayd taxations and rates of the paymentes of the ſaid ſubſedy, at and by the tyme to them preſcribed and appointed by this act, for the certificate of the taxation of the ſayd ſubſedye, vpon payne of forfeyture of .x. poundes to the kynge and quenes maieſties, for euery recogniſaunce or obligation not certified, and that euery ſuch collector ſo elected named and choſen, vpon requeſt to him made, ſhall knowlege &amp; make the ſayd recogniſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or obligation, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> like pain of forfeiture of .x. pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to the king &amp; quenes maieſtie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> refuſal therof.
<pb facs="tcp:180783:40"/>And euery ſuch collector ſo deputed hauing the ſaid eſtreate in perche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as is aforeſaid, ſhall haue auctoritie by this act, to appoint dayes and places within the circuit of his collection for the payment of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid ſubſedy to him to be made, and therof to gene warninge by proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or otherwyſe to all the ſayd conſtables or other perſons or inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunts, hauing the charge of the perticuler collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within the hundre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, pariſhes, townes, or other places by him or them limitted to make payment for theyr ſayd perticuler collection of euery ſumme as to them ſhal aperteyne, and if at the ſayd day and place ſo limitted and prefixed by the ſayd collectour, the ſaid conſtable, officer, or other perſons or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitauntes as is beforeſayd, for the ſaid perticuler collection appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; aſſigned within ſuch hundred, citie, towne, or other place, do not pay vnto the ſayde collectours the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me within theyr ſeueral hundreds townes, pariſhes, and other places due &amp; compriſed in the ſaid eſtreate therof to them deliuered by the ſaid comiſſioners or ſome of them as is aforeſayd, or ſo much therof as they haue by any meanes receiued, ij. d. of euery pounde, for the ſaid perticuler collection as is beforeſayde, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to be therof allowed, excepted, and abated, that then it ſhall be lawful to the ſaid high collectours and euerye of them, and to theyr aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, to diſtraine euery of the ſayde conſtables, officers, and other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitantes, for theyr ſayd ſeueral and perticuler collections of the ſaid ſummes compriſed in the ſayd eſtreat and writing therof, to them and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as is before expreſſed, deliuered, or for as much of the ſame ſumme as ſo then ſhal happen to be gathered and leuied, and be behind and vnpaid by the goods and cattels of euery of them ſo being behind, and the diſtres ſo taken, to be kept, aprayſed, and ſold as is aforeſaid, &amp; therof to take and leuy the ſummes ſo then being behind and vnpayd, and the ouerplus coming of the ſale of the ſayd diſtres if anye be, to be reſtored and deliuered vnto the owner in fourme aboue remembred.</p>
               <p>Prouided always that no perſon inhabitinge in any citie, borough or towne corporate, ſhalbe compelled to be an aſſeſſour or collectour, of or for any part of the ſayd ſubſedy, in any place or places out of the ſayd citie, boroughe, or towne corporate where he dwelleth.</p>
               <p>And it is alſo by the ſaid auctoritie enacted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any inhabitaunte or officer, or whatſoeuer perſon or perſons charged to and for the collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or receypt of any parte or portion of the ſayd Subſedy, by any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of meanes according to this acte, or any perſon or perſons for them ſelues, or as keper, gardian, deputy, factour, or attourney, of or for anye other perſon or perſonnes, of anye goodes and cattelles of the owner therof at the tyme of the ſayde aſſeaſſyng to be made, beyng out of this realme, or in anye other parties not knowen, or of and for the goodes and cattels of anye other perſon or perſonnes, of anye corporation, fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, miſterye, or other whatſoeuer cominaltye, beynge incorporate, or not incorporate, and all perſonnes hauing in theyr rule, gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb n="xxxvi" facs="tcp:180783:40"/>and cuſtody any goodes or cattells at the tyme of the ſayd aſſeſſyng to be made or which for any cauſe for and by collection, or for him ſelfe, or for any other, or by reaſon that he hath the rule, gouernaunce, or cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of any goodes or cattels of any other perſon or perſons, corporati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cominaltye, or fraternitie, guild, or miſtery, or any ſuch other like, or as factoure deputie or attorney of or for any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhalbe taxed, rated, valued, &amp; ſet to any ſumme or ſummes by reaſon of this acte, and after the taxation or aſſeſſing vpon aniſuch perſon or perſons as ſhalbe char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged with the receipt of the ſame, happen to die or depart from the place where he was ſo taxed and ſet, or his goodes or cattels be ſo eloined, or in ſuch pryuye and couerte maner kepte as the ſaid perſon or perſons charged with the ſame, by eſtretes or other wrytynges from the ſayde commiſſioners, or aſmany of them as ſhalbe thervnto apoynted by the ſayde commiſſion as is aforeſayde, canne ne may leuy the ſame ſumme or ſummes compriſed within the ſame eſtretes by diſtres within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of theyr collection as aforeſayd, or cannot ſel ſuch diſtres or diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes as be taken for any of the ſame paymentes, before the tyme limitted to the highe collectoure for hys paymente to be made in the kynge and Queenes maieſties receipt, then vpon relation thereof made, with due examination by the othe or examination of ſuch perſon or perſonnes, as ſhalbe charged with or for the receypte or collection of the ſame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſayde commiſſioners, or as many of them as by the ſayde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion ſhalbe therevnto apoynted, where ſuche perſon or perſonnes, or other as is aforeſayde, theyr goodes and cattells were ſet and taxed and vpon playne certificate thereof made in the kyng and quenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties eſcheker by the ſame comiſſioners, as wel of the dwelling place, names, and ſummes of the ſayd perſonnes of whom the ſaide ſummes cannot be leuied and had as is aforeſaid, then aſwell the conſtables &amp; other inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts appointed for the ſaid perticuler collection againſt the high collectors, as the high collector vpon his accounte and othin the ſayd eſcheker to be diſcharged thereof, and proces to be made for the kyng and quenes maieſties out of the ſayd eſcheker, by the diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Barons of the ſaid eſcheker agaynſt ſuch perſon his heires or executours, ſo being behind with his payment, and ouer that the ſame commiſſioners to whom any ſuch declaration of the premiſſes ſhalbe made in forme aforeſaid, from time to time ſhal haue ful power and auc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie to direct their precept or preceptes vnto the ſaid perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons charged with any ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me, of for or vpon any ſuch perſon or perſons, or other as is aforeſaid, or to any ſherif, ſteward balif, or other whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer officer miniſter, perſon or perſons of ſuch place or places wher any ſuch perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons, ſo owing ſuch ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me or ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes ſhal haue la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des and teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, or other hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or real poſſeſſions, goodes, &amp; cattels wherby anye ſuch perſon or perſons ſo indetted, his heires executours,
<pb facs="tcp:180783:41"/>or aſſignes or other hauynge the cuſtodye, gouernaunce, or diſpoſition of any goodes cattells, lands, or tenementes, or other hereditamentes, which ought or maye, by this acte lawefully be diſtreined or taken for the ſame, hath and ſhall haue goodes, cattells, landes, tenementes, or other poſſeſſions whereof ſuche ſumme or ſummes, which by any ſuche perſon or perſonnes maye or oughte to be leuied, be it within the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myttes of ſuche commiſſion where ſuch perſon or perſonnes was and were taxed, or withoute, within anye place within thys Realme of Englande, Wales, or other the queenes Maieſties dominions, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or territors, by which precept as well ſuch perſon or perſonnes, as ſhalbe charged to leuye ſuch monye, as thofficers of the place or places where ſuch diſtres maye be taken, ſhall haue ful power and aucthoritie to diſtrayne euerye ſuche perſon indetted, charged and chargeable by thys acte, or his executours or admynyſtratours of hys goodes and cattells, hys gardians, factours, deputies, leſſes, fermers, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſygnes, and alother perſonnes, by whoſehandes or oute of whoſe lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des any ſuch perſon ſhould haue rent, fee, annuitie, or other profytte, or whiche at the tyme of the ſayde aſſeſſinges ſhall haue goodes or cattels or anye other thynge moueable, or anye ſuch perſon or perſones beyng indetted or owynge ſuche ſumme, and the diſtreſſes ſo taken, cauſed to be kepte, apprayſed, and ſolde, in lyke maner and forme as is aforeſayd, for the diſtreſſe to be taken vpon ſuch perſon to be taxed to the ſaid ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedy, &amp; being ſufficient to diſtraine w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the lymyts of the collectours, inhabytantes, or other offycers, charged with or for the ſame ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes ſo vpon them to be taxed. And if any ſuch diſtres for none paymente hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be taken oute of the limit of the ſayd perſons charged and aſſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to leuye the ſame, the perſon ſo charged for the leuye of euery ſuche ſumme by dyſtreſſe, ſhall perceaue and take of the ſayde dyſtres for the laboure of euerye perſon goyng for thexecution thereof, for euery mile that anye ſuche perſon ſo laboureth for the ſame two pence, and euerye fermoure, tenaunt, gardian, factor, or other whatſoeuer perſon, beyng diſtreyned or otherwyſe charged for payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of any ſuch ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me or ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes or anye other ſummes by reaſonne of thys acte, ſhalbe of ſuche ſumme or ſummes of him or them ſo leuied and taken, diſcharged and acquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at hys nexte daye of payment of the ſame, or at the delyuery of ſuch goodes and cattells as he that is ſo diſtrayned had in hys cuſtody and gouernaunce agaynſt him or them that ſhalbe ſoo taxed and ſette, anye graunt or writyng oblygatory or other whatſoeuer matter to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye made heretofore notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>And yf anye ſuch perſon that ſhoulde be ſo diſtreyned haue no lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or tenementes ſuffycyente whereby he or hys tenauntes and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moures maye be diſtrayned, or hath aloined, aliened, or hid his goodes and cattells whereby he ſhoulde or myght be diſtrayned, in ſuch maner
<pb n="xxxvii" facs="tcp:180783:41"/>that ſuche goodes and cattelles ſhall not be knowen or founde, ſo that the ſumme of or by him to be payde in the ſayde fourme, ſhall ne can be conueniently leuied, then vpon relation thereof vnto the commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, or to as manye of them as by the ſayd commiſſion ſhalbe thervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to appoynted, where ſuche perſon or perſons was taxed and ſet, by the othes of him or them that ſhalbe charged with the leuy and paymente of that ſumme or ſummes, the ſame commiſſioners ſhall make a precept in ſuche maner as is aforeſayd, for to attache, take, &amp; arreſt the body of ſuche perſon or perſons that oughte to paye the ſayde ſummes, and by this acte ſhall be charged with and for the ſayde ſumme and ſummes, and theim ſo taken, ſafelye to kepe in priſon within the ſhyre or other place, where anye ſuche perſon or perſons ſhall be taken and attached, there to remayne without bayle or mayneprice, vntyll he haue payde the ſame ſumme or ſummes that ſuche perſons for him ſelfe or for anye other by this acte ſhall be charged or oughte to be charged withal, and alſo for the fees of euery ſuche arreſte to him or them that ſhall execute ſuche precepte twenty pence, and that euery officer vnto whome ſuche precepte ſhalbe directed, do his true diligence, and execute the ſame v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon euery perſon ſo beynge indetted, vpon payne to forfeyt to the king and Quenes maieſties, for euery default in that behalfe .xx. ſhyllinges and that no keper of any gayle, from his gayle ſuffer anye ſuche perſon to go at large by lettinge to bayle, or otherwyſe to departe oute of his priſon before he haue payd his ſayde det, and the ſayde .xx. pence, for the ſayd arreſte, vpon payne to forfeyt to the kinge and quenes maieſties, forty ſhyllynges, and the ſame gayler to paye vnto the kynge and que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes maieſties, the double value as well of the rate whiche the ſayd per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonne ſo impriſoned was taxed at, as of the ſayde .xx. pence for the fees, and like proceſſe and remedye in like fourme ſhall be graunted by the ſayde commiſſioners, or as many of them as by the ſayd comiſſion ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be therevnto apoynted at like information of euery perſon or perſons, beynge charged with any ſumme of money for any other perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, by reaſon of the ſayde Subſedye, and not thereof payde, but wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully withdrawen, ne the ſame leuiable within the limites where ſuch perſons were thervnto taxed, and if the ſumme or ſummes beynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde vnpayde by any perſon or perſonnes, as is aforeſayde, be leuied and gathered by force of the ſayde proces to be made by the ſayde com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners, or if in defaulte or for lacke of paymente thereof, the perſon or perſonnes ſo owinge the ſayde ſumme or ſummes of money, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the ſame commiſſioners to be made as is aforeſayde, be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to priſon in fourme aboueſayde, that then the ſame commiſſioners whiche ſhall awarde ſuche proces, ſhall make certificate thereof in the ſayde eſchequer, of that ſhalbe done in the premiſſes in the terme nexte folowynge, after ſuche ſumme or ſummes of money ſo beinge behinde
<pb facs="tcp:180783:42"/>ſhalbe leuied and gathered, or ſuche perſon or perſonnes for none pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of the ſame committed to pryſon. And if it happen anye of the ſayde collectours to be aſſigned, or any mayer, ſheriffe, ſtewarde, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, the headborough, houſeholder, baylif, or any other officer or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, or other whatſoeuer perſon or perſons, to diſobey the ſayd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners or any of them, at the reaſonable requeſte to theim made by the ſayde commiſſioners, for execution of the ſaid commiſſion, or yf any of the offycers or other perſons do refuſe that to them ſhall appertayne and belonge to do, by reaſon of any precepte to him or them to be dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, or anye reaſonable commaundement, inſtaunce, or requeſte tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinge the premiſſes or other defaulte in any appearaunce or collection to make, or if any perſon being ſuſpect, or not, to be indifferently taxed as is aforeſayde, do refuſe to be examined accordinge to the tenoure of this acte, before the ſayde commiſſioners, or as many of them as ſhalbe thervnto aſſigned as is aforeſayde, or wyll not appeare before the ſame commiſſioners, vpon warninge to him made, or els make reſiſtaunce or reſcues vpon any diſtres vpon him to be taken, for any percell of the ſayde Subſidie, or committe any miſbehauour in any maner of wyſe contrary to this acte, or committe any wylful omiſſion or other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer wylfull, not doynge or miſdoinge contrary to the tenour of this acte or graunt, the ſame commiſſioners and euerye nomber of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue remembred, or two of them at the leaſte, vpon probable knowlege of any ſuche miſdemenours had by information or examination, ſhall and maye ſet vpon euery ſuche offender for euery ſuch offence in name of a fyne by the ſame offender to be forfeyted .xl.s. or vnder, by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of the ſame commyſſioners. And further the ſame commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and euery number of them, or two of them at the leaſt, ſhall haue auctoritie by this preſent acte, to puniſhe euery ſuch offender by impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, there to remaine and be delyuered by theyr diſcretion, as ſhal ſeme to them conuenient, the ſayde ſynes if anye ſuche be, to be certified by the ſayd commiſſioners that ſo aſſeſſed the ſame into the kynge and quenes maieſties eſchequer, there to be leuied and payd by the collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures of that partes for the ſayde Subſidie retourned into the ſayde eſchequer, to be therewith charged with the payment of the ſayd ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedy, in ſuche maner, as if the ſayde fynes had ben ſet and taxed vppon the ſayd offenders for the ſayd Subſidye.</p>
               <p>It is alſo enacted by the ſayde aucthoritie of this parliament, that euery of the ſayd highe collectours, whiche ſhal accoumpt for any part of the ſayde Subſedye in the ſayde Eſchequer vpon theyr ſayde ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall accoumptes to be yelded, ſhalbe allowed at euery of the ſayde pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the ſayd Subſedye, for euery pounde limitted to his collecti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, whereof any ſuche collectour ſhalbe charged and yelde accoumpte ſixe pence, as percell of theyr charge, that is to ſaye, of euerye pounde
<pb n="xxxviii" facs="tcp:180783:42"/>therof for ſuch perſons as then haue had the perticuler collection in the townes and other places as is aforeſaid, ſpecified in his collection two pence and other two pence of euery pounde thereof, euery of the ſayde cheife collectours theyr accoumptauntes to reteyne to theyr owne vſe for theyr labour and charge, in and about the premiſſes, and two pence of euery pound reſidue to be deliuered, allowed, and payde by the ſayd collectoures ſo beynge thereof allowed, to ſuche of the commiſſioners as ſhall take vpon them the buſines and labour, for and aboute the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, that is to ſaye, euerye collectoure to paye that commiſſioner or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners whiche had the orderynge of the wrytinges, of, and for the ſayd Subſedy, where the ſayd collectour or collectours had their col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, for expences of the ſayde commiſſioner ſo taken vpon them the ſayd buſines and laboure of theyr clerkes, writinge the ſayd preceptes and eſtreates for the ſayd collections, the ſame laſt two pence of euerye pound to be deuided amongeſt the ſayde commiſſioners, hauynge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde to theyr labour and buſynes, taken by them or theyr ſayd clerkes in and about the premiſſes, for the whiche part ſo to the commiſſioners atteyninge, the ſayd commiſſioners, ſyxe, fiue, foure, thre, or as manye of them as ſhall be thervnto appointed by the kynge and Quenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties commiſſion, and euery of them ioyntly and ſeuerally for his and theyr ſayd part, may haue his remedy agaynſt the ſayde collectoure or collectours, which therofben and might haue ben allowed by action of debte, in the whiche the defendaunte ſhall not wage his lawe, neither protection, neither iniunction, or other eſſoigne ſhall be allowed. And that no perſon nowe beyng of the number of the companye of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament, nor any commiſſioner, ſhalbe named or aſſigned to be any collectour or ſubcollectour, or preſentour of the ſayde ſubſedie, or of any parte therof, nor no comiſſioners ſhall be compelled to make anye preſentment or certificate, other then in the kinge and quenes maieſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſaid eſcheker, of, for, or concerning the ſayd ſubſedy or any part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and likewiſe that none other perſon that ſhall be named or aſſigned to be commiſſioners in any place, to and for thexecution of this act of ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſedy, be or ſhalbe aſſigned or named head collectours of any of the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the ſayd ſubſedy, neither of any parte thereof. And that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch perſon or perſons which ſhalbe named and apointed as is afore<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſaid to be hed collectors of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid ſubſedy, or for any part therof, &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be &amp; ſhalbe acquited &amp; diſcharged of al maner fees rewards, &amp; of euery other charges in the king and Quenes Maieſties Eſchequer, or els where, of them or any of them by reaſon of that collection, payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts or accoumptes, or anye thynge concerninge the ſame, to be aſked, and that yfanye perſonne receaue and take anye fees, rewardes, or plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of anye ſuche accoumptante, that then he ſhall forfeit to the kyng and Quenes maieſtie, for euery peny or value of penye ſo taken, twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye
<pb facs="tcp:180783:43"/>pence, and ſuffer impriſonment at the king and quenes Maieſties pleaſure, and after the taxinge and ſeaſynge of the ſayde Subſedye, as is aforeſayde, had and made, and the ſayd eſtreates thereof in parche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto the collectours in maner and fourme before rehearſed deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered, the ſayde commiſſioners whiche ſhall take vpon them thexecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this acte, within the limittes of theyr commiſſion, by theyr agre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, ſhall haue metynge together, at whiche metynge euerye of the ſayde commiſſioners whiche then ſhall haue taken vpon them thexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of anye parte of the ſayde commiſſion, ſhall by him ſelfe, or by his ſufficient deputye, truelye certifie and brynge forth vnto the ſayde commiſſioners named in the ſayde commiſſion, the certificate and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentmente made before hym, and ſuche other Commiſſioners as were limitted with him in one limit, ſo that the ſame certificate maye be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted and caſt with the other certificates of the other limittes with in the ſame commiſſion, and then the ſayde commiſſioners and euerye number of them vnto two at the leaſte, as is aforeſayde, yf anye be in lyfe, or theyr executours or adminiſtratours of theyr goodes, yf they be then dede, ſhall ioyntlye and ſeuerallye, as they were deuided within theyr limits, vnder their ſeales by theyr diſcretion, make one or ſeueral wrytynges, indented, conteyninge in it as well the names of the ſayde collectours by the commiſſioners, for ſuch collection and accoumpte in the eſchequer, and paymente in the ſayde receypte, deputed and aſſyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as the groſſe and ſeuerall Summes wrytten vnto euerye ſuche collectoure to receaue the ſayde Subſidye. And alſo all fynes, amerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amentes, and other forfeytures, if any ſuche by reaſon of this acte hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be within the precincte and limitte of theyr commiſſion, to be certified vnto the kynge and quenes maieſties ſayde eſchequer, by the ſayde commiſſioners, in whiche writinge or writinges indented ſo to be certified, ſhalbe playnely declared and expreſſed, the hole and entyre Summe or Summes of the ſayde Subſedye, ſeuerallye lymitted to the collection of the ſayde collectoure, ſeuerallye deputed and aſſygned to the collection of the ſaide Summes, ſo that none of the ſayde colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours ſo certified in the ſayde Eſchequer, ſhall be compelled there to accompte, or to be charged, but onely to and for the ſumme limytted to his collection, and not to or for anye ſumme limitted to the collection of his felowe, but that euery of them ſhall be ſeuerallye charged for theyr parte limitted to theyr collection.</p>
               <p>And if the ſayd commiſſioners ioyned in one commiſſion amongeſt them ſelfes in that matter cannot agre, or yf anye of them be not redye or refuſe to make certificate with other of the ſame Commiſſioners, That then the ſame commiſſioners maye make ſeuerall indentures in fourme aforeſayde, of theyr ſeuerall limittes, or ſeperations of Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, within the limittes of theyr commiſſion, vppon and in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredes,
<pb n="xxxix" facs="tcp:180783:43"/>wardes, wapentakes, Lathes, Rapes, or ſuch other like diuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons within theyrſayde ſeuerall lymyttes of their commyſſyon, as the places there ſhall requyre, to be ſeuered and deuyded, &amp; as to the ſame commyſſioners ſhal ſeme good to make diuiſions of their limits or Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectyons for the ſeuerall charges of the ſame Collectoures. So that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye one Collectoure ſhalbe charged and accoumpte for hys parte to hym to be limitted onely by hym ſelfe and not for anye Summe lymyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the parte of any of hys felowes, and the charges of euerye of the collectoures to be ſet and certifyed ſeuerally vpon them, and euery ſuch Collectoure, vpon hys accompte and paymente of the Somme of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye lymitted within hys collection to be ſeuerallye by hym ſelfe, acquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and dyſcharged in the ſayde eſchequer, without payinge anye ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner fees, or rewardes, to anye perſonne or perſonnes for the ſame, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the payne and penaltye laſt aboueſayd, and not be charged for anye portion of any other collectoure. And yf anye Commyſſyoner after he hath taken certificate of them, that, as is aforeſayde, ſhall before anye ſuch commiſſioner be exammed, and the Summes rated and ſette and the bokes and wrytynges thereof beynge in hys handes, or yf anye col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoure, or other perſon charged with any receipte of anye parte of the ſaid ſubſedy, or any other perſon taxed, or otherwiſe by this act charged with and for anye percell of the ſayde Subſedye, or with anye other Summes, or fynes, amerciamentes, penalty, or other forfeyture, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to dye before the Commiſſioner Collectoure or other whatſoeuer perſon or perſonnes haue executed accomplyſhed, ſatified, or ſufficient lye diſcharged, that whych to euery ſuch perſonne ſhall appertayne or belonge to doo accordynge to thys acte, then thexecutours and heires of euery ſuch perſon, and al other ſeaſed of anye landes, or tenementes, that anye ſuch perſon beyng charged by thys act and deceaſſing before he be dyſcharged thereof, or anye other to hys vſe, onelye had of eſtate of inheritaunce, at the tyme that anye ſuche perſonne was named com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioner, collectoure, or otherwiſe charged with and for anye maner of thinge to be done, ſatiſfyed, or payde by reaſonne of thys acte, and all thoſe that haue in theyr poſſeſſions or handes, anye goodes, or cattells that were to anye ſuche perſonne at the tyme of hys death, or any lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or tenementes, that were the ſame perſonnes at the tyme he was as is aforeſayd, charged by this act, ſhalbe by the ſame, compelled, and charged to do and accomplyſhe in euery caſe as the ſame perſon ſoo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge charged ſhould haue done and myght haue bene compelled to do yf he had bene in playne lyfe, after ſuch rate of the landes, and goodes of the ſayde commiſſioner or collectoure as the partye ſhal haue in hys handes. And yf the ſayde Commyſſyoners for cauſes reaſonable them mouynge ſhall thynke it not conuenyent to ioyne in one certyfycate as is beforeſayde, then the ſayde perſonne or perſonnes that ſhal firſt iome
<pb facs="tcp:180783:44"/>together, or he that ſhal fyrſte certifye the ſayde writynge indentyd (as is aforeſayde) ſhall certyfye all the names of the commiſſioners of that commiſſion, whervpon ſuch wrytinges ſhalbe there then to be certy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, with the diuiſion of the hundreds, wapentakes, wardes, tithings or other places, to and amonge ſuch commyſſyoners of the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion where ſuche ſeperations and diuyſyon ſhalbe, with the groſſe Sommes of monye aſwell of and for the ſayde Subſedye, taxed or ſet of or within the ſayde hundredes, wardes, wapentakes, or other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to hym or them deuyded or aſſygned, that ſhall ſoo certyfy the ſaid fyrſte wrytynge, as of fynes, amerciamentes, penaltyes, or other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feytures, (yf anye happen to be) within the ſame lymyttes, wherof the ſame wrytynges ſhalbe certified, and after ſuche wrytynges indented whyche as is aforeſayde, ſhalbe certyfyed &amp; not conteyne in it the hole and full Summes ſet and taxed within the lymyttes of the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſſyon, thother commiſſioners of the ſame before the day of paiment of the ſayde Subſedye, ſhall certifye into the ſayde exchequer, by theyr wrytynge or wrytinge, indented to be made as is aforeſayd, the groſſe and ſeuerall Summes ſet and taxed within the places, to them lymit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, for the ſayde Subſedye, and other fynes, amercyamentes, penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes, and forfeytures, with the names of the hundredes, wardes, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentakes, and other places, to them aſſigned, or ells by theyr ſayd wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes indented to certyfye at the ſayd place before the ſayd day of pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, ſuche reaſonable cauſes, for their excuſes, whye they maye not make ſuche certifycate of and for the ſayde Subſedye, whyche ſynes amercyamentes, and other forfeytures growinge or ſette by reaſon of the cauſes of their lettes or of their none certyfying as is aboueſayd, or ells in defaulte thereof proces to be made oute of the kyng and quenes maieſties ſayde Eſcheker, agaynſte the ſayd commyſſyoners, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of them not making certificate, as is aforeſayde, by the dyſcreſyon of the Treſurer or Barons of the ſayde eſchequer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted by thaucthoritye aforeſayd, that the inhabytauntes of the Paryſhe of Saynte Martynne called Stamforde Baron, in the Suburbes of the burroughe and towne of Stampforde, in the Southe parte of the water there called Welland, whych hereafter ſhalbe contributorye to the paymente of thys preſent Subſedye, graunted to the quenes maieſtie, her heires and ſucceſſors, ſhalbe aſſeſſed, rated, and taxed for thys tyme by ſuch commyſſyoners, whych ſhalbe appoynted for the taxynge, ratyng, and ſeſſynge of ſuch Subſedye or taxe within the countye of Lyncolne, and ſhal be for this tyme contrybutorye, and paye the ſayde Subſedye, to the collectoure or collectoures, whyche ſhalbe aſſygned and appoynted for the leuying and gatherynge of the ſame, with the aldermen and burges of the ſaid boroughe and towne of Stampford.</p>
               <pb n="xl" facs="tcp:180783:44"/>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſaid that all and euery perſon and perſonnes, hauynge manoures, landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes, chargeable to the payment of the Subſedye, graunted to the Quenes Maieſtie, by this acte, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hauynge ſpirituall poſſeſſions chargeable to her ſayde Maieſtie, by the graunte made by the cleargy of thys Realme, in this their conuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and ouer thys hauyng ſubſtaunce in goodes, and cattels, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable by thys ſayd acte, that then yf any of the ſayd perſon or perſons be hereafter charged aſſeſſed and taxed for the ſayde manoures, lands, and tenementes, and ſpirituall poſſeſſions, and alſo aſſeſſed, charged &amp; taxed for his or their goodes, or cattells, that then he or they ſhalbe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye charged by vertue of thys acte, for his and their ſayde manoures, landes, tenementes, hereditamentes, or ſpirituall poſſeſſions, or onely for hys ſayde goodes, and cattels, the beſte thereof to be taken for the quenes Maieſtie and not to be charged for both, or double charged for anye of them, anye thyng in thys acte conteined to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alwayes that thys graunt of Subſedy, nor anye thynge therein conteyned, in any wiſe extende to charge the inhabitauntes, or dwellers within Ireland, Ierneſey, and Garneſey, or anye of them, of or concernynge any manours, landes, tenementes, or other poſſeſſions goodes, cattels, or other moueable ſubſtaunce, whyche the ſayd inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytauntes or dwellers or any other to their vſe haue within Ireland, Ierneſey, and Garneſeye, or in anye of them, or of for or concernynge anye fees, or wages, whych anye of the ſayde inhabytauntes, or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers haue of the kynge and quenes Maieſties, for there attendaunce, and doynge ſeruyce to oure ſayd ſoueraygne. Lord and Ladye, in Ire<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lande, Ierneſey and Garneſeye, or in anye of them, anye of them, anye thynge in this preſente acte, to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alſo that thys preſent acte of Subſedy, ne anye thynge therein conteyned, extende to anye of the Englyſhe inhabytauntes, or reſiauntes, in any of the countyes of Northumberlande, Cumberland Weſtmerlande, the towne of Barwycke the towne of Newecaſtell vpon Tyne, and the Byſhopricke of Durham, nor to anye of them, of for or concerninge any manoures, landes, tenementes, or other poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, goodes, cattells, or other moueable ſubſtaunce, whyche the ſame Inhabytauntes or dwellers, or any other to their vſe haue within the ſayde counties of Northumberlande, Cumberlande, Weſtmerlande, or the towne of Barwicke, the towne of Newecaſtell vpon Tyne, or the Byſhoprycke of Durham, or anye of them, or of for and concerning any fees, or wages, whiche anye of the ſayde. Inhabytauntes, or dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lers haue of the kynge and Queenes Maieſtyes, for their atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunce and doinge ſeruyce to the kynge and Quenes maieſtyes, for or
<pb facs="tcp:180783:45"/>within the ſayde counties of Northumberlande, Cumberlande, Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merlande, the towne of Barwycke, the Towne of Newecaſtell vpon tyne, and the Byſhopprycke of Durham, or anye of them, to or for the ſayde taxynge, leuying gatherynge or paymente, but that the Engliſh inhabytauntes, and reſiauntes, and euerye of them, of the ſaid cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ties Byſhopricke, and townes, and euerye of them, ſhalbe of and from the ſayde Subſedye, and euerye percell thereof, and for their manoures, landes, tenementes, fees, wages, goodes, and cattells, lyinge and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge in the ſayde counties, townes, and Byſhoprycke, or anye of them vtterlye acquited and diſcharged. Any thing in thys preſente acte be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearſed to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alſo that all letters patentes, graunted by the king or queenes maieſtie or anye of her moſt noble progenitoures, to anye Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Burroughes, or townes, within thys realme, of anye maner ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertyes, pryuileges or exemptions from the burden and charge of any ſuche graunt of Subſedyes, whych be at thys preſent time in force and vayleable, ſhal remayne good and effectuall, to the ſayde Cytyes, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, and townes, hereafter, accordynge to the purportes thereof, thoughe the inhabytauntes of the ſame, ſhall vpon the gret and weigh tye conſyderation of the graunt aforeſayd, be for thys graunt charged and contributory, in like maner, fourme and ſorte as other Cityes, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, and townes whych be not in anye wyſe pryuileged, be from ſuch graunt of Subſedy excepted.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alwayes and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſaid, that no Orphant or Infant within the age of .xxi. yeare, borne within anye of the quenes maieſties dominions, ſhalbe charged to anye pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente of thys Subſedye, for hys or her goodes and cattelles, to him or her lefte or bequethed. Anye thyng in thys acte conteined to the contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>PROVIDED</hi> alſo that thys acte nor any thing therein conteined, ſhal extende to the goodes, or landes of anye college, Hall, or Oſtell, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the vniuerſities of Oxenforde, and Cambrydge, or any of them, or to the goodes or landes of the colledge of Wynton founded by Byſhope Wyckeham, or to the goodes or landes of the college of Eton, nexte Wyndeſore, or to the goodes, or Landes, of anye free gramer ſcoole, within the realme of Englande or Wales, or to the goodes of anye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Scolemayſter, or ſcoller, within the ſayde vniuerſities and colled<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, or anye of them, there remaynynge for ſtudye, withoute fraude or couyne, or to the goodes and landes of any Hoſpytall, meaſondewe or Spitelhouſe prepared and vſed for the ſuſtentation and releyfe of pore people. Anye thyng in thys acte conteyned to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
               <p>Prouyded alſo, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that
<pb n="xli" facs="tcp:180783:45"/>foraſmuche as diuers and ſundrye the kynges and Quenes Maieſties tenauntes and other inhabitauntes and dwellers within the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Penbroke, Carmarthen, Cardigan, Glamorgan, Breckenocke, Radnour, Mongomery, Denbigh, Flynt, Merioneth, Angleſey, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naruan, and of the countye palantine of Cheſter, be at this preſente tyme charged and chargeable with the ſeuerall paymentes of diuers great ſummes of monye by the name of Myſe, due to their maieſtyes, accordinge to the ſeuerall cuſtomes of the ſayde counties, for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereof diuers and ſundrye the gentlemen and other the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitauntes, be, and ſtand bounden to theyr highnes. And that alſo ther do remayne yet vnpayde in diuerſe of the ſayde dominions and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie palantyne, the Subſedye graunted to the kynge and Quenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties.</p>
               <p>Be it therefore ordeyned and enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that this acte of Subſedye, or any thynge therein conteyned, ſhall not extende to charge any of the kynge and Quenes tenauntes and other inhabitauntes and dwellers within any of the ſayde counties of Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broke, Carmarthen, Cardigan, Glamorgan, Brecknocke, Radnoure, Mongomery, Denbigh, Flint, Merioneth, Angleſey, Carnaruan, and the countie palantine of Cheſter, beynge charged or chargeable wyth the ſayde Myſe, for, or in any of the paymentes of the ſayde Subſidye, graunted to the kynge and Quenes Maieſties by this acte, vntyll the ſeuerall dayes and tymes appointed and agreed for the paiment of the ſayde Myſe, ſhall be expired. And likewyſe the dayes and tymes of the ſayde Subſidye latelye graunted to oure ſayde Soueraygne Lorde and Ladye be paſt and expyred. And that then the paiment of the ſayd Subſidye graunted by this preſent acte, ſhall be made at the receipte of the kynges and queenes Eſchequer, before the fyrſt daye of Marche nexte folowinge, after the dayes appointed for the latter paymente to be made of the ſayde myſes, and alſo of the payment of the ſayd former Subſidye.</p>
               <p>Furthermore be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayd, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tenants and dwellers of euerye the ſayde counties in this prouiſo remembred, ſhall ſeuerally before the feaſt of Penthecoſt nexte enſuinge, certifye in the ſayd court of Eſchequer, vnder the ſeales of two Iuſtices of peace of euerye the ſayde counties, whereof one to be of the Quorum, when and what daye the laſte payment of the ſayde ſeuerall miſes, nowe due in any of the ſayde counties ſhall ende and expyre.</p>
               <p>Prouided alſo, that the ſayde graunte of Subſidie, or anye other thinge therein conteyned, doo not in anye wyſe extende to be preiudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall or hurtefull to the inhabitauntes or reſiauntes at thys preſente tyme, within the fyue portes, or to anye of theyr members, incorporate or vnited to the ſame fyue portes, or to anye of the ſame fyue portes, of,
<pb facs="tcp:180783:46"/>or for any parte or percell of the ſayde Sommes graunted in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, of the ſayd inhabitauntes nowe reſiaunt, or any of them, to be taxed, ſet, aſked, leuied, or payde, but the ſayde inhabitauntes and reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auntes in the ſayde fyue portes, and theyr members, be and ſhall be, of, and from the ſayde graunte and paymente of the ſayde ſubſedy during their reſiauncy there, and no lenger, clearlye acquited and diſcharged, any matter or whatſoeuer thinge in this preſente acte had or made to the contrary notwithſtandinge.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>God ſaue the Kynge and the Quene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>Excuſum Londini IN AEDIBVS IOHANNIS <hi>CAVVODI.</hi> Tipographi Regiae Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="privilege">
            <opener>
               <date>
                  <hi>Anno. M.D.LVIII.</hi>
               </date>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad imprimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:180783:46"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
